<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-AU"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-AU" /><updated>2025-09-15T20:47:38+10:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Variant Minds</title><subtitle>Unlock the potential of neurodiverse talent.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work</title><link href="/insights/workabilityexpo2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" /><published>2025-08-08T10:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-09-14T18:25:06+10:00</updated><id>/insights/the-untapped-potential-of-autism-at-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/workabilityexpo2025.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-untapped-potential-of-autism-at-work">The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work</h1><blockquote><p>The following content was presented at the Sydney Workability Expo 2025 on 8<sup>th</sup> August 2025.</p></blockquote><div class="row justify-content-center"><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s01.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s02.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Why it matters" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s03.jpg" /><ul><li>Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) (2024) <i>Autism in Australia, 2022: Key findings in plain language</i>. Canberra: <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/autism-australia-2022">ABS</a>.</li><li>Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) (2025) <i>Labour Force, Australia: June 2025</i>. Canberra: <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/labour/employment-and-unemployment">ABS</a>.</li><li>Financial Times (2024) 'UK employers eye competitive advantage in hiring neurodivergent workers', <i><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/e692c571-b56b-425a-a7a0-3d8ae617080b">Financial Times</a></i>, 18 October.</li><li>Buescher, A., Cidav, Z., Knapp, M. &amp; Mandell, D. (2014) 'Costs of Autism Spectrum Disorders in the United Kingdom and the United States', <i>JAMA Pediatrics</i>, 168(8), pp. 721–728. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.210">DOI: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.210</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Invisible effort" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s04.jpg" /><ul><li>Hull, L., Petrides, K., Allison, C., Smith, P., Baron-Cohen, S., Lai, M. &amp; Mandy, W. (2017) '"Putting on My Best Normal": Social camouflaging in Autistic adults', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 47(8), pp. 2519–2534. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-017-3166-5">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-017-3166-5</a>.</li><li>Lai, M., Lombardo, M., Ruigrok, A., Chakrabarti, B., Auyeung, B. &amp; Bullmore, E.T. (2017) 'Quantifying and exploring camouflaging in men and women with autism', <i>Autism</i>, 21(6), 690-702. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361316671012">DOI: 10.1177/1362361316671012</a>.</li><li>Hull, L., Mandy, W., Lai, M., Baron-Cohen, S., Allison, C., Smith, P. &amp; Petrides, K. (2020) 'Development and Validation of the Camouflaging Autistic Traits Questionnaire (CAT-Q)', <i>Autism Dev Disord</i>, 49, 819-833. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-018-3792-6">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-018-3792-6</a>.</li><li>Cassidy, S., Gould, K., Townsend, E., Pelton, M., Robertson, A. &amp; Rodgers, J. (2020) 'Is Camouflaging Autistic Traits Associated with Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviours? Expanding the Interpersonal Psychological Theory of Suicide in an Undergraduate Student Sample', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 50(10), 3638–3648. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-019-04323-3">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-019-04323-3</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Misread strengths" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s05.jpg" /><ul><li>Milton D. (2012) 'On the ontological status of autism: the "double empathy problem"', <i>Disability &amp; Society</i>, 27(6), 883–887. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/09687599.2012.710008">DOI: 10.1080/09687599.2012.710008</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Hiring glitch" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s06.jpg" /><ul><li>Schmidt, F. &amp; Hunter, J. (1998) 'The validity and utility of selection methods in personnel psychology: practical and theoretical implications of 85 years of research findings', <i>Psychological Bulletin</i>, 124(2), 262–274. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.124.2.262">DOI: 10.1037/0033-2909.124.2.262</a>.</li><li>Hogan, H., Hogan, R. &amp; Kaiser, R. (2009) 'Management derailment: Personality assessment and mitigation', <i>American Psychological Association Handbook of Industrial and Organizational Psychology</i>, 3, 555-575 <a href="https://researchgate.net/publication/292717475_Management_derailment_Personality_assessment_and_mitigation">ResearchGate</a>.</li><li>Gallup (2015) 'State of the American Manager'. (Key statistic quoted in Moscatello, C. (2015) 'There's a good chance your boss should not be a boss', <a href="https://www.glamour.com/story/gallup-managers-report">Glamour</a>). &#8594; Cites <a href="https://www.gallup.com/services/182138/state-american-manager.aspx">Gallup</a> [Paywall]</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Performance trap" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s07.jpg" /><ul><li>Colella, A., DeNisi, A. and Varma, A. (1997) 'Appraising the performance of employees with disabilities: A review and model', <i>Human Resource Management Review</i>, 7(1), 27-54. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S1053-4822(97)90004-8">DOI: 10.1016/S1053-4822(97)90004-8</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Late diagnosis costs" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s08.jpg" /><ul><li>Lilley, R., Lawson, W., Hall, G. et al. (2023) '"Peas in a pod": oral-history reflections on autistic identity by late-diagnosed adults', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 53, 1146–1161. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-022-05667-z">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-022-05667-z</a>.</li><li>Atherton, G., Edisbury, E., Piovesan, A. &amp; Cross, L. (2022) 'Autism Through the Ages: A Mixed Methods Approach to Understanding How Age and Age of Diagnosis Affect Quality of Life', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 52, 3639–3654. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-021-05235-x">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-021-05235-x</a>.</li><li>Brown, C., Newell, V., Sahin, E. &amp; Hedley, D. (2024) 'Updated Systematic Review of Suicide in Autism: 2018–2024', <i>Current Developmental Disorders Reports</i>, 11, 225–256. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40474-024-00308-9">DOI: 10.1007/s40474-024-00308-9</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The business upside" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s09.jpg" /><ul><li>Austin, R.D. and Pisano, G.P. (2017) 'Neurodiversity as a competitive advantage', <i>Harvard Business Review</i>, 95(3), 96–103. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/05/neurodiversity-as-a-competitive-advantage">HBR.org</a></li><li>Deloitte (2020) 'Neurodiversity: The Next Frontier in Talent'. <a href="https://www.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/topics/talent/neurodiversity-in-the-workplace.html">Deloitte Insights</a>.</li><li>Lorenz, T. &amp; Heinitz, K. (2014) 'Aspergers – Different, Not Less: Occupational Strengths and Job Interests of Individuals with Asperger's Syndrome’, <i>PLoS ONE</i>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0100358">DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100358</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Re-imagine recruitment" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s10.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Redesign workspaces" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s11.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Re-write feedback" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s12.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Language matters" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s13.jpg" /><ul><li>Kenny, L., Hattersley, C., Molins, B., Buckley, C., Povey, C. &amp; Pellicano, E. (2016) 'Which terms should be used to describe autism? Perspectives from the UK autism community', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 20(4). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361315588200">DOI: 10.1177/1362361315588200</a>.</li><li>Bury, S., Jellett, R., Spoor, J. &amp; Hedley, D. (2020) '"It Defines Who I Am" or "It's Something I Have": What Language Do [Autistic] Australian Adults [on the Autism Spectrum] Prefer?', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 53(2), 677-687. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-020-04425-3">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-020-04425-3</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Toolkit for allies" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s14.jpg" /><ul><li>CIPD (2022) <i>'Neurodiversity at Work: Guide for People Professionals'</i>. London: <a href="https://www.cipd.org/uk/knowledge/guides/neuroinclusion-work/">Chartered Institute of Personnel and Development</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Let's build neuroinclusive workplaces" src="/assets/img/insights/wexpo_250808_s15.jpg" /></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The content as presented at the Sydney Workability Expo 2025 on 8 August 2025]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/workabilityexpo2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/workabilityexpo2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</title><link href="/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-09-14T18:34:29+10:00</updated><id>/insights/adhd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Caution:</strong><em>The following text is extracted from the ICD-11 definition of Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). It is provided for informational purposes only and should not be used as a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Please note that this summary may not reflect the most up-to-date version of the ICD-11. The official and current listing can be found on the World Health Organization’s website: <a href="https://icd.who.int/browse/2025-01/mms/en#821852937">ICD-11: Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</a>.</em></p></blockquote><h1 id="attention-deficithyperactivity-disorder">Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</h1><blockquote><p>Foundation URI: <a href="http://id.who.int/icd/entity/821852937">http://id.who.int/icd/entity/821852937</a></p></blockquote><p><strong>Code: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05</code></strong></p><h2 id="description">Description</h2><p>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder is characterised by a persistent pattern (at least 6 months) of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity that has a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. There is evidence of significant inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity symptoms prior to age 12, typically by early to mid-childhood, though some individuals may first come to clinical attention later. The degree of inattention and hyperactivity-impulsivity is outside the limits of normal variation expected for age and level of intellectual functioning. Inattention refers to significant difficulty in sustaining attention to tasks that do not provide a high level of stimulation or frequent rewards, distractibility and problems with organisation. Hyperactivity refers to excessive motor activity and difficulties with remaining still, most evident in structured situations that require behavioural self-control. Impulsivity is a tendency to act in response to immediate stimuli, without deliberation or consideration of the risks and consequences. The relative balance and the specific manifestations of inattentive and hyperactive-impulsive characteristics varies across individuals and may change over the course of development. In order for a diagnosis to be made, manifestations of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity must be evident across multiple situations or settings (e.g., home, school, work, with friends or relatives), but are likely to vary according to the structure and demands of the setting. Symptoms are not better accounted for by another mental, behavioural, or neurodevelopmental disorder and are not due to the effect of a substance or medication.</p><h2 id="diagnostic-requirements">Diagnostic Requirements</h2><h3 id="essential-required-features">Essential (Required) Features:</h3><ul><li>A persistent pattern (e.g., at least 6 months) of inattention symptoms and/or a combination of hyperactivity and impulsivity symptoms that is outside the limits of normal variation expected for age and level of intellectual development. Symptoms vary according to chronological age and disorder severity.</li></ul><h3 id="inattention">Inattention</h3><ul><li>Several symptoms of inattention that are persistent, and sufficiently severe that they have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. Symptoms are typically from the following clusters:</li><li>Difficulty sustaining attention to tasks that do not provide a high level of stimulation or reward or require sustained mental effort; lacking attention to detail; making careless mistakes in school or work assignments; not completing tasks.</li><li>Easily distracted by extraneous stimuli or thoughts not related to the task at hand; often does not seem to listen when spoken to directly; frequently appears to be daydreaming or to have mind elsewhere.</li><li>Loses things; is forgetful in daily activities; has difficulty remembering to complete upcoming daily tasks or activities; difficulty planning, managing and organizing schoolwork, tasks and other activities.</li></ul><blockquote><p>Note: Inattention may not be evident when the individual is engaged in activities that provide intense stimulation and frequent rewards.</p></blockquote><h3 id="hyperactivity-impulsivity">Hyperactivity Impulsivity</h3><ul><li>Several symptoms of hyperactivity/impulsivity that are persistent, and sufficiently severe that they have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. These tend to be most evident in structured situations that require behavioural self-control. Symptoms are typically from the following clusters:</li><li>Excessive motor activity; leaves seat when expected to sit still; often runs about; has difficulty sitting still without fidgeting (younger children); feelings of physical restlessness, a sense of discomfort with being quiet or sitting still (adolescents and adults).</li><li>Difficulty engaging in activities quietly; talks too much.</li><li>Blurts out answers in school, comments at work; difficulty waiting turn in conversation, games, or activities; interrupts or intrudes on others conversations or games.</li><li>A tendency to act in response to immediate stimuli without deliberation or consideration of risks and consequences (e.g., engaging in behaviours with potential for physical injury; impulsive decisions; reckless driving)</li><li>Evidence of significant inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity symptoms prior to age 12, though some individuals may first come to clinical attention later in adolescence or as adults, often when demands exceed the individual’s capacity to compensate for limitations.</li><li>Manifestations of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity must be evident across multiple situations or settings (e.g., home, school, work, with friends or relatives), but are likely to vary according to the structure and demands of the setting.</li><li>Symptoms are not better accounted for by another mental disorder (e.g., an Anxiety or Fear-Related Disorder, a Neurocognitive Disorder such as Delirium).</li><li>Symptoms are not due to the effects of a substance (e.g., cocaine) or medication (e.g., bronchodilators, thyroid replacement medication) on the central nervous system, including and withdrawal effects, and are not due to a Disease of the Nervous System.</li></ul><h3 id="specifiers-to-describe-predominant-characteristics-of-clinical-presentation">Specifiers to describe predominant characteristics of clinical presentation:</h3><p>The characteristics of the current clinical presentation should be described using one of the following specifiers, which are meant to assist in recording the main reason for the current referral or services. Predominance of symptoms refers to the presence of several symptoms of either an inattentive or hyperactive/impulsive nature with few or no symptoms of the other type.</p><h4 id="6a050-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-predominantly-inattentive-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.0</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, predominantly inattentive presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and inattentive symptoms predominate.</li></ul><h4 id="6a051-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-predominantly-hyperactive-impulsive-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.1</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, predominantly hyperactive-impulsive presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and symptoms of hyperactivity-impulsivity predominate.</li></ul><h4 id="6a052-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-combined-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.2</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, combined presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and both hyperactive-impulsive and inattentive symptoms are clinically significant aspects of the current clinical presentation, with neither clearly predominating.</li></ul><h3 id="additional-clinical-features">Additional Clinical Features:</h3><ul><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder usually manifests in early or middle childhood. In many cases, hyperactivity symptoms predominate in preschool and decrease with age such that they are no longer prominent beyond adolescence or may instead be reported as feelings of physical restlessness. Attentional problems may be more commonly observed beginning in later childhood, especially in school and in adults in occupational settings.</li><li>The manifestations and severity of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often vary according to the characteristics and demands of the environment. Symptoms and behaviours should be evaluated across multiple types of environments as a part of clinical assessment.</li><li>Where available, teacher and parent reports should be obtained to establish the diagnosis in children and adolescents. In adults, the report of a significant other, family member, or co-worker can provide important additional information.</li><li>Some individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder may first present for services in adulthood. When making the diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in adults, a history of inattention, hyperactivity, or impulsivity before age 12 is an important corroborating feature that can be best established from school or local records, or from informants who knew the individual during childhood. In the absence of such corroborating information, a diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in older adolescents and adults should be made with caution.</li><li>In a subset of individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, especially in children, an exclusively inattentive presentation may occur. There is no hyperactivity and the presentation is characterized by daydreaming, mind-wandering, and a lack of focus. These children are sometimes referred to as exhibiting a restrictive inattentive pattern of symptoms or sluggish cognitive tempo.</li><li>In a subset of individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, combined presentation, severe inattentiveness and hyperactivity-impulsivity are both consistently present in most of the situations that an individual encounters, and are also evidenced by the clinician’s own observations. This pattern is often referred to as hyperkinetic disorder and is considered a more severe form of the disorder.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms often significantly limit academic achievement. Adults with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often find it difficult to hold down a demanding job and may be disproportionately underemployed or unemployed. Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder can also strain interpersonal relationships across the life span including those with family members, peers, and romantic partners. Individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often have greater difficulty regulating their behaviour in the context of groups than in one-on-one situations.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often co-occurs with other Neurodevelopmental Disorders, including Developmental Speech or Language Disorders, and Primary Tics or Tic Disorders, which are classified in the Chapter on Diseases of the Nervous System but cross-listed under Neurodevelopment Disorders. Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is associated with an increased risk of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder and with elevated rates of epilepsy. Emotional dysregulation, low frustration tolerance, and subtle clumsiness and other minor (‘soft’) neurological abnormalities in sensory and motor performance in the absence of any identifiable brain pathology are also common in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is associated with an increased risk for physical health problems including accidents.</li><li>Acute onset of hyperactive behaviour in a school-age child or adolescent should raise the possibility that symptoms are better accounted for by another mental disorder or by a medical condition. For example, abrupt onset of hyperactivity in adolescence or adulthood may indicate an emergent Primary Psychotic or Bipolar Disorder.</li><li>Although Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder tends to run in families with evidence of high heritability, the predominant symptom pattern in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in a given individual often changes over time and cannot be predicted based on the predominant symptoms of other family members.</li></ul><h3 id="boundary-with-normality-threshold">Boundary with Normality (Threshold):</h3><ul><li>Inattention, hyperactivity and impulsivity symptoms are present in many children, adolescents and adults, especially during certain developmental periods (e.g., early childhood). The diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder requires that these symptoms be persistent across time, pervasive across situations, significantly out of keeping with developmental level, and have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning.</li></ul><h3 id="course-features">Course Features:</h3><ul><li>Nearly half of all children diagnosed with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder will continue to exhibit symptoms into adolescence. Predictors of persistence into adolescence and adulthood include: co-occurring childhood onset Mental, Behavioural or Neurodevelopmental Disorders, lower intellectual functioning, poorer social functioning, and behavioural problems.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms tend to remain stable throughout adolescence with approximately one third of individuals diagnosed in childhood continuing to experience impairment in adulthood.</li><li>Although symptoms of hyperactivity become less overt during adolescence and adulthood, individuals may still experience difficulties with inattention, impulsivity, and restlessness.</li></ul><h3 id="developmental-presentations">Developmental Presentations:</h3><ul><li>Adolescents and adults may only seek clinical services after age 12 once symptoms become more limiting with increasing social, emotional, and academic demands or in the context of an evolving co-occurring Mental, Behavioural, or Neurodevelopmental Disorders that results in an exacerbation of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms.</li></ul><h3 id="culture-related-features">Culture-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>The symptoms of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder consistently fall into two separate dimensions across cultures: inattention and hyperactivity/impulsivity. However, culture can influence acceptability of symptoms as well as how caregivers respond to them.</li><li>The assessment of hyperactivity should take into account cultural norms of age and gender-appropriate behaviour. For example, in some countries hyperactive behaviour may be seen as a sign of strength in a boy (e.g., ‘boiling blood’) while being perceived very negatively in a girl.</li><li>Symptoms of inattention or hyperactivity/impulsivity may occur in response to exposure to traumatic events and grief reactions during childhood particularly in highly vulnerable and disadvantaged populations, including in post-conflict areas. In these settings, clinicians should consider whether the diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is warranted.</li></ul><h3 id="sex--andor-gender-related-features">Sex- and/or Gender-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is more common in males.</li><li>Females are more likely to exhibit inattentive symptoms whereas males are more likely to exhibit symptoms of hyperactivity and impulsivity particularly at younger ages.</li></ul>]]></content><author><name>World Health Organisation (WHO)</name></author><category term="ADHD," /><category term="Diagnostic," /><category term="Reference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ICD-11 entry for Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)</title><link href="/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-09-14T18:34:29+10:00</updated><id>/insights/asd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Caution:</strong><em>The following text is extracted from the ICD-11 definition of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). It is provided for informational purposes only and should not be used as a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Please note that this summary may not reflect the most up-to-date version of the ICD-11. The official and current listing can be found on the World Health Organization’s website: <a href="https://icd.who.int/browse/2025-01/mms/en#437815624">ICD-11: Autism Spectrum Disorder</a>.</em></p></blockquote><h1 id="autism-spectrum-disorder">Autism Spectrum Disorder</h1><blockquote><p>Foundation URI: <a href="http://id.who.int/icd/entity/437815624">http://id.who.int/icd/entity/437815624</a></p></blockquote><p><strong>Code: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02</code></strong></p><h2 id="description">Description</h2><p>Autism spectrum disorder is characterised by persistent deficits in the ability to initiate and to sustain reciprocal social interaction and social communication, and by a range of restricted, repetitive, and inflexible patterns of behaviour, interests or activities that are clearly atypical or excessive for the individual’s age and sociocultural context. The onset of the disorder occurs during the developmental period, typically in early childhood, but symptoms may not become fully manifest until later, when social demands exceed limited capacities. Deficits are sufficiently severe to cause impairment in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other important areas of functioning and are usually a pervasive feature of the individual’s functioning observable in all settings, although they may vary according to social, educational, or other context. Individuals along the spectrum exhibit a full range of intellectual functioning and language abilities.</p><h2 id="diagnostic-requirements">Diagnostic Requirements</h2><h3 id="essential-required-features">Essential (Required) Features:</h3><ul><li>Persistent deficits in initiating and sustaining social communication and reciprocal social interactions that are outside the expected range of typical functioning given the individual’s age and level of intellectual development. Specific manifestations of these deficits vary according to chronological age, verbal and intellectual ability, and disorder severity. Manifestations may include limitations in the following:</li><li>Understanding of, interest in, or inappropriate responses to the verbal or non-verbal social communications of others.</li><li>Integration of spoken language with typical complimentary non-verbal cues, such as eye contact, gestures, facial expressions and body language. These non-verbal behaviours may also be reduced in frequency or intensity.</li><li>Understanding and use of language in social contexts and ability to initiate and sustain reciprocal social conversations.</li><li>Social awareness, leading to behaviour that is not appropriately modulated according to the social context.</li><li>Ability to imagine and respond to the feelings, emotional states, and attitudes of others.</li><li>Mutual sharing of interests.</li><li>Ability to make and sustain typical peer relationships.</li><li>Persistent restricted, repetitive, and inflexible patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities that are clearly atypical or excessive for the individual’s age and sociocultural context. These may include:</li><li>Lack of adaptability to new experiences and circumstances, with associated distress, that can be evoked by trivial changes to a familiar environment or in response to unanticipated events.</li><li>Inflexible adherence to particular routines; for example, these may be geographic such as following familiar routes, or may require precise timing such as mealtimes or transport.</li><li>Excessive adherence to rules (e.g., when playing games).</li><li>Excessive and persistent ritualized patterns of behaviour (e.g., preoccupation with lining up or sorting objects in a particular way) that serve no apparent external purpose.</li><li>Repetitive and stereotyped motor movements, such as whole body movements (e.g., rocking), atypical gait (e.g., walking on tiptoes), unusual hand or finger movements and posturing. These behaviours are particularly common during early childhood.</li><li>Persistent preoccupation with one or more special interests, parts of objects, or specific types of stimuli (including media) or an unusually strong attachment to particular objects (excluding typical comforters).</li><li>Lifelong excessive and persistent hypersensitivity or hyposensitivity to sensory stimuli or unusual interest in a sensory stimulus, which may include actual or anticipated sounds, light, textures (especially clothing and food), odors and tastes, heat, cold, or pain.</li><li>The onset of the disorder occurs during the developmental period, typically in early childhood, but characteristic symptoms may not become fully manifest until later, when social demands exceed limited capacities.</li><li>The symptoms result in significant impairment in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other important areas of functioning. Some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder are able to function adequately in many contexts through exceptional effort, such that their deficits may not be apparent to others. A diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder is still appropriate in such cases.</li></ul><h3 id="specifiers-for-characterizing-features-within-the-autism-spectrum">Specifiers for characterizing features within the Autism Spectrum:</h3><p>These specifiers enable the identification of co-occurring limitations in intellectual and functional language abilities, which are important factors in the appropriate individualization of support, selection of interventions, and treatment planning for individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder. A qualifier is also provided for loss of previously acquired skills, which is a feature of the developmental history of a small proportion of individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder.</p><h4 id="co-occurring-disorder-of-intellectual-development">Co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development</h4><p>Individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder may exhibit limitations in intellectual abilities. If present, a separate diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development should be assigned, using the appropriate category to designate severity (i.e., Mild, Moderate, Severe, Profound, Provisional). Because social deficits are a core feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder, the assessment of adaptive behaviour as a part of the diagnosis of a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development should place greater emphasis on the intellectual, conceptual, and practical domains of adaptive functioning than on social skills.</p><p>If no co-occurring diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development is present, the following qualifier for the Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis should be applied:</p><ul><li>without Disorder of Intellectual Development</li></ul><p>If there is a co-occurring diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development, the following qualifier for the Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis should be applied, in addition to the appropriate diagnostic code for the co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development:</p><ul><li>with Disorder of Intellectual Development</li></ul><h4 id="degree-of-functional-language-impairment">Degree of Functional Language Impairment</h4><p>The degree of impairment in functional language (spoken or signed) should be designated with a second qualifier. Functional language refers to the capacity of the individual to use language for instrumental purposes (e.g., to express personal needs and desires). This qualifier is intended to reflect primarily the verbal and non-verbal expressive language deficits present in some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder and not the pragmatic language deficits that are a core feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</p><p>The following qualifier should be applied to indicate the extent of functional language impairment (spoken or signed) relative to the individual’s age:</p><ul><li>with mild or no impairment of functional language</li><li>with impaired functional language (i.e., not able to use more than single words or simple phrases)</li><li>with complete, or almost complete, absence of functional language</li></ul><h5 id="table-65-diagnostic-codes-for-autism-spectrum-disorder">Table 6.5 Diagnostic Codes for Autism Spectrum Disorder</h5><table><thead><tr><th></th><th style="text-align: center">with mild or no impairment of functional language</th><th style="text-align: center">with impaired functional language</th><th style="text-align: center">with complete, or almost complete, absence of functional language</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>without Disorder of Intellectual Development</td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.0</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.2</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><em>-</em></td></tr><tr><td>with Disorder of Intellectual Development</td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.1</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.3</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.5</code></td></tr></tbody></table><p><br />
Table 6.5 shows the diagnostic codes corresponding to the categories that result from the application of the specifiers for Co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development and Degree of Functional Language Impairment.</p><blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Note:</strong><em>The ICD-11 and DSM-5 classify Autism Spectrum Disorder differently. The ICD-11 <strong>uses diagnostic codes with specifiers</strong>, while the DSM-5 <strong>emphasises support levels</strong>.</em></p><p><br /><em>In the DSM-5, criteria span two domains:</em></p><ul><li><em>Social Communication:</em> Persistent deficits in social communication and interaction</li><li><em><abbr data-bs-toggle="tooltip" title="Restricted and Repetitive Behaviours">RRBs</abbr>:</em> Restricted, repetitive patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities</li></ul><p><em>Each domain is rated according to support needs:</em></p><ul><li><em>Level 1:</em> Requiring support</li><li><em>Level 2:</em> Requiring substantial support</li><li><em>Level 3:</em> Requiring very substantial support</li></ul></blockquote><h4 id="loss-of-previously-acquired-skills">Loss of Previously Acquired Skills</h4><p>A small proportion of individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder may present with a loss of previously acquired skills. This regression typically occurs during the second year of life and most often involves language use and social responsiveness. Loss of previously acquired skills is rarely observed after 3 years of age. If it occurs after age 3, it is more likely to involve loss of cognitive and adaptive skills (e.g., loss of bowel and bladder control, impaired sleep), regression of language and social abilities, as well as increasing emotional and behavioural disturbances.</p><p>There are two alternative specifiers, to denote whether or not loss of previously acquired skills is an aspect of the clinical history, where x corresponds to the final digit shown in Table 6.5:</p><h3 id="additional-clinical-features">Additional Clinical Features:</h3><ul><li>Common symptom presentations of Autism Spectrum Disorder in young children are parental or caregiver concerns about intellectual or other developmental delays (e.g., problems in language and motor coordination). When there is no significant impairment of intellectual functioning, clinical services may only be sought later (e.g., due to behaviour or social problems when starting school). In middle childhood, there may be prominent symptoms of anxiety, including Social Anxiety Disorder, school refusal, and Specific Phobia. During adolescence and adulthood, Depressive Disorders are often a presenting feature.</li><li>Co-occurrence of Autism Spectrum Disorder with other Mental, Behavioural or Neurodevelopmental Disorders is common across the lifespan. In a substantial proportion of cases, particularly in adolescence and adulthood, it is a co-occurring disorder that first brings an individual with Autism Spectrum Disorder to clinical attention.</li><li>Pragmatic language difficulties may manifest as an overly literal understanding of others’ speech, speech that lacks normal prosody and emotional tone and therefore appears monotonous, lack of awareness of the appropriateness of their choice of language in particular social contexts, or pedantic precision in the use of language.</li><li>Social naiveté, especially during adolescence, can lead to exploitation by others, a risk that may be enhanced by the use of social media without adequate supervision.</li><li>Profiles of specific cognitive skills in Autism Spectrum Disorder as measured by standardized assessments may show striking and unusual patterns of strengths and weaknesses that are highly variable from individual to individual. These deficits can affect learning and adaptive functioning to a greater extent than would be predicted from the overall scores on measures of verbal and non-verbal intelligence.</li><li>Self-injurious behaviours (e.g., hitting one’s face, head banging) occur more often in individuals with co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development.</li><li>Some young individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, especially those with a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development, develop epilepsy or seizures during early childhood with a second increase in prevalence during adolescence. Catatonic states have also been described. A number of medical disorders such as Tuberous Sclerosis, chromosomal abnormalities including Fragile X Syndrome, Cerebral Palsy, early onset epileptic encephalopathies, and Neurofibromatosis are associated with Autism Spectrum Disorder with or without a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development. Genomic deletions, duplications and other genetic abnormalities are increasingly described in individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, some of which may be important for genetic counselling. Prenatal exposure to valproate is also associated with an increased risk of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li><li>Some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder are capable of functioning adequately by making an exceptional effort to compensate for their symptoms during childhood, adolescence or adulthood. Such sustained effort, which may be more typical of affected females, can have a deleterious impact on mental health and well-being.</li></ul><h3 id="boundary-with-normality-threshold">Boundary with Normality (Threshold):</h3><ul><li><strong>Social interaction skills:</strong> Typically developing individuals vary in the pace and extent to which they acquire and master skills of reciprocal social interaction and social communication. A diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder should only be considered if there is marked and persistent deviation from the expected range of abilities and behaviours in these domains given the individual’s age, level of intellectual functioning, and sociocultural context. Some individuals may exhibit limited social interaction due to shyness (i.e., feelings of awkwardness or fear in new situations or with unfamiliar people) or behavioural inhibition (i.e., being slow to approach or to ‘warm up’ to new people and situations). Limited social interactions in shy or behaviourally inhibited children, adolescents, or adults are not indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder. Shyness is differentiated from Autism Spectrum Disorder by evidence of adequate social communication behaviours in familiar situations.</li><li><strong>Social communication skills:</strong> Children vary widely in the age at which they first acquire spoken language and the pace at which their speech and language become firmly established. Most children with early language delay eventually acquire similar language skills as their same-age peers. Early language delay alone is not strongly indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder unless there is also evidence of limited motivation for social communication and limited interaction skills. An essential feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder is persistent impairment in the ability to understand and use language appropriately for social communication.</li><li><strong>Repetitive and stereotyped behaviours:</strong> Many children go through phases of repetitive play and highly focused interests as a part of typical development. Unless there is also evidence of impaired reciprocal social interaction and social communication, patterns of behaviour characterized by repetition, routine, or restricted interests are not by themselves indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li></ul><h3 id="course-features">Course Features:</h3><ul><li>Although Autism Spectrum Disorder can present clinically at all ages, including during adulthood, it is a lifelong disorder the manifestations and impact of which are likely to vary according to age, intellectual and language abilities, co-occurring conditions and environmental context.</li><li>Restricted and repetitive behaviours persist over time. Specifically, repetitive sensorimotor behaviours appear to be common, consistent, and potentially severe. During the school age years and adolescence, these repetitive sensorimotor behaviours begin to lessen in intensity and number. Insistence on sameness, which is less prevalent, appears to develop during preschool and worsen over time.</li></ul><h3 id="developmental-presentations">Developmental Presentations:</h3><ul><li><em>Infancy:</em> Characteristic features may emerge during infancy although they may only be recognized as indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder in retrospect. It is usually possible to make the diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder during the preschool period (up to 4 years), especially in children exhibiting generalized developmental delay. Plateauing of social communication and language skills and failure to progress in their development is not uncommon. The loss of early words and social responsiveness, i.e., a true regression, with an onset between 1 and 2 years, is unusual but significant and rarely occurs after the third year of life. In these cases, the qualifier ‘with loss of previously acquired skills’ should be applied.</li><li><em>Preschool:</em> In preschool children, indicators of an Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis often include avoidance of mutual eye contact, resistance to physical affection, a lack of social imaginary play, language that is delayed in onset or is precocious but not used for social conversation; social withdrawal, obsessive or repetitive preoccupations, and a lack of social interaction with peers characterized by parallel play or disinterest. Sensory sensitivities to everyday sounds, or to foods, may overshadow the underlying social communication deficits.</li><li><em>Middle Childhood:</em> In children with Autism Spectrum Disorder without a Disorder of Intellectual Development, social adjustment difficulties outside the home may not be detected until school entry or adolescence when social communication problems lead to social isolation from peers. Resistance to engage in unfamiliar experiences and marked reactions to even minor change in routines are typical. Furthermore, excessive focus on detail as well as rigidity of behaviour and thinking may be significant. Symptoms of anxiety may become evident at this stage of development.</li><li><em>Adolescence:</em> By adolescence, the capacity to cope with increasing social complexity in peer relationships at a time of increasingly demanding academic expectations is often overwhelmed. In some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, the underlying social communication deficits may be overshadowed by the symptoms of co-occurring Mental and Behavioural Disorders. Depressive symptoms are often a presenting feature</li><li><em>Adulthood:</em> In adulthood, the capacity for those with Autism Spectrum Disorder to cope with social relationships can become increasingly challenged, and clinical presentation may occur when social demands overwhelm the capacity to compensate. Presenting problems in adulthood may represent reactions to social isolation or the social consequences of inappropriate behaviour. Compensation strategies may be sufficient to sustain dyadic relationships, but are usually inadequate in social groups. Special interests, and focused attention, may benefit some individuals in education and employment. Work environments may have to be tailored to the capacities of the individual. A first diagnosis in adulthood may be precipitated by a breakdown in domestic or work relationships. In Autism Spectrum Disorder there is always a history of early childhood social communication and relationship difficulties, although this may only be apparent in retrospect.</li></ul><h3 id="culture-related-features">Culture-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Cultural variation exists in norms of social communication, reciprocal social interactions, as well as interests and activities. Therefore, signs of impairment in functioning may differ depending on cultural context. For example, in some societies it may be normative for children may avoid direct eye contact out of deference, which should not be misinterpreted as impairment in social interaction.</li></ul><h3 id="sex--andor-gender-related-features">Sex- and/or Gender-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Males are four times more likely than females to be diagnosed with Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li><li>Females diagnosed with Autism Spectrum Disorder are more frequently diagnosed with co-occurring Disorders of Intellectual Development, suggesting that less severe presentations may go undetected as compared to males. Females tend to demonstrate fewer restricted, repetitive interests and behaviours than males.</li><li>During middle-childhood, gender differences in presentation differentially affect functioning. Boys may act out with reactive aggression or other behavioural symptoms when challenged or frustrated. Girls tend to withdraw socially, and react with emotional changes to their social adjustment difficulties.</li></ul>]]></content><author><name>World Health Organisation (WHO)</name></author><category term="Autism," /><category term="ASD," /><category term="Diagnostic," /><category term="Reference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ICD-11 entry for Autism Spectrum Disorder.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Mourn for Us</title><link href="/jim_sinclair_dont_mourn_for_us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Mourn for Us" /><published>1993-03-01T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-09-14T18:34:29+10:00</updated><id>/dont-mourn-for-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jim_sinclair_dont_mourn_for_us.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="dont-mourn-for-us">Don’t Mourn for Us</h1><p><strong>by Jim Sinclair</strong><br /><em>Extracted from <a href="https://www.autreat.com/dont_mourn.html">https://www.autreat.com/dont_mourn.html</a></em>.</p><blockquote><p><em>[This article was published in the Autism Network International newsletter, Our Voice, Volume 1, Number 3, 1993. It is an outline of the presentation Jim gave at the 1993 International Conference on Autism in Toronto, and is addressed primarily to parents.]</em></p></blockquote><p>Parents often report that learning their child is autistic was the most traumatic thing that ever happened to them. Non-autistic people see autism as a great tragedy, and parents experience continuing disappointment and grief at all stages of the child’s and family’s life cycle.
But this grief does not stem from the child’s autism in itself. It is grief over the loss of the normal child the parents had hoped and expected to have. Parents’ attitudes and expectations, and the discrepancies between what parents expect of children at a particular age and their own child’s actual development, cause more stress and anguish than the practical complexities of life with an autistic person.</p><p>Some amount of grief is natural as parents adjust to the fact that an event and a relationship they’ve been looking forward to isn’t going to materialize. But this grief over a fantasized normal child needs to be separated from the parents’ perceptions of the child they do have: the autistic child who needs the support of adult caretakers and who can form very meaningful relationships with those caretakers if given the opportunity. Continuing focus on the child’s autism as a source of grief is damaging for both the parents and the child, and precludes the development of an accepting and authentic relationship between them. For their own sake and for the sake of their children, I urge parents to make radical changes in their perceptions of what autism means.</p><p>I invite you to look at our autism, and look at your grief, from our perspective:</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-an-appendage">Autism is not an appendage</h5><p>Autism isn’t something a person has, or a “shell” that a person is trapped inside. There’s no normal child hidden behind the autism. Autism is a way of being. It is pervasive; it colors every experience, every sensation, perception, thought, emotion, and encounter, every aspect of existence. It is not possible to separate the autism from the person–and if it were possible, the person you’d have left would not be the same person you started with.</p><p>This is important, so take a moment to consider it: Autism is a way of being. It is not possible to separate the person from the autism.</p><p>Therefore, when parents say,</p><blockquote><p>I wish my child did not have autism,</p></blockquote><p>what they’re really saying is,</p><blockquote><p>I wish the autistic child I have did not exist, and I had a different (non-autistic) child instead.</p></blockquote><p>Read that again. This is what we hear when you mourn over our existence. This is what we hear when you pray for a cure. This is what we know, when you tell us of your fondest hopes and dreams for us: that your greatest wish is that one day we will cease to be, and strangers you can love will move in behind our faces.</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-an-impenetrable-wall">Autism is not an impenetrable wall</h5><p>You try to relate to your autistic child, and the child doesn’t respond. He doesn’t see you; you can’t reach her; there’s no getting through. That’s the hardest thing to deal with, isn’t it? The only thing is, it isn’t true.</p><p>Look at it again: You try to relate as parent to child, using your own understanding of normal children, your own feelings about parenthood, your own experiences and intuitions about relationships. And the child doesn’t respond in any way you can recognize as being part of that system.</p><p>That does not mean the child is incapable of relating at all. It only means you’re assuming a shared system, a shared understanding of signals and meanings, that the child in fact does not share. It’s as if you tried to have an intimate conversation with someone who has no comprehension of your language. Of course the person won’t understand what you’re talking about, won’t respond in the way you expect, and may well find the whole interaction confusing and unpleasant.</p><p>It takes more work to communicate with someone whose native language isn’t the same as yours. And autism goes deeper than language and culture; autistic people are “foreigners” in any society. You’re going to have to give up your assumptions about shared meanings. You’re going to have to learn to back up to levels more basic than you’ve probably thought about before, to translate, and to check to make sure your translations are understood. You’re going to have to give up the certainty that comes of being on your own familiar territory, of knowing you’re in charge, and let your child teach you a little of her language, guide you a little way into his world.</p><p>And the outcome, if you succeed, still will not be a normal parent-child relationship. Your autistic child may learn to talk, may attend regular classes in school, may go to college, drive a car, live independently, have a career–but will never relate to you as other children relate to their parents. Or your autistic child may never speak, may graduate from a self-contained special education classroom to a sheltered activity program or a residential facility, may need lifelong full-time care and supervision–but is not completely beyond your reach. The ways we relate are different. Push for the things your expectations tell you are normal, and you’ll find frustration, disappointment, resentment, maybe even rage and hatred. Approach respectfully, without preconceptions, and with openness to learning new things, and you’ll find a world you could never have imagined.</p><p>Yes, that takes more work than relating to a non-autistic person. But it can be done–unless non-autistic people are far more limited than we are in their capacity to relate. We spend our entire lives doing it. Each of us who does learn to talk to you, each of us who manages to function at all in your society, each of us who manages to reach out and make a connection with you, is operating in alien territory, making contact with alien beings. We spend our entire lives doing this. And then you tell us that we can’t relate.</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-death">Autism is not death</h5><p>Granted, autism isn’t what most parents expect or look forward to when they anticipate the arrival of a child. What they expect is a child who will be like them, who will share their world and relate to them without requiring intensive on-the-job training in alien contact. Even if their child has some disability other than autism, parents expect to be able to relate to that child on the terms that seem normal to them; and in most cases, even allowing for the limitations of various disabilities, it is possible to form the kind of bond the parents had been looking forward to.</p><p>But not when the child is autistic. Much of the grieving parents do is over the non-occurrence of the expected relationship with an expected normal child. This grief is very real, and it needs to be expected and worked through so people can get on with their lives–</p><p>but it has nothing to do with autism.</p><p>What it comes down to is that you expected something that was tremendously important to you, and you looked forward to it with great joy and excitement, and maybe for a while you thought you actually had it–and then, perhaps gradually, perhaps abruptly, you had to recognize that the thing you looked forward to hasn’t happened. It isn’t going to happen. No matter how many other, normal children you have, nothing will change the fact that this time, the child you waited and hoped and planned and dreamed for didn’t arrive.</p><p>This is the same thing that parents experience when a child is stillborn, or when they have their baby to hold for a short time, only to have it die in infancy. It isn’t about autism, it’s about shattered expectations. I suggest that the best place to address these issues is not in organizations devoted to autism, but in parental bereavement counseling and support groups. In those settings parents learn to come to terms with their loss–not to forget about it, but to let it be in the past, where the grief doesn’t hit them in the face every waking moment of their lives. They learn to accept that their child is gone, forever, and won’t be coming back. Most importantly, they learn not to take out their grief for the lost child on their surviving children. This is of critical importance when one of those surviving children arrived at t time the child being mourned for died.</p><p>You didn’t lose a child to autism. You lost a child because the child you waited for never came into existence. That isn’t the fault of the autistic child who does exist, and it shouldn’t be our burden. We need and deserve families who can see us and value us for ourselves, not families whose vision of us is obscured by the ghosts of children who never lived. Grieve if you must, for your own lost dreams. But don’t mourn for us. We are alive. We are real. And we’re here waiting for you.</p><p>This is what I think autism societies should be about: not mourning for what never was, but exploration of what is. We need you. We need your help and your understanding. Your world is not very open to us, and we won’t make it without your strong support. Yes, there is tragedy that comes with autism: not because of what we are, but because of the things that happen to us. Be sad about that, if you want to be sad about something. Better than being sad about it, though, get mad about it–and then do something about it. The tragedy is not that we’re here, but that your world has no place for us to be. How can it be otherwise, as long as our own parents are still grieving over having brought us into the world?</p><p>Take a look at your autistic child sometime, and take a moment to tell yourself who that child is not. Think to yourself: “This is not my child that I expected and planned for. This is not the child I waited for through all those months of pregnancy and all those hours of labor. This is not the child I made all those plans to share all those experiences with. That child never came. This is not that child.” Then go do whatever grieving you have to do–away from the autistic child–and start learning to let go.</p><p>After you’ve started that letting go, come back and look at your autistic child again, and say to yourself: “This is not my child that I expected and planned for. This is an alien child who landed in my life by accident. I don’t know who this child is or what it will become. But I know it’s a child, stranded in an alien world, without parents of its own kind to care for it. It needs someone to care for it, to teach it, to interpret and to advocate for it. And because this alien child happened to drop into my life, that job is mine if I want it.”</p><p>If that prospect excites you, then come join us, in strength and determination, in hope and in joy. The adventure of a lifetime is ahead of you.</p><p><em>– Jim Sinclair.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Jim Sinclair</name></author><category term="Autism," /><category term="ASD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are frequently asked why we decided to support neurodiversity. This speech is one of the answers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/jim_sinclair.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/jim_sinclair.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>