<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-AU"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-AU" /><updated>2026-01-11T11:50:00+11:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Variant Minds</title><subtitle>Unlock the potential of neurodiverse talent.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Loving Varinat Minds 🡢 Chapter 1</title><link href="/insights/lvm_chapter_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Loving Varinat Minds 🡢 Chapter 1" /><published>2025-12-10T20:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-12-30T13:38:04+11:00</updated><id>/insights/lvm-chapter-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/lvm_chapter_1.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The following is Chapter One from the book <a href="/books/lvm/"><strong>Loving Variant Minds: How to Navigate Love After a Late Neurodivergence Diagnosis</strong></a>.</p><p>Available on <a href="https://c1k.it/alvm">Apple Books</a> and <a href="https://c1k.it/klvm">Kindle</a>.</p></blockquote><h1 id="chapter-1-what-is-neurodivergence">Chapter 1: What Is Neurodivergence?</h1><h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2><p>If you have picked up this book, chances are something in your life has shifted. Perhaps you have just received a diagnosis that finally puts a name to a lifetime of feeling different. Perhaps your partner has, and you are trying to understand what this means for your relationship. Or perhaps you are simply searching for answers - a reason why things that seem effortless for others have always felt impossibly hard for you, or why the person you love sometimes feels like they are operating from an entirely different rulebook.</p><p>You are not imagining it. They are.</p><p>The human brain is not a single, standardised design. It comes in countless variations, each with its own way of processing information, experiencing emotions, and navigating the world. For most of history, we have treated one particular style of brain - the most common one - as “normal,” and measured everyone else against it. Those who fell outside this narrow band were labelled as broken, difficult, or defective. They were told to try harder, to stop being so sensitive, to just pay attention, to act their age.</p><p>This book is built on a different premise: that neurological difference is not a flaw to be fixed, but a reality to be understood. That the struggles many neurodivergent people face are not purely internal failures but often arise from a world designed without them in mind. And that relationships - particularly intimate ones - can not only survive these differences but genuinely thrive when both partners learn to see each other clearly.</p><p>But I will not pretend this is easy. Understanding neurodivergence requires unlearning much of what society has taught us about how people “should” think, feel, and behave. It asks us to sit with discomfort, to challenge assumptions, and to extend compassion - both to others and to ourselves. If you are a neurodivergent person, this book will ask you to examine patterns you may have spent a lifetime trying to hide. If you love someone who is neurodivergent, it will ask you to resist the temptation to interpret their behaviour through a neurotypical lens.</p><p>The reward for this effort is profound: genuine connection, built not on the brittle foundation of who we think our partners should be, but on the solid ground of who they actually are.</p><p>Let us begin by understanding what we mean when we talk about neurodivergence - and why getting the language right matters more than you might think.</p><h2 id="defining-neurodivergence-vs-neurodiversity">Defining Neurodivergence vs Neurodiversity</h2><p>These two terms are often used interchangeably, but they mean quite different things. Understanding the distinction is more than academic - it shapes how we think about ourselves, our partners, and our place in the world.</p><p><strong>Neurodiversity</strong> is a biological fact. It refers to the natural variation in human brains and nervous systems across our entire species. Just as biodiversity describes the range of life forms in an ecosystem, neurodiversity describes the range of neurological configurations in the human population. It is not a condition, a diagnosis, or a movement. It simply <em>is</em>. Every human being - regardless of whether they have a diagnosis of anything - is part of neurodiversity, in the same way that every person is part of human genetic diversity.</p><p>The term was coined in 1998 by Australian sociologist Judy Singer, who is herself autistic. In her honours thesis, she argued that neurological differences should be recognised and respected as a natural form of human variation, rather than pathologised as disorders to be cured <sup id="fnref:656"><a href="#fn:656" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. This was a radical idea at the time, emerging alongside the disability rights movement and challenging centuries of medical thinking that positioned atypical brains as fundamentally broken.</p><p><strong>Neurodivergent</strong>, by contrast, describes an individual. A person is neurodivergent if their brain functions in ways that diverge significantly from what society considers “typical” or “normal.” This includes people with autism, ADHD, dyslexia, dyspraxia, dyscalculia, Tourette syndrome, and a range of other neurological differences. Some definitions also include acquired neurodivergence - differences that arise from brain injury, trauma, or illness rather than developmental variation.</p><p>The counterpart to neurodivergent is <strong>neurotypical</strong> - a term describing people whose neurological development and functioning fall within the ranges that society considers standard. Neurotypical is not a compliment or an insult; it is simply a descriptor. It acknowledges that there is a dominant neurological style that shapes most of our social norms, workplace expectations, educational structures, and relationship templates.</p><p>Here is where it gets personal. If you are reading this book because you or your partner has been diagnosed with ADHD or autism, you are likely grappling with what it means to be neurodivergent in a neurotypical world. The challenges you face are real - but they are not solely the product of a “disordered” brain. They emerge from the interaction between your neurology and an environment that was not designed for you.</p><p>Think of it this way: a person who uses a wheelchair is not disabled by their body alone. They are disabled by stairs, by narrow doorways, by buildings without lifts. Their impairment becomes a disability only when the environment fails to accommodate it. The same principle applies to neurodivergence. An autistic person is not disabled by their autism in a quiet, predictable environment with clear expectations and respectful communication. They become disabled when forced into noisy open-plan offices, ambiguous social situations, and workplaces that punish direct communication as “rude.”</p><p>This is not to minimise the genuine difficulties that come with being neurodivergent. Executive dysfunction, sensory overload, emotional dysregulation, and social communication differences can be profoundly challenging regardless of environment. But it does invite us to ask a different question. Instead of asking “What is wrong with this person?”, we might ask “What does this person need to thrive?”</p><p>The neurodiversity paradigm does not deny that neurodivergent people may need support, treatment, or accommodations. It does not claim that ADHD and autism are merely “differences” with no associated struggles. What it does is reframe the conversation. It positions neurological variation as part of human diversity rather than a collection of deficits to be eliminated. It insists that neurodivergent people have inherent worth and value, not despite their neurology but inclusive of it.</p><p>For relationships, this reframing is transformative. When we stop seeing our neurodivergent partners as broken neurotypicals who need to be fixed, we can begin to see them as they are: people with a different operating system, facing genuine challenges, bringing genuine strengths, and deserving of genuine understanding.</p><p>This does not mean that anything goes - that neurodivergence excuses all behaviour or that partners must simply accept whatever happens. Chapter 14 of this book addresses accountability directly. But it does mean that we start from a place of curiosity rather than judgment, seeking first to understand before we evaluate.</p><p>One more clarification: <strong>the neurodiversity movement</strong> refers to the social and political advocacy that has grown from Singer’s original concept. This movement campaigns for the rights, acceptance, and inclusion of neurodivergent people. It pushes back against treatments aimed at making neurodivergent people appear “normal” rather than helping them live well. It argues for accommodations in schools and workplaces, for an end to stigma, and for neurodivergent voices to be centred in conversations about neurodivergence.</p><p>You do not have to align yourself with every position of the neurodiversity movement to benefit from this book. But understanding that this movement exists - and why it exists - helps explain the passion and sometimes defensiveness you may encounter in neurodivergent communities. These are people who have spent their lives being told they are the problem. The insistence on respect and acceptance is not oversensitivity. It is a hard-won boundary, built from painful experience.</p><h2 id="the-spectrum-concept-there-is-no-typical-brain">The Spectrum Concept: There Is No “Typical” Brain</h2><p>When people hear the word “spectrum,” they often picture a straight line running from “a little bit autistic” at one end to “very autistic” at the other. This image is intuitive but deeply misleading. It suggests that neurodivergence is simply a matter of severity - that some people have a mild case and others a severe one, and that with enough effort, someone might move along the line towards “normal.”</p><p>The reality is far more complex and, I think, far more interesting.</p><p>A spectrum, in the truest sense, is not a single line but a range of variation across multiple dimensions. Think of the colour spectrum: it does not run from “a little bit coloured” to “very coloured.” It encompasses entirely different hues - red, orange, yellow, green, blue, violet - each with its own character. A person can be highly saturated in one colour and barely present in another. The same is true of neurodivergence.</p><p>An autistic person, for example, might have exceptional verbal skills but struggle profoundly with sensory processing. Another might navigate sensory environments with relative ease but find social communication exhausting and confusing. A person with ADHD might have severe difficulties with time management but exceptional capacity for creative problem-solving. Another might manage deadlines adequately but struggle with emotional regulation to a degree that affects every relationship they have.</p><p>This is why two people with the same diagnosis can appear so remarkably different. The diagnosis names a cluster of traits, but the specific configuration - which traits are present, how intensely, and in what combination - varies enormously from person to person. As one clinical text notes, if you have met one autistic person, you have met one autistic person <sup id="fnref:652"><a href="#fn:652" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. The same applies to ADHD and to the many other forms of neurodivergence.</p><p>This variation has profound implications for relationships. Your neurodivergent partner is not a textbook case. They are a unique individual whose neurology interacts with their personality, their history, their culture, and their current circumstances in ways that no generalisation can fully capture. The information in this book will give you frameworks and possibilities, but only your partner can tell you what is true for them.</p><p>It also means that comparisons are often unhelpful. “My cousin has ADHD and she manages fine” is not a useful observation, because your cousin’s ADHD may present entirely differently from your partner’s. The traits that make daily life difficult for one person may not be the traits that challenge another. What looks like coping may be masking. What looks like failure may be a person pushed beyond their capacity in ways that are invisible to outside observers.</p><p>There is another dimension to the spectrum concept that often goes unacknowledged: neurotypicality itself is not a single fixed point. The brains we call “typical” also vary considerably. Some neurotypical people are more socially intuitive than others. Some handle change with ease; others find it unsettling. Some thrive on routine; others crave novelty. The line between neurotypical and neurodivergent is not a sharp boundary but a blurry zone, shaped as much by social convention as by neuroscience.</p><p>What distinguishes neurodivergent people is not that they have quirks - everyone does - but that their neurological differences are significant enough to create meaningful friction with the expectations of the world around them. This friction may manifest as a diagnosable condition, or it may simply be a persistent sense of not quite fitting, of having to work harder than others to achieve the same results, of exhaustion that nobody else seems to share.</p><p>Some researchers and clinicians now speak of the “broader autism phenotype” or “shadow traits” of ADHD - subclinical variations that do not meet diagnostic thresholds but nonetheless shape a person’s experience. If you recognise yourself in the descriptions in this book but have never received a diagnosis, you are not imagining things. You may sit somewhere in that vast grey zone between clearly neurotypical and clearly neurodivergent. Your experience is valid, even without a clinical label.</p><p>What does all this mean practically? It means that rigid categories - “autistic people do this,” “ADHD people are like that” - will only take you so far. They are starting points, not destinations. The goal is not to learn a set of rules about neurodivergent people but to develop the curiosity and flexibility to understand the specific person in front of you.</p><p>It also means releasing the idea of a “normal” brain that we should all be aspiring to. There is no neurological gold standard. There are only different configurations, each with trade-offs, each adapted to certain environments better than others. The brain that struggles in a fluorescent-lit open-plan office might excel in a quiet workshop. The brain that cannot follow a nine-to-five schedule might produce its best work at midnight. The brain that misses social subtext might offer a directness and honesty that cuts through confusion.</p><p>None of this erases difficulty. It simply places that difficulty in context. And context, as we shall see throughout this book, changes everything.</p><h2 id="common-misconceptions-and-stereotypes">Common Misconceptions and Stereotypes</h2><p>If you have recently encountered neurodivergence - whether through your own diagnosis, your partner’s, or simply by beginning to research the topic - you have likely already bumped into some deeply entrenched myths. These misconceptions circulate in casual conversation, in workplaces, in families, and even among healthcare professionals who should know better. They cause real harm, not because they are malicious but because they are invisible. They shape expectations, close down conversations, and leave neurodivergent people feeling unseen.</p><p>Let me address some of the most common.</p><h3 id="you-dont-look-autistic--you-dont-seem-like-you-have-adhd">“You don’t look autistic” / “You don’t seem like you have ADHD”</h3><p>This may be intended as a compliment. It is not received as one. What it actually communicates is: “You don’t match the stereotype I hold in my head, therefore I am questioning your reality.” The stereotypes in question are typically drawn from the most visible presentations - the nonverbal child, the hyperactive boy bouncing off walls - and exclude the vast majority of neurodivergent people who do not fit these narrow images.</p><p>Modern media has not helped. Film, television, and news coverage tend to employ a “make visible” strategy when depicting conditions that have no obvious physical markers. Autism, being invisible, is often represented by conditions that are visible - a person with intellectual or physical disabilities may be shown to represent autism, despite these being entirely different conditions. Alternatively, autism is depicted through the tantruming child or the socially awkward savant. ADHD is represented by the impulsive, scrupulous CEO who fires people without a second thought, or the chaotic creative who cannot hold down a job. These images make for easy storytelling, but they are not accurate depictions of these conditions. They are caricatures - exaggerated, narrowly selected, and often outright wrong. Yet because they are repeated so frequently, many people have internalised them as truth. They have come to believe that this is what autism looks like, what ADHD looks like. And when they meet someone who does not match the caricature, they conclude that the person cannot really have the condition.</p><p>If you are reading this book, I would ask you to consciously set aside these media-fed assumptions. Holding onto them will only blind you to the reality of what these conditions actually are - and, more importantly, to who your partner actually is. In the next two chapters, we will explore the genuine traits of ADHD and autism. You may find they bear little resemblance to what you thought you knew.</p><p>Many neurodivergent adults have spent decades learning to mask their differences, to perform neurotypicality well enough to get by. The fact that they can make eye contact, hold down a job, or conduct a conversation without obvious difficulty does not mean they are not autistic or do not have ADHD. It means they have become skilled at a form of constant, exhausting performance. When someone says, “you don’t look autistic,” they are often witnessing the mask, not the person beneath it. This is discussed in greater detail in Chapter 5.</p><h3 id="everyone-is-a-little-bit-adhdautistic-these-days">“Everyone is a little bit ADHD/autistic these days”</h3><p>This dismissal has become increasingly common as awareness of neurodivergence has grown. It contains a grain of truth wrapped in a great deal of invalidation. Yes, many neurotypical people occasionally lose their keys, feel socially awkward, or get distracted. But there is a profound difference between occasional experiences and a pervasive neurological pattern that affects every domain of life.</p><p>Consider how this logic sounds when applied elsewhere. Closing your eyes for a moment does not make you “a little bit blind.” You would never tell a person who has been blind from birth that you understand their experience because you once stumbled in a dark room. The comparison is not just inaccurate - it is insulting. It equates a momentary, chosen, reversible experience with a permanent and pervasive one. The same principle applies here. Occasionally losing focus during a dull meeting is not “being a little bit ADHD.” Feeling awkward at a party is not “being a little bit autistic.” One cannot equate incidental events that everyone experiences to a persistent, always-present, lifelong neurological reality. The thinking is as insensitive as telling a blind person that everyone is a little blind - and it leaves the neurodivergent person feeling both dismissed and utterly alone.</p><p>When someone says, “everyone is a little bit ADHD,” they are comparing their momentary lapses to another person’s lifelong struggle. It is rather like telling someone with clinical depression that everyone feels sad sometimes. Technically true, entirely unhelpful, and deeply minimising of genuine suffering. Research confirms that this kind of stigma remains widespread and contributes to diagnostic delays and reluctance to seek support <sup id="fnref:160"><a href="#fn:160" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</p><h3 id="adhd-is-just-an-excuse-for-laziness--autism-is-an-excuse-for-rudeness">“ADHD is just an excuse for laziness” / “Autism is an excuse for rudeness”</h3><p>These beliefs persist despite decades of neuroscientific research demonstrating that ADHD and autism involve measurable differences in brain structure and function. ADHD is associated with differences in the prefrontal cortex and dopamine regulation that affect attention, motivation, and impulse control <sup id="fnref:91"><a href="#fn:91" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. Autism involves differences in connectivity across multiple brain regions, affecting social processing, sensory integration, and prediction <sup id="fnref:661"><a href="#fn:661" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>. These are not character flaws. They are not choices. They are neurology.</p><p>The persistence of these myths reflects a broader cultural tendency to interpret behaviour through a moral lens. If someone does not do what we expect, we assume they are choosing not to - that they are lazy, selfish, or rude. This assumption makes sense when applied to neurotypical people operating in a neurotypical world. It falls apart entirely when applied to people whose brains process motivation, time, social cues, and sensory information differently.</p><p>When your ADHD partner fails to complete a task they promised to do, they are rarely choosing to let you down. When your autistic partner says something that lands as blunt or hurtful, they are rarely intending to wound. This does not mean the impact is not real, or that accountability does not matter. But it does mean that attributing malice or laziness where none exists will poison your relationship faster than almost anything else.</p><h3 id="autism-means-you-lack-empathy">“Autism means you lack empathy”</h3><p>This myth has caused immeasurable damage. It originated from early research that conflated cognitive empathy (the ability to read what others are thinking and feeling) with affective empathy (the ability to feel compassion and care in response). Autistic people often struggle with the former - correctly interpreting facial expressions, body language, and social subtext does not come naturally. But research consistently shows that affective empathy is intact and often heightened <sup id="fnref:285"><a href="#fn:285" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. Many autistic people care deeply, sometimes overwhelmingly, about others’ wellbeing. They simply may not express it in ways that neurotypical people recognise.</p><p>The “double empathy problem,” a concept we will explore in Chapter 3, suggests that the difficulty runs both ways. Neurotypical people are often just as poor at reading autistic people as autistic people are at reading them. The difference is that neurotypical people are in the majority, so their failures of empathy are treated as the autistic person’s problem.</p><h3 id="people-grow-out-of-adhd--autism-is-a-childhood-condition">“People grow out of ADHD” / “Autism is a childhood condition”</h3><p>Both ADHD and autism are lifelong neurodevelopmental conditions. While presentations may change with age - hyperactivity often decreases in adulthood (or more correctly, internalises), for example, while inattention persists - the underlying neurology does not disappear. The reason so many adults are receiving diagnoses for the first time is not that they suddenly developed these conditions. It is that they were missed in childhood, often because they did not fit the stereotypical profile or because they learned to compensate and mask.</p><p>The consequences of late diagnosis are significant and will be explored fully in Chapter 5. For now, it is enough to note that the adult sitting across from you, diagnosed at forty-five, has been neurodivergent their entire life. They did not just become this way. They always were, and simply, finally, have a name for it.</p><h2 id="why-language-matters-person--vs-identity-first-language">Why Language Matters: Person- vs Identity-First Language</h2><p>The words we use to describe neurodivergence are not neutral. They carry assumptions, signal attitudes, and shape how both neurodivergent and neurotypical people think about these conditions. Getting the language right is not about political correctness or walking on eggshells. It is about respect - and about accuracy.</p><p>You will encounter two main approaches: person-first language and identity-first language. Understanding both, and knowing when to use each, will serve you well as you navigate conversations about neurodivergence.</p><p><strong>Person-first language</strong> puts the person before the condition. It sounds like: “person with autism,” “individual with ADHD,” “someone who has dyslexia.” The logic behind this approach is that a person is more than their diagnosis - that by naming the person first, we avoid reducing them to a label. This framework emerged from disability advocacy movements and was championed by organisations seeking to humanise people with disabilities who had long been defined solely by their conditions <sup id="fnref:660"><a href="#fn:660" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup><sup id="fnref:661:1"><a href="#fn:661" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.</p><p>For many years, person-first language was considered best practice across healthcare, education, and social services. It remains preferred in some contexts and by some individuals. If someone tells you they prefer to be called “a person with autism,” that preference should be honoured without question.</p><p><strong>Identity-first language</strong> puts the condition first. It sounds like: “autistic person,” “ADHD adult,” “dyslexic writer.” This approach has gained significant ground in neurodivergent communities, particularly among autistic self-advocates. The reasoning is that autism and ADHD are not separable from the person - they are not diseases attached to an otherwise “normal” individual, but fundamental aspects of how that person experiences and interacts with the world.</p><p>The autistic self-advocate Jim Sinclair articulated this position powerfully in his influential essay “Why I Dislike Person-First Language” <sup id="fnref:655"><a href="#fn:655" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>. Sinclair argued that saying “person with autism” implies that autism is something negative, something that can and should be separated from the person, like a tumour to be removed. But autism is not a tumour. It shapes perception, cognition, memory, social connection, sensory experience - nearly everything that makes a person who they are. To speak of the “person” as separate from the “autism” is to imagine a person who does not exist.</p><p>Research into the preferences of autistic people themselves supports this view. Studies consistently find that a majority of autistic adults prefer identity-first language, while professionals and parents are more likely to favour person-first constructions <sup id="fnref:86"><a href="#fn:86" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup><sup id="fnref:692"><a href="#fn:692" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup>. This gap is telling. It suggests that person-first language, despite its good intentions, may reflect the preferences of those looking at neurodivergence from the outside rather than those living it from within.</p><p>The ADHD community is somewhat more mixed in its preferences, though identity-first language is increasingly common there as well. You will hear people describe themselves as “an ADHDer” or simply say “I’m ADHD” as naturally as they might say “I’m Australian” or “I’m left-handed.”</p><p>So what should you do? The honest answer is: ask, and then listen.</p><p>If you are speaking about a specific person, use the language they prefer. If your partner describes themselves as “autistic,” do not correct them to “person with autism” because a textbook told you that was more respectful. Their self-identification takes precedence. If they prefer person-first language, honour that instead.</p><p>If you are speaking about neurodivergent people in general - as I do throughout this book - identity-first language is increasingly the safer and more accepted choice within the communities themselves. I use “autistic person” and “ADHD adult” throughout this text, not to reduce anyone to a label, but to reflect the preference of those whose voices should matter most in this conversation. I also think that the “person with” phrasing infers that “without” is possible - it’s not.</p><p>There are other language considerations worth noting.</p><p>Avoid language that frames neurodivergence as disease or tragedy. Terms like “suffering from autism,” “afflicted with ADHD,” or “struck by” these conditions imply that neurodivergence is inherently a source of misery. While neurodivergent people certainly face challenges - some of them severe - the conditions themselves are not illnesses to be cured. Many neurodivergent people live rich, meaningful lives and would not choose to be neurotypical even if they could.</p><p>Be cautious with functioning labels. You may encounter terms like “high-functioning autism” or “low-functioning ADHD.” These labels are increasingly rejected by the neurodivergent community because they flatten complex profiles into misleading binaries. A person labelled “high-functioning” may be struggling enormously in ways that are invisible; the label can be used to deny them support. A person labelled “low-functioning” may have capabilities and insights that the label obscures; it can be used to deny them agency.</p><p>You may also encounter ongoing debates - in media, in parent advocacy groups, and occasionally in clinical circles - arguing that “severe autism” should be classified as an entirely separate condition from what was once called Asperger’s syndrome. The impulse is understandable: parents of children with very high support needs often feel that their experiences are invisible in conversations dominated by articulate autistic self-advocates. However, this push toward separation is contentious and raises significant concerns about fracturing a community that already struggles for recognition and resources. We will explore support levels and the spectrum concept more fully in Chapter 3, but for now, be aware that these debates exist and that the language you encounter may carry political weight you did not anticipate.</p><p>The current diagnostic framework for autism varies depending on where you live. In the United States and Australia, clinicians typically use the DSM-5, which categorises autism by support levels (Level 1, 2, or 3). In the United Kingdom and much of Europe, the ICD-11 is more commonly used; this system does not use support levels at all, instead describing the presence or absence of intellectual impairment and functional language impairment. Both systems have limitations, and neither fully captures the complexity of individual presentations. When in doubt, describe specific strengths and challenges rather than reaching for a shorthand that may do more harm than good.</p><p>Avoid using diagnostic terms as casual adjectives. “I’m so OCD about my bookshelf” or “the weather is so bipolar today” trivialises genuine conditions and contributes to the misconceptions discussed in the previous section. These are not quirky personality traits or metaphors for mild preferences. They are neurological realities that significantly affect people’s lives.</p><p>Finally, remember that language evolves. The terms considered respectful today may shift in a decade. What matters more than memorising the “correct” vocabulary is cultivating an attitude of genuine respect and a willingness to learn. If you use a term that someone finds hurtful, apologise, adjust, and move on. The goal is connection, not perfection.</p><p>Words are not everything. But in a world where neurodivergent people have so often been spoken about rather than spoken with, choosing language carefully is one small way of signalling that you see them as full human beings deserving of dignity. That signal matters more than you might think.</p><h2 id="the-medical-model-vs-the-social-model-of-disability">The Medical Model vs the Social Model of Disability</h2><p>How we understand disability shapes everything - how we treat people, what solutions we pursue, where we place responsibility, and whether we offer compassion or judgment. Two competing frameworks have dominated this conversation for decades: the medical model and the social model. Understanding both is essential, not just for grasping the politics of neurodivergence, but for navigating your own relationships with greater wisdom and less blame.</p><h3 id="the-medical-model">The Medical Model</h3><p>The medical model of disability locates the problem inside the individual. It views disability as a defect, a deviation from normal functioning that resides in the person’s body or brain. The goal, under this framework, is to fix, cure, or rehabilitate the individual - to bring them as close to “normal” as possible.</p><p>This model has deep roots in Western medicine and has delivered genuine benefits. It drives research into treatments, funds therapies, and provides diagnostic categories that help people access support. When someone receives an ADHD diagnosis and finds that medication helps them function, the medical model is working as intended. When an autistic child receives speech therapy that helps them communicate, the medical model has contributed something valuable.</p><p>But the medical model also carries significant limitations, particularly when applied to neurodevelopmental conditions.</p><p>First, it positions the neurodivergent person as inherently broken. The language of disorder, deficit, and dysfunction permeates diagnostic criteria and clinical literature. The very names of these conditions - Attention Deficit Hyperactivity <em>Disorder</em>, Autism Spectrum <em>Disorder</em> - encode the assumption that something is wrong with the person. This framing can be internalised, leading neurodivergent people to see themselves as faulty versions of what they should have been, rather than as complete human beings with a different neurological profile.</p><p>Second, the medical model is often interpreted as placing the entire burden of adaptation on the individual. When people hear terms like “disorder” or “deficit,” they frequently infer that something is faulty and must be corrected. But this is a translation error. In clinical usage, “disorder” simply means a condition - a recognised pattern of traits that may require support. It does not mean broken, and it does not demand that the person contort themselves to appear normal.</p><p>Yet this nuance is routinely lost. Outside clinical settings, diagnostic language is heard through a cultural filter that equates difference with defect. The result is that neurodivergent people - and those around them - come to believe that they must mask their differences, suppress their needs, and reshape themselves to fit a world that was not designed for them. The environment escapes scrutiny. The systems that exclude are treated as neutral, natural, and unchangeable. This is not what the medical model intends, but it is often what the medical model produces when its language enters the wider world without adequate translation.</p><p>Third, the medical model can - in the hands of inadequately trained or inexperienced clinicians - justify interventions that prioritise the comfort of others over the wellbeing of the neurodivergent person. Historically, this has led to therapies aimed at eliminating autistic behaviours - like stimming or avoiding eye contact - not because these behaviours harm the autistic person, but because they make neurotypical people uncomfortable. The goal becomes making the neurodivergent person <em>appear</em> normal, regardless of the psychological cost.</p><p>But it is important to be precise about where this problem originates. It is not the medical model itself that demands such interventions. It is clinicians whose training has not kept pace with current understanding, or whose experience of neurodivergence is limited to textbook stereotypes. The assumption that “the doctor is always right” is widespread - but a clinician’s ability to interpret a condition depends heavily on their experience and training. And the evidence suggests that many fall short.</p><p>Systematic reviews confirm that clinicians themselves report only moderate knowledge and low self-efficacy when working with autistic people <sup id="fnref:161"><a href="#fn:161" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>. Qualitative studies consistently highlight dissatisfaction with services, lack of accommodations, and poor communication among neurodivergent clients. Even psychotherapists acknowledge significant gaps in autism education and competence <sup id="fnref:783"><a href="#fn:783" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>. The consequences are not abstract. One in four autistic adults report receiving inaccurate psychiatric diagnoses before their neurodevelopmental condition was recognised <sup id="fnref:784"><a href="#fn:784" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>. Others avoid formal assessment altogether, citing past experiences of being misunderstood, blamed, or dismissed <sup id="fnref:785"><a href="#fn:785" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup>.</p><p>I have felt these blind spots directly. A renowned psychiatrist, who had diagnosed my ADHD condition, told me that I could not be autistic because I was able to make eye contact with him - a statement later refuted by a panel who formally diagnosed the ASD, and one that reveals how easily stereotypes override evidence. Beyond my own experience, I have watched family members struggle to find professionals able to genuinely support them in living with their conditions. I have also seen family members take personal insult at these diagnoses, because the outdated and long-refuted assumption that autism is caused by bad parenting still persists in some circles. These experiences are why so many in the neurodivergent community approach psychology and psychiatry with scepticism. They are why the phrase “neurodiversity-affirming” has become a shorthand that people actively seek out when looking for clinicians. It is not about division. It is about the repair of trust that has been repeatedly broken.</p><p>This is not to say that all medical intervention is harmful or unwanted. Many neurodivergent people actively seek diagnosis, medication, and therapy, and find these supports life-changing. The critique is not of medicine itself, but of clinicians who lack adequate training, and of a broader culture that too often treats the person as the problem and adaptation as their sole responsibility.</p><h3 id="the-social-model">The Social Model</h3><p>The social model of disability, developed by disability rights activists in the 1970s and 1980s, offers a fundamentally different perspective. It distinguishes between <em>impairment</em> (the physical or neurological difference itself) and <em>disability</em> (the disadvantage created by a society that fails to accommodate that difference).</p><p>Under this framework, a person who uses a wheelchair has an impairment affecting their mobility. But they are <em>disabled</em> by stairs, not by their legs. They are disabled by buildings without ramps, buses without lifts, and attitudes that treat walking as the only legitimate way to move through the world. If the environment were fully accessible, the impairment would remain, but much of the disability would disappear.</p><p>Applied to neurodivergence, the social model asks us to look beyond the individual brain and examine the world that brain must navigate. An autistic person may have genuine differences in sensory processing, this is the impairment. Yet they may be <em>disabled</em> by open-plan offices with flickering fluorescent lights, by social norms that insist on eye contact and small talk, and by job interviews that reward confident self-promotion rather than actual competence. Change the environment and the disability diminishes.</p><p>An ADHD individual may not receive enough stimulation at work to elevate dopamine levels to a functional baseline, leading to tonic hypodopaminergia and a resulting drop in cognitive efficiency. In other words, when the environment under-stimulates, performance collapses and the resulting cognitive impedance is disabling. Or, they may have genuine differences in attention regulation and time perception - this is the impairment. But they are <em>disabled</em> by workplaces that demand eight hours of sustained focus on unstimulating tasks, by educational systems built around sitting still and listening, by a culture that moralises punctuality and treats lateness as a character flaw. Create structures that work with the ADHD brain rather than against it, and the disability becomes far less disabling.</p><p>The social model does not deny that impairments can be challenging in themselves. Sensory overload is painful regardless of environment. Executive dysfunction creates real difficulties even in the most accommodating workplace. The social model does not claim that neurodivergence would be effortless in a perfect world. What it does is refuse to let the environment off the hook. It insists that society bears responsibility for the barriers it creates - and that removing those barriers is a matter of justice, not charity.</p><p>This shift in perspective has profound implications. Instead of asking “How do we fix this person?”, we begin to ask “How do we change this environment?” Instead of telling the neurodivergent person to try harder, we ask what support they need to succeed. Instead of treating accommodations as special favours, we recognise them as basic accessibility - no different, in principle, from providing ramps for wheelchair users or captions for deaf viewers.</p><h3 id="why-this-matters-for-relationships">Why This Matters for Relationships</h3><p>You may be wondering what disability models have to do with your relationship. The answer is: everything.</p><p>The way you frame your partner’s neurodivergence will shape every interaction you have. If you operate from a purely medical model, you will see their differences as deficits to be overcome. You will wait for them to be “fixed” by medication or therapy. You will measure their progress against a neurotypical standard they may never reach. And you will grow frustrated, resentful, and exhausted when the fixing never quite happens.</p><p>If you incorporate the social model, you will begin to ask different questions. Instead of “Why can’t they just remember to do this?”, you might ask “What systems could we put in place to support their memory?” Instead of “Why do they always get overwhelmed at family gatherings?”, you might ask “How can we structure these events so they’re manageable?” Instead of “Why can’t they be normal?”, you might ask “What does our life need to look like for both of us to thrive?”</p><p>This is not about lowering your standards or accepting behaviour that genuinely harms you. Chapter 14 addresses accountability directly. But it is about recognising that many of the struggles in neurodiverse relationships arise not from one partner being broken, but from two people with different neurology trying to share a life in a world designed for only one of them.</p><p>The social model also invites self-compassion for the neurodivergent partner. If you have spent your life believing you are lazy, stupid, or fundamentally flawed, the social model offers an alternative narrative. Your struggles are real, but they are not evidence of your worthlessness. Many of them arise from a mismatch between your brain and your environment - a mismatch you did not create and are not solely responsible for solving.</p><h3 id="a-bothand-approach">A Both/And Approach</h3><p>In practice, most people find that neither model alone captures the full picture. The medical model offers useful tools: diagnosis provides understanding, medication can be transformative, therapy builds skills. The social model offers essential perspective: it challenges stigma, demands accommodations, and refuses to locate all responsibility in the individual.</p><p>The most helpful approach is often a both/and rather than an either/or. Yes, seek diagnosis and treatment where they help. And also, advocate for environments that accommodate rather than exclude. Yes, build skills to navigate a neurotypical world. And also, refuse to accept that the neurotypical way is the only legitimate way. Yes, take responsibility for your own growth. And also, insist that others take responsibility for their part in creating accessible, compassionate spaces.</p><p>For relationships, this means holding two truths at once. Your neurodivergent partner may benefit from treatment and skill-building - this is not unkind to acknowledge. And your relationship may benefit from environmental adjustments, revised expectations, and a willingness to do things differently - this is not unfair to ask. Both partners contribute. Both partners adapt. The goal is not to fix one person, but to build a shared life that works for both.</p><p>This is harder than it sounds. It requires letting go of the fantasy that one day, with enough effort, your partner will become neurotypical. They will not. It requires grieving the relationship you imagined and building the relationship that is actually possible. It requires creativity, flexibility, and a willingness to question assumptions you may not even know you hold.</p><p>But it also opens up possibilities that the medical model alone forecloses. When you stop trying to fix your partner and start trying to understand them, something shifts. When you stop measuring them against a neurotypical yardstick and start appreciating what they actually bring, connection becomes possible in ways it was not before. When you stop seeing their needs as burdens and start seeing them as information, you can begin to build a life together rather than fighting an endless war against their neurology.</p><p>That is the invitation of this book. Not to fix anyone, but to understand. Not to cure, but to accommodate. Not to erase difference, but to build a relationship capacious enough to hold it.</p><h2 id="where-this-leaves-us">Where This Leaves Us</h2><p>This chapter has introduced the core concepts you will need to understand the rest of this book: what neurodivergence means, how it differs from neurodiversity, why the spectrum is not a straight line, and how our choice of words shapes our understanding. We have examined the stereotypes that harm neurodivergent people and compared two ways of thinking about disability - one that locates the problem in the individual, another that asks the environment to change.</p><p>But if there is one idea I hope you carry forward from this chapter, it is this: <strong>you cannot change your partner</strong>.</p><p>This is not a failure of effort or love. It is a fundamental truth about human relationships - one that applies whether or not neurodivergence is involved, but becomes especially urgent when it is.</p><p>Research into what makes relationships succeed or fail consistently points to the same conclusion. John Gottman’s decades of research at the University of Washington found that couples who approach their partners with the intent to change or “fix” them create precisely the conditions that predict relationship breakdown: criticism, contempt, defensiveness, and stonewalling. Contempt - the sense that you are superior to your partner and that they are fundamentally flawed - is the single strongest predictor of divorce <sup id="fnref:781"><a href="#fn:781" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup>. And contempt grows directly from the belief that your partner is a broken version of who they should be.</p><p>Melissa Orlov, whose work on ADHD relationships aligns with much of this book, puts it plainly: “You must put your dreams of forcing your partner to change aside” <sup id="fnref:782"><a href="#fn:782" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup>. She describes how her own marriage transformed only when she stopped trying to control her husband’s ADHD and started taking responsibility for her own happiness. Not because his symptoms no longer mattered, but because her attempts to change him were making everything worse. The anger, the vigilance, the disappointment - these created a toxic environment in which no one could thrive. Only when she let go of the illusion of control did change become possible.</p><p>This pattern appears across every account of successful neurodiverse relationships. The neurotypical partner who spends years trying to make their autistic spouse more emotionally expressive, more socially comfortable, more “normal,” typically ends up exhausted, resentful, and no closer to their goal. The partner who tries to nag, threaten, or shame their ADHD spouse into reliability finds that the nagging itself becomes the problem - generating defensiveness, eroding trust, and destroying the very motivation they hoped to inspire.</p><p>The reason is more complex than it first appears. Some behaviours can change with effort, support, and the right strategies. But many neurodivergent traits are not behaviours at all - they are neurology. They are how the brain is wired. No amount of wanting, on either partner’s part, will make an ADHD brain suddenly track time accurately or an autistic brain stop being overwhelmed by sensory input.</p><p>This creates two painful problems. First, the neurotypical partner may continue hoping for changes that are neurologically impossible, setting themselves up for repeated disappointment and their partner up for repeated failure. Second - and this is perhaps more damaging - the neurodivergent partner may also desperately want to change. They may have spent their entire life trying to be “normal,” believing that if they just tried hard enough, they could fix themselves. When change does not come, they do not conclude that the goal was impossible. They conclude that they are failures.</p><p>The only path left is masking: performing neurotypicality at immense personal cost. And masking does not solve the problem - it hides it while creating new ones. The exhaustion, the loss of identity, the eventual breakdown when the mask slips or becomes unsustainable. Chapter 5 explores masking in detail, but for now, the key point is this: asking a neurodivergent person to change their neurology is not just futile. It is harmful. It drives them toward a coping strategy that will eventually exact a devastating toll.</p><p>This does not mean nothing can change. Strategies can be developed. Environments can be modified. Communication patterns can improve. Support systems can be built. But these are adaptations, not transformations. They work with the neurodivergent brain, not against it. The goal is not to turn your partner into someone else. It is to build a life that accommodates who they actually are.</p><p>This also does not mean you must accept everything. It does not mean boundaries do not matter, or that harmful behaviour must be tolerated. Later chapters will address accountability, boundaries, and the difficult question of when a relationship cannot be saved. But it does mean that entering a relationship - or remaining in one - with the primary goal of transforming your partner into someone else is a path to mutual misery.</p><p>The invitation of this book is different. It asks you to seek understanding rather than change. To become curious about how your partner’s brain actually works, rather than measuring it against an imaginary standard. To ask not “Why can’t they be normal?” but “What do we each need to build a life together?”</p><p>This may seem like the more difficult path. It is not. Trying to fix your partner feels like the obvious approach - it appears direct, actionable, like something you can work on. But it is a path that leads nowhere. You will spend years pushing against immovable neurology, growing more frustrated and exhausted with each attempt, while your partner feels increasingly broken and unloved. The route that appears harder - acceptance, adaptation, building something new - is the only one that actually goes somewhere. It requires grieving the partner you imagined and accepting the one you have. It requires examining your own assumptions, your own contributions to conflict, your own areas for growth. It requires humility.</p><p>But it also opens possibilities that the “fix my partner” approach forecloses entirely. When you stop fighting against your partner’s neurology and start working with it, something shifts. When they feel accepted rather than constantly corrected, safety replaces defensiveness. When you stop waiting for them to become someone else and start appreciating who they are, connection becomes possible.</p><p>That is the work ahead. It will not be easy. But if you have read this far, you have already taken the first step: you have chosen curiosity over judgment, understanding over blame.</p><p>Let us continue.</p><p style="text-align:center">⁂</p><hr /><div class="d-flex justify-content-center align-items-center my-4"><a class="btn btn-lg btn-success" href="/books/buy-lvm/"><i class="fas fa-cart-shopping"></i> Buy this book</a></div><hr /><div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"><ol><li id="fn:656"><p>Singer, J. (1999). Why can’t you be normal for once in your life? From a ‘problem with no name’ to the emergence of a new category of difference. In M. Corker &amp; S. French (Eds.), <em>Disability Discourse</em>. [ISBN: 978-0-335-20222-5]. <a href="#fnref:656" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:652"><p>Silverman, C. (2011). <em>Understanding autism: Parents, doctors, and the history of a disorder</em>. Princeton University Press. [ISBN: 978-0-691-15968-3]. <a href="#fnref:652" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:160"><p>Corden, K., Brewer, R., &amp; Cage, E. (2021). Personal Identity After an Autism Diagnosis: Relationships With Self-Esteem, Mental Wellbeing, and Diagnostic Timing. <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em>, <em>12</em>, 699335. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.699335">DOI: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.699335</a><a href="#fnref:160" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:91"><p>Bozhilova, N. S., Michelini, G., Kuntsi, J., &amp; Asherson, P. (2018). Mind Wandering Perspective on Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder. <em>Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2018.07.010">DOI: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2018.07.010</a><a href="#fnref:91" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:661"><p>Snow, K. (2006). To ensure inclusion, freedom, and respect for all, it’s time to embrace people first language. <em>DisablityIsNatural. com</em>, 1–4. <a href="#fnref:661" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:661:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:285"><p>Grove, R., Baillie, A., Allison, C., Baron-Cohen, S., &amp; Hoekstra, R. A. (2014). The latent structure of cognitive and emotional empathy in individuals with autism, first-degree relatives and typical individuals. <em>Mol Autism</em>, <em>5</em>, 42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/2040-2392-5-42">DOI: 10.1186/2040-2392-5-42</a><a href="#fnref:285" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:660"><p>Snow, K. (2001, 2001). <em>People first language. Disability is Natural.</em>. <a href="#fnref:660" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:655"><p>Sinclair, J. (1999, 1999). <em>Why I dislike “person-first” language</em>. <a href="#fnref:655" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:86"><p>Botha, M., Hanlon, J., &amp; Williams, G. L. (2023). Does Language Matter? Identity-First Versus Person-First Language Use in Autism Research: A Response to Vivanti. <em>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</em>, <em>53</em>(2), 870–878. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-020-04858-w">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-020-04858-w</a><a href="#fnref:86" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:692"><p>Taboas, A., Doepke, K., &amp; Zimmerman, C. (2023). Preferences for Identity-First Versus Person-First Language in a US Sample of Autism Stakeholders. <em>Autism</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/13623613221130845">DOI: 10.1177/13623613221130845</a><a href="#fnref:692" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:161"><p>Corden, K., Brewer, R., &amp; Cage, E. (2021). A Systematic Review of Healthcare Professionals’ Knowledge, Self-Efficacy and Attitudes Towards Working with Autistic People. <em>Review Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</em>, <em>9</em>(3), 386–399. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40489-021-00263-w">DOI: 10.1007/s40489-021-00263-w</a><a href="#fnref:161" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:783"><p>Lipinski, S., Boegl, K., Blanke, E. S., Suenkel, U., &amp; Dziobek, I. (2022). A blind spot in mental healthcare? Psychotherapists lack education and expertise for the support of adults on the autism spectrum. <em>Autism</em>, <em>26</em>(6), 1509–1521. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/13623613211057973">DOI: 10.1177/13623613211057973</a><a href="#fnref:783" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:784"><p>Kentrou, V., Livingston, L. A., Grove, R., Hoekstra, R. A., &amp; Begeer, S. (2024). Perceived misdiagnosis of psychiatric conditions in autistic adults. <em>EClinicalMedicine</em>, <em>71</em>, 102586. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102586">DOI: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102586</a><a href="#fnref:784" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:785"><p>Lewis, L. F. (2017). A Mixed Methods Study of Barriers to Formal Diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder in Adults. <em>J Autism Dev Disord</em>, <em>47</em>(8), 2410–2424. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-017-3168-3">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-017-3168-3</a><a href="#fnref:785" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:781"><p>Gottman, J., &amp; Silver, N. (2018). <em>The seven principles for making marriage work</em>. Harmony. [ISBN: 9780553447712]. <a href="#fnref:781" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:782"><p>Orlov, M. (2010). <em>The ADHD Effect on Marriage</em>. Specialty Press/A.D.D. Warehouse. [ISBN: 9781886941977]. <a href="#fnref:782" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li></ol></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><category term="ASD," /><category term="ADHD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is Chapter One from the book Loving Variant Minds: How to Navigate Love After a Late Neurodivergence Diagnosis.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/lvm-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/lvm-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Modernising HR: Autism 🡢 Postscript</title><link href="/insights/mhr_asd_postscript.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modernising HR: Autism 🡢 Postscript" /><published>2025-11-01T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-12-30T13:38:04+11:00</updated><id>/insights/mhr-asd-postscript</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/mhr_asd_postscript.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The following is the unpublished Postscript from the Book Modernising HR for Variant Minds: Autism - The Monotropic Mind. At the time of publication I was not comfortable with adding it to the book, so I cut it. Alas, some have said I should have left it in… so here it is.</p><p>(Available on <a href="https://c1k.it/amat">Apple Books</a> and <a href="https://c1k.it/kmat">Kindle</a>).</p></blockquote><h1 id="postscript-a-personal-reflection">Postscript: A Personal Reflection</h1><p>I have to say, this book has been the hardest one for me to write so far. <em>(Mind you, the future one on personal relationships is the one I’m really dreading!)</em> The reason is pretty simple - how do I explain Autism to a world of HR people when society has gotten Autism all wrong?</p><p>Let me use a metaphor here <em>(and I do this a lot, because it’s often the easiest way to help people understand something)</em>. It’s akin to calling coffee “normal” or “what most people drink.” Now, how do you describe tea? Or juice? Or water? Or the hundreds of other beverages one can have. Sure, there are lots of different coffees and ways to make coffee, but coffee is still coffee, compared to other drinks. So how do you write practical strategies for accommodating minds that could be anything except what we’re used to? Every single Autistic person is different from every other Autistic person. And that’s exactly the problem when companies try to hire Autistic people - most managers don’t understand us, most don’t think like us, and most can’t figure out why we act the way we do or what we need.</p><p>But then I reminded myself - that’s not really what this book is about. This book is about changing how businesses see Autistic people. Not as problems to fix or people to feel sorry for, but as valuable employees who think differently and can help companies do better. And if I stick with the established diagnostic traits only, then I can somewhat generalise some strategies … albeit, in reality, each person, each workplace, each leadership team will need nuanced refinement.</p><p>Writing about Autism today comes with some real challenges that go way beyond just workplace best practices. We’re living in a time when reality TV shows have turned Autism into entertainment. People watch these shows and think they understand what Autism is really like. Add to that the political climate over the past few years - that hasn’t helped either. It’s made some people question whether invisible disabilities are even real.</p><p>What really bothers me is how the media keeps trying to connect Autism with things like Down Syndrome or Williams Syndrome. Head on over to Google Images and search for “Autistic person” … more than half the results show images of people who have these conditions. It’s not because society wants to understand Autism better - It’s because people seem to need to <strong><em>see</em></strong> something different about a person before they’ll believe that person has a disability. Autism is seen as people who cannot function in life, that their disability means they walk around perpetually with noise-cancelling headphones on, that they are non-verbal and prone to “tantrums” … and while ASD Level 3 is truly difficult to support, it makes up smaller fraction of people who have been diagnosed with ASD. This book is not about that though - and even though the full spectrum of Autism deserves more informed attention than it currently gets - this book is about the larger portion of Autistic people who can work, who want to work, but have to navigate systemic thinking that impedes, and in many cases blocks, them from achieving successful working careers. This book is about a corporate society that is too comfortable in normality to understand that not being like others is where innovation is born, where excellence is born, where real advantage over normal-seeking competitors can drive phenomenal success.</p><p>And it’s not only the media misrepresenting Autism - there are also individuals who weaponise it as an excuse for inexcusable behaviour. The executive who mistreats employees and claims it’s their Autism. The public figure who engages in harassment and points to their diagnosis as justification. Autism is a set of observable traits, namely: a) persistent differences in social communication and interaction across contexts; and, b) restricted or repetitive patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities. Nowhere in that definition will you find ethics, morality, compassion, or malice - yet those who happen to possess both terrible character and Autism will blame the latter for the former. And the media will lap it up and run with it. I’ve noticed that most of these public bad actors also happen to have brown hair - so should we conclude that all people with brown hair are unethical? It’s ludicrous, yet this correlation-as-causation thinking persists because sensationalism sells, and too many people are buying.</p><p>And then there’s this thing that drives me crazy - people keep saying “everyone is a little Autistic.” I’ve written about this in my other books, Autistic influencers post about it on social media, and it just won’t go away. Even my closest friends have said this to me, even after I’ve explained why it doesn’t make sense. So now I usually ask them: “Close your eyes. What do you see?” They’ll say something like “nothing” or “darkness.” Then I say: “Well, by your thinking, blind people aren’t really disabled because everyone sometimes can’t see things!” I know it sounds harsh, and I don’t mean any disrespect to people with other disabilities. But sometimes you need a strong example to help people understand that invisible disabilities are real. And inevitably they’ll say “that’s not the same thing.” So here’s another example: Crohn’s disease, a debilitating condition of the digestive tract that causes intense and painful spasms and often leads to unexpected bouts of diarrhoea. It’s not a visible disability - but try to sit in a meeting when your digestive tract has its own agenda. Everyone has diarrhoea now and then - so it can’t be a disability, right? What makes a condition a disability is that it significantly impacts a person’s ability to function and requires meaningful support for that person to live a humane life. Autism is a disability - it’s included in many countries’ laws under their disability legislation. And yes, Autism is a set of diagnostic traits that many, if not most people may have - but what makes ASD “real” is that Autistic people need to navigate those traits every waking moment of their lives.</p><p>But here’s what most people don’t grasp about what makes Autism a disability: it’s not the traits themselves that disable us - it’s the world’s refusal to accept different ways of being. An Autistic person who processes information differently, who communicates directly rather than through layers of social convention, who finds comfort in routine and logic - none of these things are inherently disabling. What disables us is working in environments designed exclusively for neurotypical minds, being judged as “difficult” or “unprofessional” for communicating honestly, facing rejection for not performing the elaborate social theatre that everyone else seems to know the script for. The disability isn’t in our neurology - it’s in a society that mistakes difference for deficiency and conformity for competence - and the ostracisation that comes with that. We’re disabled by exclusion, by assumptions, by workplaces that could accommodate us but choose not to because “that’s not how we do things here.” That’s what makes Autism a disability in the legal sense - not because we’re broken, but because the world around us refuses to make room for minds that work differently.</p><p>I’ve often seen the explanation of a disability as a graphic where 3 people are standing by a fence trying to look over it. The first person is a lot shorter than the fence. The second is just as tall as the fence. And the third person is taller than the fence. This graphic is often used to describe that disability support is not about equality in resources, but rather <strong><em>equity</em></strong> in outcomes. That supporting the shorter person will need two boxes to get them as tall as the third, and the second person only needs one box to stand on. This anecdotal explanation tries to show that support varies depending on the severity of the disability. And this leads me to the second thing that really gets me angry - when people say things like “you’ll just have to mask more” or “can’t you just try harder to fit in?” or “everyone has to adapt at work.” This is akin to asking that short person in the fence graphic to jump up and down more so that they can see over the fence. And you know what? They can, and I bet they do - the alternative is to just give up, right? One would not dare say to a wheelchair-bound person that they can just leopard crawl up the stairs, because they <em>can</em> do that. So why is it okay to ask an Autistic person to mask more when the act of masking is what causes their burnout, anxiety, mental health impacts, identity confusion, and eventual loss of authenticity? And therein lies the problem … we <em>can</em>, and we <em>do</em>, but what if we didn’t have to? What if we just got the right support, or our hurdles removed, so that we can have an equitable and just existence as other people do? What if, instead of expecting us to exhaust ourselves jumping - or in many cases, we simply give up - someone just gave us the box we need to stand on? Or better yet, what if we just tore down the barriers that shouldn’t be there to begin with?</p><p>The other societal habit I have a distinct distaste for is speaking about Autism as something on a simple scale. Terms like “high functioning” or “severe” Autism suggest a measurable ranking of people, but that view is superficial and fundamentally flawed.</p><p>Consider two people. The first was diagnosed early in childhood with more pronounced traits but received proper support and coping strategies from the beginning. The second had less apparent traits initially, so they went undiagnosed. Perhaps they lived a privileged life where circumstances naturally accommodated them, or perhaps they simply masked brilliantly. Then one day, something changes - a new job, a relationship breakdown, a pandemic, burnout. What worked before suddenly doesn’t, and their life collapses around them. Many never even discover why. Who is “higher functioning” here? The person with stronger traits who learned to navigate them, or the person with milder traits whose life fell apart? The question itself reveals how meaningless these labels are.</p><p>And here’s what those reality TV shows and dismissive politicians consistently miss: Autism rarely exists in isolation. Many Autistic people also have ADHD, anxiety disorders, dyslexia, or other conditions. Humans aren’t singular, neat categories. Saying someone is “just Autistic” is like saying a person has a left hand and therefore they are a left hand, full stop - as if the right hand, the legs, the brain, the heart don’t exist or matter. Yet this reductive thinking persists.</p><p>Even the diagnostic frameworks can’t agree on how to classify Autism. The US system uses three levels based on support needs. The European approach classifies people by cognitive and language abilities instead. If psychology itself hasn’t found a consistent way to categorise us, perhaps that should tell us something: Autism isn’t a ranking system of who’s “better” or “worse.” It’s just part of what a person is - one aspect of their humanity, not a measure of their worth or capability.</p><p>So why write this book at all when there’s so much misunderstanding to fight against? Because despite all the confusion out there, some companies are figuring out that when they support neurodivergent employees properly, those employees become some of their best workers. These companies aren’t doing charity work - they’re making smart business decisions. This book comes out of frustration, yes, but also out of hope.</p><div style="text-align:center">&#8258;</div><p></p><p>These pages aren’t about feeling sorry for Autistic people or doing the <em>“right thing”</em> just to be nice. They’re about making your business better. When you stop valuing people primarily for their social conformity and start valuing them for their productive contributions, when you stop seeing Autism as a list of problems and start seeing it as a different way of thinking that can help your company, that’s when real change happens.</p><p>If you’ve read this far, you’re probably already someone who cares about doing better. And whether you realise it or not, you likely have something many Autistic people don’t: the privilege of social advantage. Perhaps you’re a hiring manager who finds networking effortless, a leader whose communication style naturally aligns with corporate norms, an HR professional who instinctively navigates office politics, or someone with connections in other companies. That’s not a criticism - it’s an acknowledgment of reality. But with that privilege comes an opportunity, and frankly, a responsibility.</p><p>Help us. Use that privilege to hire the candidate who interviews awkwardly but has brilliant ideas. Use that influence to challenge the manager who dismisses someone as “not a culture fit” simply because they’re different. Talk to your connections in other companies about this book - recommend it. Better yet, speak to those connections about considering neurodivergent talent that their recruitment processes are currently blocking. Champion the Autistic employee who delivers exceptional work but struggles in open-plan offices. Push back when colleagues mistake directness for rudeness or routine for rigidity.</p><p>Start small if you need to. Implement even one strategy from this book. Question one assumption about what “professional” behaviour must look like. Defend one Autistic employee from criticism that’s really just coded language for “doesn’t conform.” Create one policy that values output over social performance. That’s how systemic change begins - not with grand gestures, but with people who have advantage choosing to use it to dismantle barriers rather than reinforce them.</p><p>We’re not asking for charity or sympathy. We’re asking you to recognise that innovation, excellence, and competitive advantage don’t come from everyone thinking the same way - they come from making room for minds that work differently. The way things have always been done isn’t the only way, and it’s often not even the best way.</p><p>Help us. Because we can’t do this alone.</p><div style="text-align:center">&#8258;</div><p></p><hr /><div class="d-flex justify-content-center align-items-center my-4"><a class="btn btn-lg btn-primary" href="/books/buy-mvm/"><i class="fas fa-cart-shopping"></i> Buy this book</a></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><category term="ASD," /><category term="Autism," /><category term="Book" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is the unpublished Postscript from the Book Modernising HR for Variant Minds: Autism - The Monotropic Mind. At the time of publication I was not comfortable with adding it to the book, so I cut it. Alas, some have said I should have left it in... so here it is.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh2-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh2-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Modernising HR: Autism 🡢 Chapter 1</title><link href="/insights/mhr_asd_chapter_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modernising HR: Autism 🡢 Chapter 1" /><published>2025-10-10T08:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-12-30T13:38:04+11:00</updated><id>/insights/mhr-asd-chapter-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/mhr_asd_chapter_1.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The following is Chapter One from the book <a href="/books/mvm/"><strong>Modernising HR for Variant Minds: Autism - The Monotropic Mind</strong></a>.</p><p>Available on <a href="https://c1k.it/amat">Apple Books</a> and <a href="https://c1k.it/kmat">Kindle</a>.</p></blockquote><h1 id="chapter-1--what-autism-is">Chapter 1 – What Autism is</h1><p><em>Autism isn’t rare, complicated, or tragic - it’s simply misunderstood, mostly by workplaces designed for everyone else.</em></p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/bell-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Manager Confession: The Quiet Star in the Corner</strong><br /><em>“I used to think Ethan was difficult. He never joined the small talk before meetings, didn’t come to Friday drinks, and I assumed he wasn’t a team player. Then one morning we had a system outage. While everyone else was scrambling, Ethan quietly opened a log file, found the fault, and fixed it before IT arrived. He’d been tracking tiny inconsistencies for weeks - just because they didn’t “look right.” That was the day I realised he wasn’t disengaged. He was hyper-engaged, just differently. I’d been managing through assumptions, not understanding.”</em></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="autism-in-a-cubicle">Autism in a cubicle</h2><p>Most people think they know what autism is, yet few understand how it actually operates in day-to-day working life. For many managers, “autism” still conjures images of savants, social awkwardness, or someone who “doesn’t make eye contact.” In truth, autism is a distinctive cognitive and sensory profile - not a malfunction, but a different operating system. It values depth over breadth, truth over convention, and structure over spontaneity.</p><p>Autistic people are not detached from the world; they are often deeply tuned in - just not always to the same signals their neurotypical colleagues notice. What looks like avoidance is usually sensory overload. What seems like obsession is often passion. What appears blunt is usually clarity. The problem is not the person; it is that workplaces have been built for multitasking, socially driven minds, rewarding the behaviours those minds find effortless. Autism doesn’t break those systems - it exposes where they were never as fair or efficient as we assumed.</p><p>In clinical classification systems such as the <em>DSM-5-TR</em><sup id="fnref:31"><a href="#fn:31" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and the <em>ICD-11</em><sup id="fnref:32"><a href="#fn:32" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is defined as a neurodevelopmental condition characterised by:</p><ul><li>Persistent differences in social communication and interaction across contexts; and</li><li>Restricted or repetitive patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities.</li></ul><p>It is worth noting, however, that while both systems describe the same condition, their purposes diverge. The DSM-5 serves a clinical function - assigning one of three “support levels” based on how much assistance a person may need. These levels (1: requiring support, 2: substantial support, and 3: very substantial support) can change over time as they depend heavily on the person’s environment. The ICD-11, by contrast, categorises autism through a matrix model, using two primary axes: impairment of functional language and presence or absence of intellectual disability.</p><p>But that is the clinical view - and it tells us almost nothing about the lived reality of autistic adults in the workplace. These classifications matter for diagnosis and support access, but they tell managers almost nothing about daily collaboration. At its core, autism reflects a brain that is wired differently from the statistical majority - what society calls “normal.” Pause for a moment and consider what that means. There are billions of potential neurological variations within that definition. And therein lies the complexity: autism cannot define a person as a fixed set of traits or behaviours. Each individual presents differently.</p><p>Decades of study have identified clusters of common - though not universal - features. Some autistic people prefer quiet spaces or minimal social interaction. Others thrive on structure and find comfort in sorting, categorising, or repeating patterns. Some display physical movements, such as hand-flapping when excited. Others talk a great deal, often about specific topics like trains or data systems, and may struggle to “read the room” or avoid interrupting. And then there are those who appear entirely “typical” but are expending enormous energy masking - consciously suppressing their natural behaviours to appear socially conventional. These employees often return home so exhausted from the effort of “acting normal” that they cannot fully engage with family or friends. Imagine performing social theatre every day, knowing the wrong gesture could be misread as disinterest or defiance.</p><p>All these are expressions of what we call the Autism Spectrum. It is not a scale from “low” to “high,” nor a ladder from Level 1 to 3. It is more like a lake of difference - wide, deep, and varied. One person may struggle with noise but excel at visual patterns; another may shut down in crowds yet find joy in precision and order. Autism isn’t about how autistic someone is - it’s about how autism shows up. Each person different. Each experience unique.</p><h2 id="when-different-is-different-enough">When “different” is different enough</h2><p>It’s fair to ask: if everyone is different, what makes one person’s difference Autism and another’s simply personality? After all, most workplaces already celebrate individuality, creativity, and “thinking outside the box.”</p><p>The answer lies in how deep and consistent the differences run. Autism isn’t a collection of quirks or preferences; it’s a stable neurological architecture that shapes how someone perceives, filters, and responds to the world. These aren’t situational traits - they’re built into how the brain connects and communicates.</p><p>For neurotypical people, social, sensory, and cognitive differences fluctuate depending on mood, environment, or experience. For autistic people, those differences are constant and structural. The wiring itself channels attention, perception, and communication along distinct pathways. It’s not about a degree of difference, but a kind of difference.</p><p>Autistic brains process information through networks that favour precision, pattern recognition, and depth of focus, sometimes at the expense of rapid social inference or effortless multitasking <sup id="fnref:34"><a href="#fn:34" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:35"><a href="#fn:35" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. Social meaning, for example, is decoded through logic rather than intuition. The brain doesn’t “fill in the blanks” of implied communication - it needs the blanks filled in. Likewise, sensory systems register stimuli that others might not even notice, turning what seems like mild background noise into an avalanche of competing data.</p><p>The result is a predictable pattern across multiple life domains:</p><ul><li>Communication and interaction follow clear, literal logic.</li><li>Sensory input is processed more intensely or unevenly.</li><li>Attention flows in single, deep channels rather than dispersed multitasking.</li><li>Transitions and unpredictability impose heavier executive-function loads.</li></ul><p>This consistency is what distinguishes autism from ordinary variation. Everyone occasionally misses a cue, seeks quiet, or focuses deeply. Autistic people experience those differences as the baseline - not the exception. They move through the world interpreting information on a different frequency, and that frequency remains constant regardless of circumstance.</p><p>Dr Lorna Wing described it <sup id="fnref:33"><a href="#fn:33" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> simply: <em>“It’s not that autistic people have special features; it’s that their whole perception of reality is organised differently.”</em></p><p>That’s why autism is not a set of “traits” that a person happens to have, but a distinct cognitive lens - one that influences how reality itself is experienced. When that difference intersects with environments designed for another lens, challenges appear. But the difference itself is neither wrong nor inferior. It is, quite literally, another way of being human.</p><h2 id="a-brief-detour-how-we-learned-to-misunderstand-autism">A brief detour: how we learned to misunderstand Autism</h2><p>For decades, autism was interpreted almost entirely through a medical or deficit lens. Early research in the mid-twentieth century viewed autistic traits as symptoms to be eliminated rather than patterns to be understood. Even as diagnostic frameworks improved, popular culture reinforced stereotypes of emotionless logic, child-like helplessness, or detached intellect. Those narratives quietly seeped into organisational life.</p><p>But the misunderstanding runs deeper than clinical history. Over the last century, social science itself codified social behaviour into moral behaviour. Traits that made people comfortable were labelled “good,” and those that didn’t were labelled “bad.” Eye contact became shorthand for honesty; a firm handshake signified confidence; smiling at the right moments suggested warmth and cooperation; interrupting seen as arrogance; quietness mistaken for disengagement.</p><p>These moralised interpretations of social behaviour - born from neurotypical majority norms - still dominate workplaces today. They appear in performance reviews (“lacks interpersonal warmth”), hiring rubrics (“strong eye contact”), and leadership training (“commanding presence”). None of these have anything to do with skill, integrity, or competence - but everything to do with conformity to a particular social rhythm.</p><p>Autistic communication simply runs on a different rhythm. Many autistic people process social signals literally, rely on direct language, and prefer depth over small talk. Their facial expressions, tone, or gestures may not align with expected conventions, but that has no bearing on their honesty, intent, or empathy. As psychologist Damian Milton <sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> observed in his Double Empathy theory, communication breakdowns between autistic and non-autistic people are bi-directional misunderstandings, not deficits on one side.</p><p>HR systems inherited both these medical and moral assumptions: framing autism as a set of deficits to fix and deviations to manage. The language followed suit: “high-functioning”, “low-functioning”, “disorder”, and “abnormal”. Each term subtly locates the “problem” inside the person rather than within the environment. The modern neurodiversity paradigm reverses that logic. It recognises autism as one natural variation of human cognition and argues that social and workplace barriers - not autistic traits - create disadvantage <sup id="fnref:36"><a href="#fn:36" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:37"><a href="#fn:37" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>.</p><p>This shift matters. Workplaces are still catching up. Many diversity frameworks remain trapped in the “medical–moral” hybrid - expecting individuals to adapt, then rewarding those who best mimic the majority. True inclusion begins when organisations stop reading difference as defiance and start recognising that social fluency is not the same as moral character.</p><p>Policies built on pathology focus on accommodation after the fact, rather than designing systems that work for everyone from the start. Understanding autism through this updated lens reframes inclusion from charity to competence: a matter of design, not diagnosis.</p><h2 id="a-business-case-for-those-who-dont-think-they-care">A business case (for those who don’t think they care)</h2><p>Even leaders unmoved by moral or social arguments should pay attention to the economics. Across developed economies, between 60 and 80 per cent of autistic adults remain unemployed or under-employed - an extraordinary waste of skill and investment <sup id="fnref:38"><a href="#fn:38" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>. This gap represents lost productivity, higher turnover, and billions in unused talent every year. Yet where organisations build the right conditions, autistic employees consistently show greater accuracy, reliability, and ethical integrity than their peers <sup id="fnref:25"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup>.</p><p>Inclusion is often framed through the language of law - the Americans with Disabilities Act (1990), the UK Equality Act (2010), the Canadian Human Rights Act (1985), and the Australian Disability Discrimination Act (1992). These frameworks are essential, but they are also reactive: they protect rights after someone has already been excluded or harmed. In practice, this means most corporate risk systems treat disability inclusion as a compliance safeguard, not as a strategic design principle.</p><p>That mindset creates a quiet paradox. When companies see disability as a potential legal exposure, they may unconsciously avoid hiring people they fear they’ll later have to “accommodate.” It’s not malicious - it’s risk aversion disguised as neutrality. But it’s also how opportunity is lost before talent ever reaches the interview.</p><p>The real advantage comes when inclusion is built upstream, before recruitment even begins. When hiring systems, job descriptions, and performance criteria are designed with neurodiversity in mind, compliance becomes almost irrelevant - because the environment itself no longer discriminates. This is the essence of universal design in HR: make systems functional for all minds, and the need for accommodation largely disappears.</p><p>Diverse cognitive teams outperform homogeneous ones because they approach problems differently. They notice the blind spots others miss, identify errors earlier, and challenge assumptions that would otherwise go untested. According to Deloitte’s Human Capital Trends analysis <sup id="fnref:26"><a href="#fn:26" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>, cognitive diversity can lift problem-solving performance by up to 20% and risk detection by nearly 30%.</p><p>For HR leaders focused on productivity, retention, and innovation, inclusion is not about avoiding lawsuits or managing liabilities. It’s about future-proofing the organisation itself - guarding against the risk of sameness, missed opportunity, and stagnant thinking. In that sense, inclusion is less a moral gesture and more a resilience strategy: it strengthens the business by expanding how it thinks, reacts, and adapts.</p><h2 id="autism-as-a-different-way-of-processing-information">Autism as a different way of processing information</h2><p>Autism isn’t defined by a single feature or deficit. It is a constellation of interconnected differences in how people perceive, filter, and act on information. These differences don’t reflect intelligence or motivation - they reflect a distinct way of organising experience.</p><p>For autistic people, those filters work differently. Research in sensory neuroscience shows that autistic brains assign unusually high precision to incoming data - sights, sounds, words, and even internal thoughts - meaning that information arrives with roughly equal importance instead of being automatically prioritised <sup id="fnref:39"><a href="#fn:39" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:35:1"><a href="#fn:35" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. What others’ brains dampen as background noise remains present, demanding conscious effort to sort and interpret. That extra filtering step consumes mental energy, which is why seemingly simple tasks - like following a meeting conversation in a noisy room - can be exhausting. It’s not distraction; it’s data overload.</p><p>Different theoretical frameworks attempt to explain these cognitive patterns. Frith and Happé’s weak central coherence theory <sup id="fnref:46"><a href="#fn:46" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup> suggests autistic people naturally focus on details rather than gestalt wholes. Others, like enhanced perceptual functioning theory <sup id="fnref:47"><a href="#fn:47" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup>, emphasise superior discrimination of sensory information. More recent predictive processing <sup id="fnref:48"><a href="#fn:48" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:39:1"><a href="#fn:39" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup> accounts explore differences in how autistic brains generate and update expectations about the world. Each framework illuminates particular aspects of autistic cognition without fully capturing its complexity. For workplace purposes, one especially practical lens is <strong>monotropism</strong>, which describes autistic cognition as tending toward narrow, deep streams of attention rather than spreading focus broadly across multiple inputs <sup id="fnref:34:1"><a href="#fn:34" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. This does not define autism, but it helps explain the familiar pattern of intense concentration, difficulty switching tasks, and strong preference for clarity that many autistic people report.</p><p>This attentional style can be an extraordinary advantage when work aligns with interest. It fuels the kind of sustained concentration behind breakthrough research, flawless code, and process excellence. When interest meets purpose, the autistic brain enters what Mihály Csíkszentmihályi called flow <sup id="fnref:40"><a href="#fn:40" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup> - a state of deep focus that can last hours without fatigue.</p><p>However, in environments that demand constant context switching or social multitasking, that same strength becomes a liability. Every interruption, ambiguous instruction, or “quick chat” triggers an expensive mental reorientation. Think of it like shifting a microscope lens mid-focus: each time the field changes, the entire system must recalibrate before clarity returns. Over a full workday, those micro-switches accumulate into what psychologists call executive-function load - the hidden cognitive tax of unpredictability.</p><p>Understanding this cost helps HR stop pathologising behaviour and start adjusting structure. The employee who resists “ad hoc meetings” may not be inflexible; they may be protecting their processing bandwidth. The person who prefers written instructions isn’t avoiding collaboration; they’re minimising ambiguity to stay accurate. Once these patterns are recognised as neurological, not attitudinal, productivity strategies shift from fixing people to fixing friction.</p><p>The idea of the spectrum is also widely misunderstood. Autism is not a straight line from “mild” to “severe.” It is more accurately a multidimensional profile - a pattern of traits that vary in intensity across domains such as communication, sensory experience, and attention amongst others. The specific mix, not the “level,” defines the individual.</p><p>To borrow an image: imagine a lake with countless depths and currents. Each autistic person moves through that water differently. Some need calm surfaces and predictable routines to stay afloat. Others dive deep into their interests and surface with insights no one else imagined. Some are driven by rules, others by creativity; many by both. The water isn’t shallow or deep - it’s simply varied. Autism isn’t about how autistic someone is; it’s about how autism shows up in their particular current.</p><p>For HR, understanding that variability is crucial. It reminds us that no policy, job description, or accommodation will fit everyone. The goal is not uniformity, but design elasticity - systems flexible enough to meet employees where their cognition naturally flows.</p><h2 id="communication-and-the-double-empathy-problem">Communication and the double empathy problem</h2><p>Modern communication theory, from Carl Rogers’ humanistic psychology <sup id="fnref:45"><a href="#fn:45" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup> to symbolic interactionism <sup id="fnref:43"><a href="#fn:43" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:44"><a href="#fn:44" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup>, has long posited that empathy is the foundation of mutual understanding. Empathy enables people to infer others’ intentions, predict reactions, and maintain social harmony - what Rogers described as a “necessary and sufficient condition” for genuine connection. But these theories were developed through neurotypical lenses. They assume that empathy operates in predictable ways.</p><p>Social communication differences - one of the two diagnostic domains of autism <sup id="fnref:31:1"><a href="#fn:31" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> - are among the most frequent fault lines in workplace misunderstanding. Autistic people often prioritise accuracy over tone. A manager’s “constructive feedback” may sound vague or contradictory; an autistic employee’s directness may be mistaken for rudeness.</p><p>Psychologist Damian Milton <sup id="fnref:15:1"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> proposed that these breakdowns aren’t caused by a lack of empathy, but by a mismatch in how empathy works between autistic and non-autistic people - a theory he called the Double Empathy Problem.</p><p>In traditional psychology, empathy may be described with two different meanings. Cognitive empathy is the ability to infer what someone else is thinking or intending. While emotional empathy, is the ability to feel and respond to another’s emotions. In simpler terms, cognitive empathy is when I understand how you feel, and emotional empathy is when I literally feel what you feel.</p><p>Research suggests that autistic people generally show typical or even heightened emotional empathy - they feel deeply, often to the point of overwhelm - but may struggle with cognitive empathy when social cues are subtle or inconsistent <sup id="fnref:41"><a href="#fn:41" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup>. Non-autistic people, conversely, tend to rely heavily on shared social conventions and can misread autistic communication because it follows a different logic and rhythm.</p><p>In other words, both sides experience empathy - just differently. The autistic person may miss a hint, while the neurotypical person misses sincerity. Each interprets the other through their own social code, and both can leave the exchange feeling unseen or disrespected.</p><p>Milton’s research, later expanded by Crompton and colleagues <sup id="fnref:42"><a href="#fn:42" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup>, shows that autistic-to-autistic communication is often fluent, intuitive, and mutually satisfying, while mixed-neurotype exchanges are more likely to falter. The lesson for HR is profound: communication breakdowns arise not because one party lacks empathy, but because both are operating from different empathic frameworks.</p><p>Once managers grasp this, they stop confusing clarity with conflict and begin recognising that “poor communication” may simply mean mismatched translation. Building systems that favour explicit, written, and predictable interaction closes that gap - not by asking one side to adapt more, but by levelling the interpretive field for both.</p><h2 id="bridging-forward-from-understanding-to-design">Bridging forward: from understanding to design</h2><p>So when we talk about autism at work, we are not describing deficits in people but mismatches between minds and systems. The differences we’ve explored - in perception, attention, and communication - only become problems when the workplace demands conformity to a single cognitive style.</p><p>The next chapter turns from definition to impact. It examines what happens when organisations fail to recognise these mismatches - the hidden costs of exclusion, burnout, and lost innovation - and why inclusion is not simply a moral gesture but a business imperative. By understanding the price of inaccessibility, we can begin designing workplaces that value difference as an asset rather than treating it as an exception.</p><p style="text-align:center">⁂</p><hr /><div class="d-flex justify-content-center align-items-center my-4"><a class="btn btn-lg btn-success" href="/books/buy-mvm/"><i class="fas fa-cart-shopping"></i> Buy this book</a></div><hr /><div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"><ol><li id="fn:31"><p>APS. (2022). <em>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-5-TR™</em> (A. P. Association, Ed. Fifth edition, text revision ed.). American Psychiatric Association Publishing. [ISBN: 978-0-89042-576-3]. <a href="#fnref:31" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:31:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:32"><p>WHO. (2024). <em>Clinical descriptions and diagnostic requirements for ICD-11 mental, behavioural and neurodevelopmental disorders (CDDR)</em>. World Health Organization. [ISBN: 978-92-4-007726-3]. <a href="#fnref:32" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:34"><p>Murray, D., Lesser, M., &amp; Lawson, W. (2005). Attention, monotropism and the diagnostic criteria for autism. <em>Autism</em>, <em>9</em>(2), 139–156. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361305051398">DOI: 10.1177/1362361305051398</a><a href="#fnref:34" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:34:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:35"><p>Robertson, C. E., &amp; Baron-Cohen, S. (2017). Sensory perception in autism. <em>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</em>, <em>18</em>(11), 671–684. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn.2017.112">DOI: 10.1038/nrn.2017.112</a><a href="#fnref:35" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:35:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:33"><p>Wing, L. (1996). <em>The autistic spectrum: A guide for parents and professionals</em>. Constable &amp; Robinson. [ISBN: 978-0094751606]. <a href="#fnref:33" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:15"><p>Milton, D. E. M. (2012). On the ontological status of autism: the ‘double empathy problem’. <em>Disability &amp; Society</em>, <em>27</em>(6), 883–887. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/09687599.2012.710008">DOI: 10.1080/09687599.2012.710008</a><a href="#fnref:15" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:15:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:36"><p>Singer, J. (1999). Why can’t you be normal for once in your life? From a ‘problem with no name’ to the emergence of a new category of difference. In M. Corker &amp; S. French (Eds.), *Disability Discourse *. [ISBN: 978-0335202225] <a href="#fnref:36" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:37"><p>Kapp, S. K., Gillespie-Lynch, K., Sherman, L. E., &amp; Hutman, T. (2013). Deficit, difference, or both? Autism and neurodiversity. <em>Developmental Psychology</em>, <em>49</em>(1), 59–71. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0028353">DOI: 10.1037/a0028353</a><a href="#fnref:37" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:38"><p>Howlin, P., &amp; Moss, P. (2012). Adults with Autism Spectrum Disorders. <em>The Canadian Journal of Psychiatry</em>, <em>57</em>(5), 275–283. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/070674371205700502">DOI: 10.1177/070674371205700502</a><a href="#fnref:38" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:25"><p>Austin, R. D., &amp; Pisano, G. P. (2017). Neurodiversity as a Competitive Advantage. <em>Harvard Business Review</em>. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/05/neurodiversity-as-a-competitive-advantage">http://hbr.org</a><a href="#fnref:25" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:26"><p>Mahto, M., Hogan, S. K., &amp; Sniderman, B. (2022). <em>A rising tide lifts all boats</em>. Deloitte Insights. <a href="https://deloitte.com/us/en/insights/topics/talent/neurodiversity-in-the-workplace.html">http://deloitte.com</a><a href="#fnref:26" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:39"><p>Pellicano, E., &amp; Burr, D. (2012). When the world becomes ‘too real’: a Bayesian explanation of autistic perception. <em>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</em>, <em>16</em>(10), 504–510. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tics.2012.08.009">DOI: 10.1016/j.tics.2012.08.009</a><a href="#fnref:39" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:39:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:46"><p>Happé, F., &amp; Frith, U. (2006). The Weak Coherence Account: Detail-focused Cognitive Style in Autism Spectrum Disorders. <em>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</em>, <em>36</em>(1), 5–25. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-005-0039-0">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-005-0039-0</a><a href="#fnref:46" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:47"><p>Mottron, L., Dawson, M., Soulières, I., Hubert, B., &amp; Burack, J. (2006). Enhanced Perceptual Functioning in Autism: An Update, and Eight Principles of Autistic Perception. <em>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</em>, <em>36</em>(1), 27–43. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-005-0040-7">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-005-0040-7</a><a href="#fnref:47" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:48"><p>Van De Cruys, S., Evers, K., Van Der Hallen, R., Van Eylen, L., Boets, B., de-Wit, L., &amp; Wagemans, J. (2014). Precise minds in uncertain worlds: Predictive coding in autism. <em>Psychological Review</em>, <em>121</em>(4), 649–675. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037665">DOI: 10.1037/a0037665</a><a href="#fnref:48" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:40"><p>Csíkszentmihályi, M. (2008). <em>Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience</em>. Harper Perennial Modern Classics. [ISBN: 978-0061339202]. <a href="#fnref:40" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:45"><p>Rogers, C. R. (1957). The necessary and sufficient conditions of therapeutic personality change. <em>Journal of Consulting Psychology</em>, <em>21</em>(2), 95–103. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/h0045357">DOI: 10.1037/h0045357</a><a href="#fnref:45" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:43"><p>Mead, G. H. (1934). <em>Mind, Self, and Society from the Standpoint of a Social Behaviorist</em>. Chicago. [ISBN: 978-0226516684] <a href="#fnref:43" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:44"><p>Blumer, H. (1986). <em>Symbolic interactionism: Perspective and method</em>. Univ of California Press. [ISBN: 0520056760]. <a href="#fnref:44" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:41"><p>Bird, G., &amp; Cook, R. (2013). Mixed emotions: the contribution of alexithymia to the emotional symptoms of autism. <em>Translational Psychiatry</em>, <em>3</em>(7), e285–e285. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/tp.2013.61">DOI: 10.1038/tp.2013.61</a><a href="#fnref:41" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:42"><p>Crompton, C. J., Ropar, D., Evans-Williams, C. V., Flynn, E. G., &amp; Fletcher-Watson, S. (2020). Autistic peer-to-peer information transfer is highly effective. <em>Autism</em>, <em>24</em>(7), 1704–1712. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361320919286">DOI: 10.1177/1362361320919286</a><a href="#fnref:42" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li></ol></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><category term="ASD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is Chapter One from the Book Modernising HR for Variant Minds: Autism - The Monotropic Mind.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh2-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh2-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Modernising HR: ADHD 🡢 Chapter 1</title><link href="/insights/mhr_adhd_chapter_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modernising HR: ADHD 🡢 Chapter 1" /><published>2025-08-18T07:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-12-30T13:38:04+11:00</updated><id>/insights/mhr-adhd-chapter-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/mhr_adhd_chapter_1.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The following is Chapter One from the book <a href="/books/mvm/"><strong>Modernising HR for Variant Minds: ADHD: The Tidal Brain</strong></a>.</p><p>Available on <a href="https://c1k.it/amad">Apple Books</a> and <a href="https://c1k.it/kmad">Kindle</a>.</p></blockquote><h1 id="chapter-1---the-tidal-brain">Chapter 1 - The Tidal Brain</h1><p><em>How shifting dopamine tides shape - rather than define - ADHD work rhythms, and how smart structures transform surges into strengths.</em></p><h2 id="adhd-at-work">ADHD at work</h2><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/bell-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Manager Confession</strong><br /><em>“When Sam joined my customer-success team, their energy was electric. They could solve a client’s labyrinth-level problem in minutes, yet somehow miss the weekly status call entirely. I bounced between awe and frustration - until I realised I was managing as if every brain runs the same operating system.”</em></td></tr></tbody></table><p>That small amount of honesty from a mid-level HR official helps to explain why this opener exists. The book you are holding is for practitioners, not clinicians; we will not teach you every diagnostic subtlety; but, in the next few pages you will walk away knowing exactly why Sam is brilliant <em>and</em> late, why reminders feel like nagging to them until five minutes before a deadline, and why “try harder” lands like an insult rather than a solution.</p><h4 id="two-everyday-snapshots">Two everyday snapshots</h4><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Mini case - time slips through the crack</strong><br /> Nina, an ADHD sales engineer, blocks ninety minutes before a client call to tailor slides. She checks one spec-sheet link, sees a pop-up about a firmware patch, and dives in. Ninety minutes later, the call starts. No slides. The fix takes five minutes; the missed opportunity costs the firm a potential six-figure sale.</td></tr><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Mini case - hyperfocus saves the bid</strong><br /> Forty-eight hours before a public-sector tender closes, the documentation team finds the encryption appendix full of errors. Ethan, another ADHD employee, volunteers. He locks in at 19:30, surfaces at dawn with thirty annotated pages, and the bid ships on time - winning the deal by three points on technical merit.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Same condition, opposite business outcomes. The rest of this chapter explains why.</p><h2 id="adhd-in-ten-sentences">ADHD in ten sentences</h2><p>The heart of Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is a dysregulation of the brain’s dopamine system - a key driver of interneuron communication and a major influence on the reward-and-priority circuitry of the wider prefrontal networks. When this critical brain function does not operate normally, the outcome can vary from difficulty initiating tasks to bursts of concentrated attention, often called hyperfocus. That’s why an ADHD person can overlook a simple compliance-form deadline yet map a complex network failure at 3 a.m. in microscopic detail. In other words, variable attention is a downstream symptom, not the root cause. These variant brain functions often lead to what is perceived as attention swings, and is often mistaken for bad character or laziness <sup id="fnref:25"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p><p>That neurological variability isn’t rare; in adults the global diagnosed prevalence hovers around 2.5% <sup id="fnref:20"><a href="#fn:20" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, while the symptomatic screening scale indicate ≈6-7%, meaning that about three in every hundred employees to have ADHD that meets full clinical criteria, or, if you include undiagnosed and sub-threshold cases, the pool can rise to one in fifteen - so odds are there’s someone on your floor right now who doesn’t yet know they have ADHD traits.</p><p>Although diagnostic manuals list three presentations - mostly inattentive, mostly hyperactive-impulsive, and combined - real-world expression is a messy spectrum. Many ADHD people, particularly women and groups who were culturally marginalised, were missed as children because their symptoms resembled day-dreaming, inner restlessness, or perfect note-taking that covered the turmoil beneath <sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. Late identification and misdiagnosis are thus common; the emotional whiplash of “how did nobody spot this earlier” walks into your HR office alongside the accommodation request <sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. And there is no “fix” for it, ADHD is a life-long condition.</p><h2 id="myth-fact-reality-check">Myth-fact reality check</h2><p><strong>Myth:</strong><em>ADHD people just need to try harder.</em></p><p><strong>Fact:</strong><em>Harder has been tried; inconsistent dopamine timing blocks voluntary effort <sup id="fnref:25:1"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</em></p><p><strong>Myth:</strong><em>Medication fixes everything.</em></p><p><strong>Fact:</strong><em>Even optimally medicated adults still benefit from structural supports <sup id="fnref:16"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.</em></p><p><strong>Myth:</strong><em>ADHD employees are too erratic for leadership roles.</em></p><p><strong>Fact:</strong><em>Founders with higher ADHD-symptom scores are over-represented among high-growth start-ups <sup id="fnref:23"><a href="#fn:23" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.</em></p><h2 id="the-dopamine-dance">The dopamine dance</h2><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Mini case - a typical career</strong><br /><br /><strong>School years:</strong> Sam aces creative writing but forgets to submit it, pulls sparkling grades in subjects fuelled by novelty, flounders where rote repetition rules. Report cards alternate between “gifted” and “distracted”. <br /><br /><strong>Early career:</strong> Deadlines morph into all-nighters. A graduate program supervisor praises “crisis wizardry” yet files “needs to plan ahead” on the same review. Sam self-educates on three coding languages in evenings - pure dopamine curiosity - but can’t keep expense reports on schedule. <br /><br /><strong>Mid-career leap:</strong> With coaching and the right stimulant, performance stabilises - until promotion adds a meeting-rich calendar. Executive-function load climbs; masking the struggle drains energy, anxiety creeps in. Without systemic scaffolds Sam risks burnout even while colleagues perceive “high potential”.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Think of dopamine as the brain’s project-manager-plus-barista: it gives priority <em>and</em> provides the jolt of inspiration to get going. In ADHD circuitry, delivery service is erratic - sometimes early, sometimes non-existent and sometimes in excess and sometimes in deficit. Routine chores (expenses, required e-learning, monthly measurements) present with no dopamine attached, so they slide down the mental escalator. On the other hand, high-novelty or high-stakes assignments or problem solving cause a flood that sets off a turbo-charged sprint at 3 a.m. the night before board papers are due.</p><p>Neuroscience shows dopamine has two different rhythms. <strong>Phasic bursts</strong> are the sudden, sharp waves that occur when something suddenly matters, while <strong>tonic firing</strong> is the slow, background drip that keeps attention in neutral <sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>. In ADHD phasic spikes occur later and shoot higher than usual, while the tonic baseline is lower than usual <sup id="fnref:25:2"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Imagine a harbour during spring tide, when the water rushes in and floods the pier after pulling back so far that you can see the sandbars. Routine e-learning, monthly metrics, and expense forms are like wading through mud at low tide. New client fire drills, hack-day prototypes, and unexpected pattern recognition are all examples of high tide.</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/lightbulb-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Insight:</strong><em>Why it matters for HR</em><br /><br /><em>Workplace design must happen at low tide.</em> Calendars, checkpoints and feedback scripts get locked in while the water is calm, because that is when the employee most needs the external map. <em>Performance can peak at high tide.</em> Those same phasic surges drive hyperfocus, crisis composure and idea generation. In other words, the condition’s greatest management liability and its sharpest competitive edge are two faces of the same tidal cycle. <br /><br /> A longitudinal study of stimulant-treated adults found that when projects supplied clear schedules and visible progress cues, baseline (tonic-state) productivity rose by 27% - and the phasic highs still delivered 40% faster bug-resolution times than non-ADHD peers <sup id="fnref:29"><a href="#fn:29" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>. Structure does not blunt the surge; it lets the surge hit the right target.&lt;/p&gt;</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Functional MRI studies show reduced activity in the ventral striatum during anticipation of low-reward tasks <sup id="fnref:18"><a href="#fn:18" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>. Behavioural economists neatly sum this up: People with ADHD have a <em>present-bias</em> curve so steep that “next Tuesday” and “never” seem oddly similar until Tuesday becomes “now” <sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup>. ADHD advocates joke that their brains have only two modes; Now and Not-Now.</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/thumbtack-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Manager cue:</strong><br /> Build the workflow so the low-dopamine moments rely on rails (pre-blocked work sessions, automatic nudges, shared Kanban) and the high-dopamine moments land where speed and creativity pay off (brainstorm sprints, last-mile troubleshooting, client escalations). The tidal rhythm becomes an asset, not a risk.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Interestingly, emotional regulation rides the same neuro-circuit that governs the tidal swing of dopamine, which is why Sam’s cheeks can flush crimson at either praise or critique. The reaction often puzzles managers: you thank Sam for “saving the day,” Sam shrugs it off as “just doing my job,” yet one hour later a mild note about font size feels like a gut-punch. This paradox is best understood through Rejection-Sensitive Dysphoria (RSD), a form of neurologically amplified social pain reported by many ADHD adults <sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>. Because ADHD heightens threat detection, the brain flags possible rejection as urgent, giving negative cues priority access to attention and memory while letting positive cues slide by almost unnoticed <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>. A passing remark you meant as routine coaching can hit Sam like a red-alert siren. Instead of leaving a gap that might fester, give the context and the core message up front and in writing - but stay in the room (or on the call). A short note that states the purpose (“Two quick tweaks to tighten the slide deck, add clout to the pitch; goal is client-ready by 4 p.m.”) lets Sam read the exact words, check for hidden landmines, and ask clarifying questions on the spot. Seeing the text anchors working memory; hearing your steady tone signals the sky isn’t falling. Follow with one specific success, one concrete improvement, and agree on the very next action. The brain now has a roadmap, not a riddle, so the threat response winds down, and the cognitive engine can engage.</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/thumbtack-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Manager cue:</strong><br /> Safety first, then standards. Put the feedback in a brief written stub, share your screen or slide it across the table, then walk through it together. The clarity quells rumination; collaboration turns potential rejection into joint problem-solving - not judge and defendant. The emotional load drops; the cognitive engine switches on.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="signature-challenges-in-the-workplace">Signature challenges in the workplace</h2><p>Time blindness is the headline act. Ask an ADHD employee for an estimate and you may receive optimism untethered to arithmetic. It is not dishonesty; the temporal self-monitor of the brain is simply missing batteries <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>. Combine that with executive-function gridlock - difficulties starting, sequencing and switching tasks - and the typical corporate day becomes an obstacle course.</p><p>Meetings layer on another hazard: working-memory deficits. Even if Sam can remember every specification of the client’s software stack from three years ago, he may forget point 1 by the time you reach point 4 when agenda items fly in fast succession. Add an open-plan office with fluorescent lighting, and you have a live sensory distraction demonstration.</p><p>The perplexing lag between knowing and doing is known as “initiation inertia.” Sam can visualise every step - open the spreadsheet, pull the data from the previous month, and drop it into the dashboard - but he simply won’t get started. Neuroimaging research indicates that the stall starts when low-tonic dopamine is unable to provide the slight surge of perceived importance that typically initiates action <sup id="fnref:25:3"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. The prefrontal cortex hesitates in the absence of a chemical “go” signal, and two types of drag simultaneously take over. First comes decision paralysis, where the task feels more difficult than it actually is because every micro-choice (which tab, which field, which font) vies for limited executive bandwidth <sup id="fnref:2:1"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>. Optimal Arousal Theory is the basis for the second strategic delay. Sam’s brain knows that a phasic dopamine surge will make the work nearly effortless once the deadline approaches, so starting early feels inefficient. After all, why push mud uphill now when a tide will lift it later <sup id="fnref:24"><a href="#fn:24" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup>? Deeper down, however, a more subtle motivation may be concealed: the worry that if you finish too soon, you’ll have a period of under-stimulating time, which many ADHD sufferers find more punishing than the task itself <sup id="fnref:21"><a href="#fn:21" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup> - ADHD individuals literally fear boredom. The outcome is an odd combination of involuntary procrastination and paralysis, neither of which gives way to a quick “just get started.” An external spark - an accountability check-in, a visible countdown clock, a coworker working concurrently- breaks the impasse until the brain’s natural chemistry catches up.</p><p>Ignored, these conflict areas lead to performance-review heartache, presenteeism, or quiet quitting masquerading as tiredness <sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup>.</p><table class="box"><thead><tr><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong class="h3">Optimal Arousal Theory</strong><br /><br /> … was developed long before ADHD was listed in diagnostic manuals. Its origins date back to 1908, when American psychologists Robert Yerkes and John Dodson demonstrated that mice learned a task most quickly at a middle-range stimulus intensity level: too little stimulation resulted in slow learning, while too much caused disarray <sup id="fnref:28"><a href="#fn:28" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup>. Donald Hebb expanded the concept to humans half a century later, suggesting that the brain looks for a “just-right” zone of cortical arousal and will take conscious or unconscious action to bring it back whenever it deviates <sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup>. <br /><br /> In the 1970s, Hebb’s thread was picked up by researchers looking into children’s hyperactivity. Susan Zentall’s classroom experiments found that children who were later recognised as ADHD performed better on academic tasks when they were allowed to move around or listen to background noise, and worse when they were made to sit still and silent. She explicitly framed this pattern in terms of Optimal Arousal <sup id="fnref:30"><a href="#fn:30" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup>. These behavioural findings were linked to dopamine-driven fluctuations in the brain’s alerting networks by later neurobiological research, such as Edmund Sonuga-Barke’s dual-pathway theory and Emmanuel Sergeant’s state-regulation model <sup id="fnref:19"><a href="#fn:19" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:22"><a href="#fn:22" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup>. <br /><br /> Put simply, the theory says that each brain has a preferred stimulation bandwidth. In its tonic state, an ADHD brain sits lower than the majority of neurotypical brains, which automatically hover there, i.e. ADHD brains are, in their unaroused mode, dysfunctional. Thus, it unconsciously looks for additional input - fidgeting, novelty-hunting, crisis-chasing - to enter the “Goldilocks” zone until phasic dopamine surges provide sufficient arousal. Following the discovery of this connection to dopamine timing, the Optimal Arousal Theory emerged as a key lens through which to explain why ADHD behaviour fluctuates between under-engagement and laser-like intensity and why managers can effectively use external structure instead of self-discipline lectures. This is also why off-the-shelf personality inventories often misclassify ADHD potential, but more of that in Chapter 4.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="unequalled-advantages-when-conditions-are-right">Unequalled advantages (when conditions are right)</h2><p>Flip the script, and those same neurological traits power serious competitive edge. Hyperfocus is the proverbial super-laser on bleeding-edge puzzles: cybersecurity incident rooms, forensic audits, emergency logistics, late-stage product bugs, critical event management. Hyperfocus weapons-grade problem-solving. Pattern recognition often exceeds neurotypical peers since the ADHD attentional filter lets in more stimuli; correlations pop where others see static <sup id="fnref:26"><a href="#fn:26" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:27"><a href="#fn:27" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup>.</p><p>Dopamine-driven novelty-seeking fuels idea generation. Evidence points in the same direction wherever you look. A multi-country study of entrepreneurs showed that individuals with higher ADHD-symptom scores engaged more often in innovative and internationalising activities, which in turn raised their ventures’ growth aspirations <sup id="fnref:23:1"><a href="#fn:23" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. Furthermore, a Deloitte Insights review of major neuro-inclusion programmes found that “teams with neurodivergent professionals in some roles can be 30 per cent more productive than those without them” <sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup>. Combine that with crisis-mode calm - paradoxically, ADHD cortisol spikes sharpen decision speed - and you have talent exactly suited for zero-to-one product sprints or customer-escalation triage.</p><p>The upside is real.</p><h2 id="why-work-harder-fails---and-what-works-instead">Why “work harder” fails - and what works instead</h2><p>Most performance guides advise staff members to set early deadlines, divide large projects into smaller ones and schedule backwards. None of those strategies alter the fundamental dopamine-timing flaw, thus an ADHD brain just experiences those effects as more administrative <sup id="fnref:2:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>. That’s why Sam tried three highly rated productivity apps last quarter and still filed the vendor contract late: every app assumed Sam would remember to open it, interpret its dashboard and act on it unaided.</p><p>What works is an externalised structure seen by the entire team, not merely buried on Sam’s phone. Research on ADHD coaching, CBT and workplace accommodations shows the largest gains when the cue lives outside the individual - on a calendar everyone sees, in an automated prompt the system sends, or in a physical or digital Kanban board that makes status obvious <sup id="fnref:16:1"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup><sup>,</sup><sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">25</a></sup>.</p><table class="table"><thead><tr><th>Executive-function pinch-point</th><th>Shared scaffold (example)</th><th>Why it works</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Time blindness</td><td>Calendar invites with time-boxed micro-deliverables (“Draft intro 09:00-10:30”, not “Work on report”)</td><td>Turns an abstract deadline into a visible block; the invite itself triggers action <sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">26</a></sup>.</td></tr><tr><td>Initiation inertia</td><td>Just-in-time prompts - an automatic Slack nudge 48h and 4h before hand-in</td><td>Supplies the missing <em>now</em> tag; brief digital nudges outperform monthly check-ins <sup id="fnref:16:2"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.</td></tr><tr><td>Sequencing overload</td><td>Explicit licence to <em>draft in bullet fragments</em>, then polish later</td><td>Aligns work with natural motivation peaks; removes perfectionism bottleneck <sup id="fnref:29:1"><a href="#fn:29" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>.</td></tr><tr><td>Sensory distraction</td><td>A standing offer of noise-cancelling headphones or a bookable quiet pod</td><td>Lets the employee modulate input without ad-hoc permission, protecting focus <sup id="fnref:12:1"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">26</a></sup>.</td></tr></tbody></table><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/thumbtack-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Manager cue:</strong><br /> The difference is where the prompt lives. <br /><br /> If the cue sits only on the employee’s personal device, it still depends on their fluctuating executive function. Place the cue in the shared workflow, and the system - not the ADHD brain - does the reminding.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>A Deloitte Insights survey <sup id="fnref:5:1"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup> of knowledge-work teams show that adoption of shared-cue practices, like colour-coded Kanban boards, auto-reminders and agendas shared 24h in advance, delivered a 28% drop in missed deadlines and no loss of throughput for neurotypical colleagues. Fundamentally, universal design pulled variant minds firmly into the game and raised the floor for everyone. None of these interventions calls for a medical degree or a costly software licence; rather, they call for managerial flexibility anchored in outcome measurements rather than process orthodoxy.</p><p>Thus, an ideal outcome would look like this:</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Mini case - Sam’s productive week</strong><br /><br /><strong>Monday:</strong> Alex, the product manager, begins a launch sprint on Monday. Alex previously sent out an email with a Friday night deadline; this time, Alex makes calendar invites for micro-milestones: draft by Wednesday at 17:00, outline by Tuesday at 14:00, and polish window on Thursday night. Six and two hours prior to each checkpoint, Slack reminders automatically go off.<br /><br /><strong>Tuesday:</strong> The time-boxed block transforms an abstract goal into an instantaneous cue when Sam opens the outline invite. Sam’s card slides to “in progress” on the team wall, which eliminates the need for everyone, including Sam, to keep track of who is on what.<br /><br /><strong>Wednesday:</strong> Open-plan noise spikes on Wednesdays. Sam turns on his firm-supplied, permission-implied-by-policy noise-cancelling headphones. The draft lands at 16:48 and slides to “awaiting review” on the board, preventing derailment thanks to the sensory toggle. <br /><br /><strong>Thursday:</strong> QA feedback is disseminated. Revisions conclude within the allotted polishing block, and Sam’s rejection-sensitive dysphoria remains silent because feedback follows a script: one positive note, one actionable correction if needed. No one works past 19:00, and the team turns over to Marketing on time.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Sam didn’t have to download any additional apps or summon hidden will-power at any point. The heavy lifting was done by shared scaffolds, which included external memory, visible time, sensory control, and clear feedback.</p><h2 id="what-else-might-show-up">What else might show up?</h2><p>Rarely does ADHD show up alone. According to a dimensional analysis of 60 studies, roughly six in ten ADHD adults fit full criteria for an anxiety disorder and roughly one-third for a depressive disorder <sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">27</a></sup>. Medication and counselling can reduce impairment scores; in workplaces that demand constant self-camouflage, that progress collapses. Employees pour energy into “looking normal” instead of performing their jobs. The resulting cognitive fatigue drags symptoms back to baseline.</p><p>Diagnostic blind-spots magnify that risk. Women and gender-diverse ADHD people are routinely identified years later than men, in part because inattentive or internalising profiles violate the cultural stereotype of the disruptive boy in the classroom; long-form reviews report delays of five-plus years and higher rates of misdiagnosed anxiety or mood disorder <sup id="fnref:17"><a href="#fn:17" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">28</a></sup>. Race and ethnicity add another layer: a ten-year cohort study of more than five million Kaiser Permanente members showed that Asian, Black and Hispanic adults were 20-40% less likely than White peers to receive an ADHD code even when symptom counts and impairment levels matched <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">29</a></sup>. Under-recognition means those employees enter HR processes without a label, but not without the executive-function load.</p><p>And one of the most dangerous outcomes of all this misinterpretation is when chronic under-stimulation begins to resemble clinical depression, particularly for workers whose ADHD tends to be quiet or internal.</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/lightbulb-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Insight:</strong> For ADHD minds, boredom isn’t trivial - <i>it’s dangerous</i>. Extended periods of low stimulation can trigger an emotional state that mimics clinical depression: fatigue, hopelessness, disinterest, even suicidal ideation. And too often, this state is misdiagnosed, leading to treatment plans that miss the root cause: dopamine starvation. This is not a failure of resilience; it’s a neurological consequence of how <em>lifelong</em> brain function shapes experience for these individuals. Environments that fail to engage the ADHD brain aren’t just unproductive (underutilising a brain that can do more) - they’re mentally hazardous.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>The implication is clear for HR. First, create universal-design practices - clear written agendas, shared task boards, quiet-focus options - that any employee can use without declaring a diagnosis. Second, create a voluntary, confidential, low-friction accommodation-to-need disclosure path free from documentation. When the base environment aligns with the ADHD nervous system, stimulant prescriptions and coaching aren’t forced to fight the workplace too. They finally get to work with it.</p><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/lightbulb-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Insight:</strong> ADHD rarely walks into a clinical office alone - and it rarely walks out with the right label. The DSM-5-TR references ADHD in over sixty pages linking it with several differential diagnoses, including anxiety, depression, personality disorders, and trauma-related conditions <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">30</a></sup>. This book won’t turn you into a diagnostician, but it will help you recognise that employees with seemingly inconsistent, emotional, or hard-to-categorise behaviours aren’t difficult - they’re navigating a brain you haven’t been trained to understand.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="micro-case-two-emails-two-outcomes">Micro-case: two emails, two outcomes</h2><table class="offset"><thead><tr><th></th><th></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Scenario A</strong><br /><br /> Friday 18:47, subject line “URGENT - need slide deck by Monday”. Manager attaches last year’s template and logs off. Sam sees the email Sunday night at 16:10, hyperfocuses, pulls an all-nighter, delivers at 04:52, then sleeps through Monday’s stand-up. Performance note: “unreliable”.</td></tr><tr><td><img src="/assets/img/insights/2025/clipboard-32x32.svg" alt="" /></td><td><strong>Scenario B</strong><br /><br /> Same request, but the manager schedules the email for Monday 09:05 with three bullet checkpoints: <br /> ● <em>Draft headlines by 13:00 today.</em><br /> ● <em>First slide pass by 16:00.</em><br /> ● <em>Polishing window 18:00-19:00. Calendar invites embedded.</em><br /><br /> Sam completes in two manageable bursts, attends the stand-up, gets kudos.</td></tr></tbody></table><p>The difference never about will-power, ability, or Sam’s commitment to the team. Pulling an all-nighter proves Sam has plenty of grit, and the slides in both versions of the tale were equally polished. What changed was the runway the manager built. Sam’s invisible, last-minute deadline let time work against him in the first scenario, thus the outcome appeared to be flakiness and inadequate cooperation. The visible checkpoints in the second scenario handled timekeeping and let everyone see consistent development. Without a performance plan, a pep-talk, or a single extra dollar of budget, the manager turned the same employee from “high-maintenance” to “high-value” by moving the emphasis from personal virtue to shared structure.</p><p style="text-align:center">&#x2042;</p><h2 id="reality-check">Reality check</h2><p>ADHD is not a passing phase or a motivational flaw - it is a lifetime variation in how the dopamine system of the brain pulses and times its signals <sup id="fnref:25:4"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Routine tasks never seem urgent when that timing runs late; when it surges, the same brain can lock into hyperfocus and map a complex problem at lightning speed. Medication can help to smooth out peaks and valleys; coaching can teach workarounds; neither rewires the circuitry. Though the outward symptoms vary, the condition lasts all of life <sup id="fnref:2:3"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>.</p><p>What makes the biggest workplace difference is managing, not “fixing,” the biology: visible timelines, shared reminders, quiet-focus options and feedback given in clear, concrete language makes the biggest workplace difference. Install those scaffolds for one of your colleagues with ADHD, and the whole team gains from better priorities and simpler teamwork. Laziness never entered the picture; consistent dopamine timing does; and smart design can bridge that gap for all.</p><p style="text-align:center">&#x2042;</p><hr /><div class="d-flex justify-content-center align-items-center my-4"><a class="btn btn-lg btn-info" href="/books/buy-mvm/"><i class="fas fa-cart-shopping"></i> Buy this book</a></div><hr /><div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"><ol><li id="fn:25"><p>Volkow, N. D., Wang, G.J., Kollins, S. H., Wigal, T. L., Newcorn, J. H., Telang, F., Fowler, J. S., Zhu, W., Logan, J., Yeming Ma, Pradhan, K., Wong, C., &amp; Swanson, J. M. (2009). Evaluating Dopamine Reward Pathway in ADHD. Journal of the American Medical Association. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2009.1308">DOI: 10.1001/jama.2009.1308</a><a href="#fnref:25" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:25:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a><a href="#fnref:25:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a><a href="#fnref:25:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>4</sup></a><a href="#fnref:25:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>5</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:20"><p>Simon, V., Czobor, P., Bálint, S., &amp; Bitter, I. (2009). Prevalence and Correlates of Adult ADHD: Meta-analysis. The British Journal of Psychiatry. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1192/bjp.bp.107.048827">DOI: 10.1192/bjp.bp.107.048827</a><a href="#fnref:20" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:15"><p>Quinn, P. O., &amp; Madhoo, M. (2014). A Review of ADHD in Women and Girls. European Psychiatry. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4088/PCC.13r01596">DOI: 10.4088/PCC.13r01596</a><a href="#fnref:15" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:7"><p>French, B., Daley, D., Groom, M., &amp; Cassidy, S. (2023). Risks Associated with Undiagnosed ADHD and/or Autism: A Mixed-method Systematic Review. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/10870547231176862">DOI: 10.1177/10870547231176862</a><a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:16"><p>Ramsay, J. R., &amp; Rostain, A. L. (2008). Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy for Adult ADHD: An Integrative Psychosocial and Medical Approach. Taylor &amp; Francis [CAM]. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203844519">DOI: 10.4324/9780203844519</a><a href="#fnref:16" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:16:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a><a href="#fnref:16:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:23"><p>Stappers, J., &amp; Andries, P. (2024). Entrepreneurs’ Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Symptoms and Growth Aspirations: The Moderating Role of Team and Industry Characteristics. International Entrepreneurship and Management Journal. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11365-023-00888-9">DOI: 10.1007/s11365-023-00888-9</a><a href="#fnref:23" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:23:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:8"><p>Grace, A. A. (2016). Dysregulation of the Dopamine System in the Pathophysiology of Schizophrenia and Depression. Nature Reviews Neuroscience. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn.2016.57">DOI: 10.1038/nrn.2016.57</a><a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:29"><p>Young, S., &amp; Bramham, J. (2012). Cognitive-Behavioural Therapy for ADHD in Adolescents and Adults: A Psychological Guide to Practice. Wiley-Blackwell. [ISBN: 978-1119960737] <a href="#fnref:29" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:29:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:18"><p>Schultz, W. (2013). Updating Dopamine Reward Signals. Current Opinion in Neurobiology. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.conb.2012.11.012">DOI: 10.1016/j.conb.2012.11.012</a><a href="#fnref:18" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:13"><p>Kurth-Nelson, Z., &amp; Redish, A. D. (2009). Temporal-Difference Reinforcement Learning with Distributed Representations. PLoS ONE. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0007362">DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0007362</a><a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:6"><p>Dodson, W. R., Modestino, E. J., Ceritoğlu, H. T., &amp; Zayed, B. (2024). Rejection Sensitivity Dysphoria in Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder. In Acta Scientific Neurology. <a href="http://actascientific.com/ASNE/pdf/ASNE-07-0762.pdf">http://actascientific.com/…0762.pdf</a><a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:3"><p>Beheshti, A., Chavanon, M. L., &amp; Christiansen, H. (2020). Emotion Dysregulation in Adults with Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: A Meta-analysis. BMC Psychiatry. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-020-2442-7">DOI: 10.1186/s12888-020-2442-7</a><a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:2"><p>Barkley, R. A. (2018). Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: A Handbook for Diagnosis and Treatment (4th ed.). Guilford Press. [ISBN: 978-1462517725] <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:2:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a><a href="#fnref:2:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a><a href="#fnref:2:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>4</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:24"><p>Steel, P. (2007). The Nature of Procrastination: A Meta-analytic and Theoretical Review of Quintessential Self-regulatory Failure. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.133.1.65">DOI: 10.1037/0033-2909.133.1.65</a><a href="#fnref:24" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:21"><p>Sirois, F. M., &amp; Pychyl, T. A. (2013). Procrastination and the Priority of Short-Term Mood Regulation: Consequences for Future Self. Social and Personality Psychology Compass. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/spc3.12011">DOI: 10.1111/spc3.12011</a><a href="#fnref:21" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:11"><p>Kessler, R. C., Adler, L., Ames, M., Barkley, R. A., Birnbaum, H., Greenberg, P., Johnston, J. A., Spencer, T., &amp; Üstün, T. B. (2005). The Prevalence and Effects of Adult Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder on Work Performance in a Nationally Representative Sample of Workers. Journal of Occupational and Environmental Medicine. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1097/01.jom.0000166863.33541.39">DOI: 10.1097/01.jom.0000166863.33541.39</a><a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:28"><p>Yerkes, R. M., &amp; Dodson, J. D. (1908). The Relation of Strength of Stimulus to Rapidity of Habit‐formation. In Journal of Comparative Neurology and Psychology. <a href="https://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Yerkes/Law/">https://psychclassics.yorku.ca</a><a href="#fnref:28" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:9"><p>Hebb, D. O. (1955). Drives and the C.N.S. (Conceptual Nervous System). In Psychological Review. <a href="https://yorku.ca/pclassic/Hebb/">https://yorku.ca</a><a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:30"><p>Zentall, S. S. (1975). Optimal Stimulation as a Theoretical Basis of Hyperactivity. Exceptional Children. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1939-0025.1975.tb01185.x">DOI: 10.1111/j.1939-0025.1975.tb01185.x</a><a href="#fnref:30" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:19"><p>Sergeant, J. A. (2000). The Cognitive‐Energetic Model: An Empirical Approach to Attention‐Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0149-7634(99)00060-3">DOI: 10.1016/S0149-7634(99)00060-3</a><a href="#fnref:19" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:22"><p>Sonuga-Barke, E. J. S. (2002). Psychological Heterogeneity in ADHD - A Dual Pathway Model of Behaviour and Cognition. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0166-4328(01)00432-6">DOI: 10.1016/S0166-4328(01)00432-6</a><a href="#fnref:22" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:26"><p>White, H. A. (2018). Creative cognition in ADHD. Personality and Individual Differences. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1939-0025.1975.tb01185.x">DOI: 10.1111/j.1939-0025.1975.tb01185.x</a><a href="#fnref:26" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:27"><p>White, H. A., &amp; Shah, P. (2011). Creative Style and Achievement in Adults with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder. Personality and Individual Differences. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2010.12.015">DOI: 10.1016/j.paid.2010.12.015</a><a href="#fnref:27" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:5"><p>Deloitte. (2022). A rising tide lifts all boats: Creating a better work environment for all by embracing neurodiversity. Retrieved June 2025 from <a href="https://deloitte.com/content/dam/insights/articles/2024/us164891_cir-career-paths-and-critical-success-factors-for-neurodivergent-workforce/di-cir-career-paths-and-critical-success-factors-for-neurodivergent-workforce.pdf">https://deloitte.com/…workforce.pdf</a><a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:5:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:14"><p>Prevatt, F., &amp; Yelland, S. (2015). An Empirical Evaluation of ADHD Coaching in College Students. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1087054713480036">DOI: 10.1177/1087054713480036</a><a href="#fnref:14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:12"><p>Kooij, S. J., Bejerot, S., Blackwell, A., Caci, H., Casas-Brugué, M., Carpentier, P. J., Edvinsson, D., Fayyad, J., Foeken, K., Fitzgerald, M., Gaillac, V., Ginsberg, Y., Henry, C., Krause, J., Lensing, M. B., Manor, I., Niederhofer, H., Nunes-Filipe, C., Ohlmeier, M. D.,…Asherson, P. (2010). European consensus statement on diagnosis and treatment of adult ADHD. In European Psychiatry. <a href="https://biomedcentral.com/1471-244X/10/67">http://biomedcentral.com</a><a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a><a href="#fnref:12:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p></li><li id="fn:10"><p>Katzman, M. A., Bilkey, T. S., Chokka, P. R., Fallu, A., &amp; Klassen, L. J. (2017). Adult ADHD and Comorbid Disorders: Clinical Implications of a Dimensional Approach. BMC Psychiatry. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-017-1463-3">DOI: 10.1186/s12888-017-1463-3</a><a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:17"><p>Rucklidge, J. J. (2010). Gender Differences in Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder. Psychiatric Clinics. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psc.2010.01.006">DOI: 10.1016/j.psc.2010.01.006</a><a href="#fnref:17" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:4"><p>Chung, W., Jiang, S.-F., Paksarian, D., Nikolaidis, A., Castellanos, F. X., Merikangas, K. R., &amp; Milham, M. P. (2019). Trends in the Prevalence and Incidence of Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Among Adults and Children of Different Racial and Ethnic Groups. JAMA Network Open. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.14344">DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.14344</a><a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:1"><p>American Psychiatric Association. (2022). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5-TR (5th, Text Revision ed.). APS. [ISBN: 978-0890425756] <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li></ol></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><category term="ADHD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is Chapter One from the Book Modernising HR for Variant Minds: ADHD: The Tidal Brain.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh1-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/mh1-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work</title><link href="/insights/workability_expo_2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" /><published>2025-08-08T10:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-12-11T15:13:37+11:00</updated><id>/insights/the-untapped-potential-of-autism-at-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/workability_expo_2025.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-untapped-potential-of-autism-at-work">The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work</h1><blockquote><p>The following content was presented at the Sydney Workability Expo 2025 on 8<sup>th</sup> August 2025.</p></blockquote><div class="row justify-content-center"><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s01.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The Untapped Potential of Autism at Work" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s02.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Why it matters" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s03.jpg" /><ul><li>Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) (2024) <i>Autism in Australia, 2022: Key findings in plain language</i>. Canberra: <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/articles/autism-australia-2022">ABS</a>.</li><li>Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) (2025) <i>Labour Force, Australia: June 2025</i>. Canberra: <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/labour/employment-and-unemployment">ABS</a>.</li><li>Financial Times (2024) 'UK employers eye competitive advantage in hiring neurodivergent workers', <i><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/e692c571-b56b-425a-a7a0-3d8ae617080b">Financial Times</a></i>, 18 October.</li><li>Buescher, A., Cidav, Z., Knapp, M. &amp; Mandell, D. (2014) 'Costs of Autism Spectrum Disorders in the United Kingdom and the United States', <i>JAMA Pediatrics</i>, 168(8), pp. 721–728. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.210">DOI: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.210</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Invisible effort" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s04.jpg" /><ul><li>Hull, L., Petrides, K., Allison, C., Smith, P., Baron-Cohen, S., Lai, M. &amp; Mandy, W. (2017) '"Putting on My Best Normal": Social camouflaging in Autistic adults', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 47(8), pp. 2519–2534. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-017-3166-5">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-017-3166-5</a>.</li><li>Lai, M., Lombardo, M., Ruigrok, A., Chakrabarti, B., Auyeung, B. &amp; Bullmore, E.T. (2017) 'Quantifying and exploring camouflaging in men and women with autism', <i>Autism</i>, 21(6), 690-702. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361316671012">DOI: 10.1177/1362361316671012</a>.</li><li>Hull, L., Mandy, W., Lai, M., Baron-Cohen, S., Allison, C., Smith, P. &amp; Petrides, K. (2020) 'Development and Validation of the Camouflaging Autistic Traits Questionnaire (CAT-Q)', <i>Autism Dev Disord</i>, 49, 819-833. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-018-3792-6">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-018-3792-6</a>.</li><li>Cassidy, S., Gould, K., Townsend, E., Pelton, M., Robertson, A. &amp; Rodgers, J. (2020) 'Is Camouflaging Autistic Traits Associated with Suicidal Thoughts and Behaviours? Expanding the Interpersonal Psychological Theory of Suicide in an Undergraduate Student Sample', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 50(10), 3638–3648. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-019-04323-3">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-019-04323-3</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Misread strengths" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s05.jpg" /><ul><li>Milton D. (2012) 'On the ontological status of autism: the "double empathy problem"', <i>Disability &amp; Society</i>, 27(6), 883–887. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/09687599.2012.710008">DOI: 10.1080/09687599.2012.710008</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Hiring glitch" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s06.jpg" /><ul><li>Schmidt, F. &amp; Hunter, J. (1998) 'The validity and utility of selection methods in personnel psychology: practical and theoretical implications of 85 years of research findings', <i>Psychological Bulletin</i>, 124(2), 262–274. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.124.2.262">DOI: 10.1037/0033-2909.124.2.262</a>.</li><li>Hogan, H., Hogan, R. &amp; Kaiser, R. (2009) 'Management derailment: Personality assessment and mitigation', <i>American Psychological Association Handbook of Industrial and Organizational Psychology</i>, 3, 555-575 <a href="https://researchgate.net/publication/292717475_Management_derailment_Personality_assessment_and_mitigation">ResearchGate</a>.</li><li>Gallup (2015) 'State of the American Manager'. (Key statistic quoted in Moscatello, C. (2015) 'There's a good chance your boss should not be a boss', <a href="https://www.glamour.com/story/gallup-managers-report">Glamour</a>). &#8594; Cites <a href="https://www.gallup.com/services/182138/state-american-manager.aspx">Gallup</a> [Paywall]</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Performance trap" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s07.jpg" /><ul><li>Colella, A., DeNisi, A. and Varma, A. (1997) 'Appraising the performance of employees with disabilities: A review and model', <i>Human Resource Management Review</i>, 7(1), 27-54. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S1053-4822(97)90004-8">DOI: 10.1016/S1053-4822(97)90004-8</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Late diagnosis costs" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s08.jpg" /><ul><li>Lilley, R., Lawson, W., Hall, G. et al. (2023) '"Peas in a pod": oral-history reflections on autistic identity by late-diagnosed adults', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 53, 1146–1161. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-022-05667-z">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-022-05667-z</a>.</li><li>Atherton, G., Edisbury, E., Piovesan, A. &amp; Cross, L. (2022) 'Autism Through the Ages: A Mixed Methods Approach to Understanding How Age and Age of Diagnosis Affect Quality of Life', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 52, 3639–3654. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-021-05235-x">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-021-05235-x</a>.</li><li>Brown, C., Newell, V., Sahin, E. &amp; Hedley, D. (2024) 'Updated Systematic Review of Suicide in Autism: 2018–2024', <i>Current Developmental Disorders Reports</i>, 11, 225–256. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40474-024-00308-9">DOI: 10.1007/s40474-024-00308-9</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="The business upside" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s09.jpg" /><ul><li>Austin, R.D. and Pisano, G.P. (2017) 'Neurodiversity as a competitive advantage', <i>Harvard Business Review</i>, 95(3), 96–103. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/05/neurodiversity-as-a-competitive-advantage">HBR.org</a></li><li>Deloitte (2020) 'Neurodiversity: The Next Frontier in Talent'. <a href="https://www.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/topics/talent/neurodiversity-in-the-workplace.html">Deloitte Insights</a>.</li><li>Lorenz, T. &amp; Heinitz, K. (2014) 'Aspergers – Different, Not Less: Occupational Strengths and Job Interests of Individuals with Asperger's Syndrome’, <i>PLoS ONE</i>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0100358">DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100358</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Re-imagine recruitment" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s10.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Redesign workspaces" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s11.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Shifting HR - Re-write feedback" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s12.jpg" /></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Language matters" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s13.jpg" /><ul><li>Kenny, L., Hattersley, C., Molins, B., Buckley, C., Povey, C. &amp; Pellicano, E. (2016) 'Which terms should be used to describe autism? Perspectives from the UK autism community', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 20(4). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361315588200">DOI: 10.1177/1362361315588200</a>.</li><li>Bury, S., Jellett, R., Spoor, J. &amp; Hedley, D. (2020) '"It Defines Who I Am" or "It's Something I Have": What Language Do [Autistic] Australian Adults [on the Autism Spectrum] Prefer?', <i>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</i>, 53(2), 677-687. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10803-020-04425-3">DOI: 10.1007/s10803-020-04425-3</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Toolkit for allies" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s14.jpg" /><ul><li>CIPD (2022) <i>'Neurodiversity at Work: Guide for People Professionals'</i>. London: <a href="https://www.cipd.org/uk/knowledge/guides/neuroinclusion-work/">Chartered Institute of Personnel and Development</a>.</li></ul></div><div class="col-lg-6 mb-4"><img class="rounded img-fluid border border-secondary-subtle border-2 rounded-4" alt="Let's build neuroinclusive workplaces" src="/assets/img/insights/2025/wexpo_250808_s15.jpg" /></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Silvino Rodrigues</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The content as presented at the Sydney Workability Expo 2025 on 8 August 2025]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/workabilityexpo2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2025/workabilityexpo2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Risks of Untreated ADHD</title><link href="/insights/untreated_adhd_risks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Risks of Untreated ADHD" /><published>2024-08-27T22:59:59+10:00</published><updated>2025-12-11T15:13:37+11:00</updated><id>/insights/untreated_adhd_risks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/untreated_adhd_risks.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The following is an extract from the YouTube video titled <strong>“<a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=eRPeU1DYOWA">This Is Why You Can’t Get ADHD Treatment</a>“</strong>, by Ben Jordan. We extracted from 4:24 to 5:52, where he did a really good job of explaining the other side of the ADHD medication question - that of the choice not to leverage it. So we’ve added this clip and it’s transcript as is, and then added the appropriate citations. <em>(Please view the original full video to support Ben Jordan’s online presence.)</em></p></blockquote><h1 id="the-risks-of-untreated-adhd">The Risks of Untreated ADHD</h1><h2 id="summary">Summary</h2><ul><li><strong>30%</strong> Increased risk of anxiety, depression, and physical ailments</li><li><strong>2x</strong> Higher substance abuse</li><li><strong>9x</strong> Risk of unwanted pregnancy</li><li><strong>3x</strong> More car accidents</li><li>Increased risk of
    <ul><li>Suicide</li><li>Homicide</li><li>Job loss</li><li>Dropping out</li><li>Divorce</li></ul></li></ul><h2 id="video">Video</h2><div class="mb-4 border border-3 rounded rounded-4 p-2"><div class="ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe class="object-fit-contain rounded rounded-3" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eRPeU1DYOWA?start=264&amp;end=356" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div></div><h2 id="transcript">Transcript</h2><p><small class="text-info">(Partial)</small></p><blockquote><h4 id="how-incredibly-dangerous-not-being-treated-is">How incredibly dangerous not being treated is.</h4><p>Let’s start with the most direct and horrifying statistic that you’re going to hear in this video.
In a study published earlier this year it was found that people receiving treatment for ADHD in the form of medication had a <strong>19% lower risk of death</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> than those who are not being treated, and this is a really legit study tracking hundreds of thousands of people in each group over a period of 2 years.</p><p></p><p>Here’s some <strong>more not at all fun facts</strong>.</p><ul><li>Adults with ADHD who are not treated as children suffer from <strong>anxiety, depression and physical ailments 30% more</strong> than adults without ADHD <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</li><li>Adolescents with ADHD who are left untreated are <strong>twice as likely to abuse alcohol, marijuana, cocaine and unprescribed drugs</strong> such as stimulants than adolescents who are adequately treated and prescribe those stimulants <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</li><li>Young adults with ADHD who are not receiving medication as treatment are <strong>nine times more likely to have or cause an unwanted pregnancy</strong><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.</li><li>Young drivers with untreated ADHD have <strong>three times more motor vehicle crashes than average</strong> and are statistically at a higher risk of destroying their vehicle than an adult who is legally drunk <sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.</li></ul><p>Then when you mix in a dozen or so studies strongly suggesting <strong>higher suicide and homicide risk</strong><sup id="fnref:6a"><a href="#fn:6a" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup><sup id="fnref:6b"><a href="#fn:6b" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup><sup id="fnref:6c"><a href="#fn:6c" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> it gets pretty easy to say that having <strong>untreated ADHD is incredibly dangerous</strong>.
And that’s on top of studies showing that untreated ADHD results in <strong>poor job performance</strong><sup id="fnref:7a"><a href="#fn:7a" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup><sup id="fnref:7b"><a href="#fn:7b" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup><sup id="fnref:7c"><a href="#fn:7c" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>, <strong>poor school performance</strong><sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>, <strong>higher divorce rates</strong><sup id="fnref:9a"><a href="#fn:9a" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup><sup id="fnref:9b"><a href="#fn:9b" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup> and so on.</p></blockquote><h2 id="references">References</h2><div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"><ol><li id="fn:1"><p>Vasiliadis, H. M., Lunghi, C., Rahme, E., Rochette, L., Gignac, M., Massamba, V., … &amp; Lesage, A. (2024). ADHD medications use and risk of mortality and unintentional injuries: a population-based cohort study. Translational Psychiatry, 14(1), 128. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41398-024-02825-y <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:2"><p>Caye, A., et al. (2024). The impacts associated with having ADHD: an umbrella review. Frontiers in Psychiatry. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1343314 <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:3"><p>Srichawla, B., Telles, C., Schweitzer, M., Darwish, B. (2022). Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder and Substance Use Disorder: A Narrative Review. https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.24068 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:4"><p>Skoglund, C. et al. (2019). Association of ADHD with teenage birth among women and girls. JAMA Network Open, 2(4), e 197450. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.12463 <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:5"><p>Chang, Z., et al. (2014). Serious transport accidents in adults with ADHD, and the effect of medication: a population-based study. JAMA Psychiatry, 71(3), 335-343. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2013.4174 <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:6a"><p>Chang, Z., Quinn, P. D., O’Reilly, L., Sjölander, A., Hur, K., Gibbons, R., Larsson, H., &amp; D’Onofrio, B. M. (2020). Medication for Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Risk for Suicide Attempts. Biological psychiatry, 88(6), 452–458. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.12.003 <a href="#fnref:6a" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:6b"><p>Chen, V. C., Chan, H. L., Wu, S. I., Lee, M., Lu, M. L., Liang, H. Y., Dewey, M. E., Stewart, R., &amp; Lee, C. T. (2019). Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Mortality Risk in Taiwan. JAMA network open, 2(8), e198714. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.8714 <a href="#fnref:6b" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:6c"><p>Dalsgaard, S., Østergaard, S. D., Leckman, J. F., Mortensen, P. B., &amp; Pedersen, M. G. (2015). Mortality in children, adolescents, and adults with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a nationwide cohort study. Lancet (London, England), 385(9983), 2190–2196. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61684-6 <a href="#fnref:6c" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:7a"><p>de Graaf, R., Kessler, R. C., Fayyad, J., ten Have, M., Alonso, J., Angermeyer, M., Borges, G., Demyttenaere, K., Gasquet, I., de Girolamo, G., Haro, J. M., Jin, R., Karam, E. G., Ormel, J., &amp; Posada-Villa, J. (2008). The prevalence and effects of adult attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) on the performance of workers: results from the WHO World Mental Health Survey Initiative. Occupational and environmental medicine, 65(12), 835–842. https://doi.org/10.1136/oem.2007.038448 <a href="#fnref:7a" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:7b"><p>Kessler, R. C., Lane, M., Stang, P. E., &amp; Van Brunt, D. L. (2009). The prevalence and workplace costs of adult attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in a large manufacturing firm. Psychological Medicine, 39(1), 137–147. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291708003309 <a href="#fnref:7b" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:7c"><p>Kosheleff, A. R., Mason, O., Jain, R., Koch, J., &amp; Rubin, J. (2023). Functional Impairments Associated With ADHD in Adulthood and the Impact of Pharmacological Treatment. Journal of attention disorders, 27(7), 669–697. https://doi.org/10.1177/10870547231158572 <a href="#fnref:7c" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:8"><p>Jangmo, A., Stålhandske, A., Chang, Z., Chen, Q., Almqvist, C., Feldman, I., Bulik, C. M., Lichtenstein, P., D’Onofrio, B., Kuja-Halkola, R., &amp; Larsson, H. (2019). Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder, School Performance, and Effect of Medication. Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 58(4), 423–432. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2018.11.014 <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:9a"><p>Kosheleff, A. R., Mason, O., Jain, R., Koch, J., &amp; Rubin, J. (2023). Functional Impairments Associated With ADHD in Adulthood and the Impact of Pharmacological Treatment. Journal of attention disorders, 27(7), 669–697. https://doi.org/10.1177/10870547231158572 <a href="#fnref:9a" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li><li id="fn:9b"><p>Fischer, S., &amp; Nilsen, C. (2024). ADHD in older adults – a scoping review. Aging &amp; Mental Health, 28(9), 1189–1196. https://doi.org/10.1080/13607863.2024.2339994 <a href="#fnref:9b" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p></li></ol></div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Jordan</name></author><category term="adhd" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is an extract from the YouTube video titled "This Is Why You Can't Get ADHD Treatment", by Ben Jordan.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2024/untreated_adhd_risks.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2024/untreated_adhd_risks.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)</title><link href="/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-10-30T20:09:55+11:00</updated><id>/insights/asd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/icd11_6a02_asd.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Caution:</strong><em>The following text is extracted from the ICD-11 definition of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). It is provided for informational purposes only and should not be used as a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Please note that this summary may not reflect the most up-to-date version of the ICD-11. The official and current listing can be found on the World Health Organization’s website: <a href="https://icd.who.int/browse/2025-01/mms/en#437815624">ICD-11: Autism Spectrum Disorder</a>.</em></p></blockquote><h1 id="autism-spectrum-disorder">Autism Spectrum Disorder</h1><blockquote><p>Foundation URI: <a href="http://id.who.int/icd/entity/437815624">http://id.who.int/icd/entity/437815624</a></p></blockquote><p><strong>Code: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02</code></strong></p><h2 id="description">Description</h2><p>Autism spectrum disorder is characterised by persistent deficits in the ability to initiate and to sustain reciprocal social interaction and social communication, and by a range of restricted, repetitive, and inflexible patterns of behaviour, interests or activities that are clearly atypical or excessive for the individual’s age and sociocultural context. The onset of the disorder occurs during the developmental period, typically in early childhood, but symptoms may not become fully manifest until later, when social demands exceed limited capacities. Deficits are sufficiently severe to cause impairment in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other important areas of functioning and are usually a pervasive feature of the individual’s functioning observable in all settings, although they may vary according to social, educational, or other context. Individuals along the spectrum exhibit a full range of intellectual functioning and language abilities.</p><h2 id="diagnostic-requirements">Diagnostic Requirements</h2><h3 id="essential-required-features">Essential (Required) Features:</h3><ul><li>Persistent deficits in initiating and sustaining social communication and reciprocal social interactions that are outside the expected range of typical functioning given the individual’s age and level of intellectual development. Specific manifestations of these deficits vary according to chronological age, verbal and intellectual ability, and disorder severity. Manifestations may include limitations in the following:</li><li>Understanding of, interest in, or inappropriate responses to the verbal or non-verbal social communications of others.</li><li>Integration of spoken language with typical complimentary non-verbal cues, such as eye contact, gestures, facial expressions and body language. These non-verbal behaviours may also be reduced in frequency or intensity.</li><li>Understanding and use of language in social contexts and ability to initiate and sustain reciprocal social conversations.</li><li>Social awareness, leading to behaviour that is not appropriately modulated according to the social context.</li><li>Ability to imagine and respond to the feelings, emotional states, and attitudes of others.</li><li>Mutual sharing of interests.</li><li>Ability to make and sustain typical peer relationships.</li><li>Persistent restricted, repetitive, and inflexible patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities that are clearly atypical or excessive for the individual’s age and sociocultural context. These may include:</li><li>Lack of adaptability to new experiences and circumstances, with associated distress, that can be evoked by trivial changes to a familiar environment or in response to unanticipated events.</li><li>Inflexible adherence to particular routines; for example, these may be geographic such as following familiar routes, or may require precise timing such as mealtimes or transport.</li><li>Excessive adherence to rules (e.g., when playing games).</li><li>Excessive and persistent ritualized patterns of behaviour (e.g., preoccupation with lining up or sorting objects in a particular way) that serve no apparent external purpose.</li><li>Repetitive and stereotyped motor movements, such as whole body movements (e.g., rocking), atypical gait (e.g., walking on tiptoes), unusual hand or finger movements and posturing. These behaviours are particularly common during early childhood.</li><li>Persistent preoccupation with one or more special interests, parts of objects, or specific types of stimuli (including media) or an unusually strong attachment to particular objects (excluding typical comforters).</li><li>Lifelong excessive and persistent hypersensitivity or hyposensitivity to sensory stimuli or unusual interest in a sensory stimulus, which may include actual or anticipated sounds, light, textures (especially clothing and food), odors and tastes, heat, cold, or pain.</li><li>The onset of the disorder occurs during the developmental period, typically in early childhood, but characteristic symptoms may not become fully manifest until later, when social demands exceed limited capacities.</li><li>The symptoms result in significant impairment in personal, family, social, educational, occupational or other important areas of functioning. Some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder are able to function adequately in many contexts through exceptional effort, such that their deficits may not be apparent to others. A diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder is still appropriate in such cases.</li></ul><h3 id="specifiers-for-characterizing-features-within-the-autism-spectrum">Specifiers for characterizing features within the Autism Spectrum:</h3><p>These specifiers enable the identification of co-occurring limitations in intellectual and functional language abilities, which are important factors in the appropriate individualization of support, selection of interventions, and treatment planning for individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder. A qualifier is also provided for loss of previously acquired skills, which is a feature of the developmental history of a small proportion of individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder.</p><h4 id="co-occurring-disorder-of-intellectual-development">Co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development</h4><p>Individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder may exhibit limitations in intellectual abilities. If present, a separate diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development should be assigned, using the appropriate category to designate severity (i.e., Mild, Moderate, Severe, Profound, Provisional). Because social deficits are a core feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder, the assessment of adaptive behaviour as a part of the diagnosis of a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development should place greater emphasis on the intellectual, conceptual, and practical domains of adaptive functioning than on social skills.</p><p>If no co-occurring diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development is present, the following qualifier for the Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis should be applied:</p><ul><li>without Disorder of Intellectual Development</li></ul><p>If there is a co-occurring diagnosis of Disorder of Intellectual Development, the following qualifier for the Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis should be applied, in addition to the appropriate diagnostic code for the co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development:</p><ul><li>with Disorder of Intellectual Development</li></ul><h4 id="degree-of-functional-language-impairment">Degree of Functional Language Impairment</h4><p>The degree of impairment in functional language (spoken or signed) should be designated with a second qualifier. Functional language refers to the capacity of the individual to use language for instrumental purposes (e.g., to express personal needs and desires). This qualifier is intended to reflect primarily the verbal and non-verbal expressive language deficits present in some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder and not the pragmatic language deficits that are a core feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</p><p>The following qualifier should be applied to indicate the extent of functional language impairment (spoken or signed) relative to the individual’s age:</p><ul><li>with mild or no impairment of functional language</li><li>with impaired functional language (i.e., not able to use more than single words or simple phrases)</li><li>with complete, or almost complete, absence of functional language</li></ul><h5 id="table-65-diagnostic-codes-for-autism-spectrum-disorder">Table 6.5 Diagnostic Codes for Autism Spectrum Disorder</h5><table><thead><tr><th></th><th style="text-align: center">with mild or no impairment of functional language</th><th style="text-align: center">with impaired functional language</th><th style="text-align: center">with complete, or almost complete, absence of functional language</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>without Disorder of Intellectual Development</td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.0</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.2</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><em>-</em></td></tr><tr><td>with Disorder of Intellectual Development</td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.1</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.3</code></td><td style="text-align: center"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A02.5</code></td></tr></tbody></table><p><br />
Table 6.5 shows the diagnostic codes corresponding to the categories that result from the application of the specifiers for Co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development and Degree of Functional Language Impairment.</p><blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Note:</strong><em>The ICD-11 and DSM-5 classify Autism Spectrum Disorder differently. The ICD-11 <strong>uses diagnostic codes with specifiers</strong>, while the DSM-5 <strong>emphasises support levels</strong>.</em></p><p><br /><em>In the DSM-5, criteria span two domains:</em></p><ul><li><em>Social Communication:</em> Persistent deficits in social communication and interaction</li><li><em><abbr data-bs-toggle="tooltip" title="Restricted and Repetitive Behaviours">RRBs</abbr>:</em> Restricted, repetitive patterns of behaviour, interests, or activities</li></ul><p><em>Each domain is rated according to support needs:</em></p><ul><li><em>Level 1:</em> Requiring support</li><li><em>Level 2:</em> Requiring substantial support</li><li><em>Level 3:</em> Requiring very substantial support</li></ul></blockquote><h4 id="loss-of-previously-acquired-skills">Loss of Previously Acquired Skills</h4><p>A small proportion of individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder may present with a loss of previously acquired skills. This regression typically occurs during the second year of life and most often involves language use and social responsiveness. Loss of previously acquired skills is rarely observed after 3 years of age. If it occurs after age 3, it is more likely to involve loss of cognitive and adaptive skills (e.g., loss of bowel and bladder control, impaired sleep), regression of language and social abilities, as well as increasing emotional and behavioural disturbances.</p><p>There are two alternative specifiers, to denote whether or not loss of previously acquired skills is an aspect of the clinical history, where x corresponds to the final digit shown in Table 6.5:</p><h3 id="additional-clinical-features">Additional Clinical Features:</h3><ul><li>Common symptom presentations of Autism Spectrum Disorder in young children are parental or caregiver concerns about intellectual or other developmental delays (e.g., problems in language and motor coordination). When there is no significant impairment of intellectual functioning, clinical services may only be sought later (e.g., due to behaviour or social problems when starting school). In middle childhood, there may be prominent symptoms of anxiety, including Social Anxiety Disorder, school refusal, and Specific Phobia. During adolescence and adulthood, Depressive Disorders are often a presenting feature.</li><li>Co-occurrence of Autism Spectrum Disorder with other Mental, Behavioural or Neurodevelopmental Disorders is common across the lifespan. In a substantial proportion of cases, particularly in adolescence and adulthood, it is a co-occurring disorder that first brings an individual with Autism Spectrum Disorder to clinical attention.</li><li>Pragmatic language difficulties may manifest as an overly literal understanding of others’ speech, speech that lacks normal prosody and emotional tone and therefore appears monotonous, lack of awareness of the appropriateness of their choice of language in particular social contexts, or pedantic precision in the use of language.</li><li>Social naiveté, especially during adolescence, can lead to exploitation by others, a risk that may be enhanced by the use of social media without adequate supervision.</li><li>Profiles of specific cognitive skills in Autism Spectrum Disorder as measured by standardized assessments may show striking and unusual patterns of strengths and weaknesses that are highly variable from individual to individual. These deficits can affect learning and adaptive functioning to a greater extent than would be predicted from the overall scores on measures of verbal and non-verbal intelligence.</li><li>Self-injurious behaviours (e.g., hitting one’s face, head banging) occur more often in individuals with co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development.</li><li>Some young individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, especially those with a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development, develop epilepsy or seizures during early childhood with a second increase in prevalence during adolescence. Catatonic states have also been described. A number of medical disorders such as Tuberous Sclerosis, chromosomal abnormalities including Fragile X Syndrome, Cerebral Palsy, early onset epileptic encephalopathies, and Neurofibromatosis are associated with Autism Spectrum Disorder with or without a co-occurring Disorder of Intellectual Development. Genomic deletions, duplications and other genetic abnormalities are increasingly described in individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, some of which may be important for genetic counselling. Prenatal exposure to valproate is also associated with an increased risk of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li><li>Some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder are capable of functioning adequately by making an exceptional effort to compensate for their symptoms during childhood, adolescence or adulthood. Such sustained effort, which may be more typical of affected females, can have a deleterious impact on mental health and well-being.</li></ul><h3 id="boundary-with-normality-threshold">Boundary with Normality (Threshold):</h3><ul><li><strong>Social interaction skills:</strong> Typically developing individuals vary in the pace and extent to which they acquire and master skills of reciprocal social interaction and social communication. A diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder should only be considered if there is marked and persistent deviation from the expected range of abilities and behaviours in these domains given the individual’s age, level of intellectual functioning, and sociocultural context. Some individuals may exhibit limited social interaction due to shyness (i.e., feelings of awkwardness or fear in new situations or with unfamiliar people) or behavioural inhibition (i.e., being slow to approach or to ‘warm up’ to new people and situations). Limited social interactions in shy or behaviourally inhibited children, adolescents, or adults are not indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder. Shyness is differentiated from Autism Spectrum Disorder by evidence of adequate social communication behaviours in familiar situations.</li><li><strong>Social communication skills:</strong> Children vary widely in the age at which they first acquire spoken language and the pace at which their speech and language become firmly established. Most children with early language delay eventually acquire similar language skills as their same-age peers. Early language delay alone is not strongly indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder unless there is also evidence of limited motivation for social communication and limited interaction skills. An essential feature of Autism Spectrum Disorder is persistent impairment in the ability to understand and use language appropriately for social communication.</li><li><strong>Repetitive and stereotyped behaviours:</strong> Many children go through phases of repetitive play and highly focused interests as a part of typical development. Unless there is also evidence of impaired reciprocal social interaction and social communication, patterns of behaviour characterized by repetition, routine, or restricted interests are not by themselves indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li></ul><h3 id="course-features">Course Features:</h3><ul><li>Although Autism Spectrum Disorder can present clinically at all ages, including during adulthood, it is a lifelong disorder the manifestations and impact of which are likely to vary according to age, intellectual and language abilities, co-occurring conditions and environmental context.</li><li>Restricted and repetitive behaviours persist over time. Specifically, repetitive sensorimotor behaviours appear to be common, consistent, and potentially severe. During the school age years and adolescence, these repetitive sensorimotor behaviours begin to lessen in intensity and number. Insistence on sameness, which is less prevalent, appears to develop during preschool and worsen over time.</li></ul><h3 id="developmental-presentations">Developmental Presentations:</h3><ul><li><em>Infancy:</em> Characteristic features may emerge during infancy although they may only be recognized as indicative of Autism Spectrum Disorder in retrospect. It is usually possible to make the diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder during the preschool period (up to 4 years), especially in children exhibiting generalized developmental delay. Plateauing of social communication and language skills and failure to progress in their development is not uncommon. The loss of early words and social responsiveness, i.e., a true regression, with an onset between 1 and 2 years, is unusual but significant and rarely occurs after the third year of life. In these cases, the qualifier ‘with loss of previously acquired skills’ should be applied.</li><li><em>Preschool:</em> In preschool children, indicators of an Autism Spectrum Disorder diagnosis often include avoidance of mutual eye contact, resistance to physical affection, a lack of social imaginary play, language that is delayed in onset or is precocious but not used for social conversation; social withdrawal, obsessive or repetitive preoccupations, and a lack of social interaction with peers characterized by parallel play or disinterest. Sensory sensitivities to everyday sounds, or to foods, may overshadow the underlying social communication deficits.</li><li><em>Middle Childhood:</em> In children with Autism Spectrum Disorder without a Disorder of Intellectual Development, social adjustment difficulties outside the home may not be detected until school entry or adolescence when social communication problems lead to social isolation from peers. Resistance to engage in unfamiliar experiences and marked reactions to even minor change in routines are typical. Furthermore, excessive focus on detail as well as rigidity of behaviour and thinking may be significant. Symptoms of anxiety may become evident at this stage of development.</li><li><em>Adolescence:</em> By adolescence, the capacity to cope with increasing social complexity in peer relationships at a time of increasingly demanding academic expectations is often overwhelmed. In some individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder, the underlying social communication deficits may be overshadowed by the symptoms of co-occurring Mental and Behavioural Disorders. Depressive symptoms are often a presenting feature</li><li><em>Adulthood:</em> In adulthood, the capacity for those with Autism Spectrum Disorder to cope with social relationships can become increasingly challenged, and clinical presentation may occur when social demands overwhelm the capacity to compensate. Presenting problems in adulthood may represent reactions to social isolation or the social consequences of inappropriate behaviour. Compensation strategies may be sufficient to sustain dyadic relationships, but are usually inadequate in social groups. Special interests, and focused attention, may benefit some individuals in education and employment. Work environments may have to be tailored to the capacities of the individual. A first diagnosis in adulthood may be precipitated by a breakdown in domestic or work relationships. In Autism Spectrum Disorder there is always a history of early childhood social communication and relationship difficulties, although this may only be apparent in retrospect.</li></ul><h3 id="culture-related-features">Culture-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Cultural variation exists in norms of social communication, reciprocal social interactions, as well as interests and activities. Therefore, signs of impairment in functioning may differ depending on cultural context. For example, in some societies it may be normative for children may avoid direct eye contact out of deference, which should not be misinterpreted as impairment in social interaction.</li></ul><h3 id="sex--andor-gender-related-features">Sex- and/or Gender-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Males are four times more likely than females to be diagnosed with Autism Spectrum Disorder.</li><li>Females diagnosed with Autism Spectrum Disorder are more frequently diagnosed with co-occurring Disorders of Intellectual Development, suggesting that less severe presentations may go undetected as compared to males. Females tend to demonstrate fewer restricted, repetitive interests and behaviours than males.</li><li>During middle-childhood, gender differences in presentation differentially affect functioning. Boys may act out with reactive aggression or other behavioural symptoms when challenged or frustrated. Girls tend to withdraw socially, and react with emotional changes to their social adjustment difficulties.</li></ul>]]></content><author><name>World Health Organisation (WHO)</name></author><category term="Autism," /><category term="ASD," /><category term="Diagnostic," /><category term="Reference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ICD-11 entry for Autism Spectrum Disorder.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2018/icd11_6a02_asd.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2018/icd11_6a02_asd.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</title><link href="/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2025-10-12T16:46:00+11:00</updated><id>/insights/adhd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/icd11_6a05_adhd.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="sidenote"><p><strong>Caution:</strong><em>The following text is extracted from the ICD-11 definition of Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). It is provided for informational purposes only and should not be used as a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Please note that this summary may not reflect the most up-to-date version of the ICD-11. The official and current listing can be found on the World Health Organization’s website: <a href="https://icd.who.int/browse/2025-01/mms/en#821852937">ICD-11: Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</a>.</em></p></blockquote><h1 id="attention-deficithyperactivity-disorder">Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</h1><blockquote><p>Foundation URI: <a href="http://id.who.int/icd/entity/821852937">http://id.who.int/icd/entity/821852937</a></p></blockquote><p><strong>Code: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05</code></strong></p><h2 id="description">Description</h2><p>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder is characterised by a persistent pattern (at least 6 months) of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity that has a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. There is evidence of significant inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity symptoms prior to age 12, typically by early to mid-childhood, though some individuals may first come to clinical attention later. The degree of inattention and hyperactivity-impulsivity is outside the limits of normal variation expected for age and level of intellectual functioning. Inattention refers to significant difficulty in sustaining attention to tasks that do not provide a high level of stimulation or frequent rewards, distractibility and problems with organisation. Hyperactivity refers to excessive motor activity and difficulties with remaining still, most evident in structured situations that require behavioural self-control. Impulsivity is a tendency to act in response to immediate stimuli, without deliberation or consideration of the risks and consequences. The relative balance and the specific manifestations of inattentive and hyperactive-impulsive characteristics varies across individuals and may change over the course of development. In order for a diagnosis to be made, manifestations of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity must be evident across multiple situations or settings (e.g., home, school, work, with friends or relatives), but are likely to vary according to the structure and demands of the setting. Symptoms are not better accounted for by another mental, behavioural, or neurodevelopmental disorder and are not due to the effect of a substance or medication.</p><h2 id="diagnostic-requirements">Diagnostic Requirements</h2><h3 id="essential-required-features">Essential (Required) Features:</h3><ul><li>A persistent pattern (e.g., at least 6 months) of inattention symptoms and/or a combination of hyperactivity and impulsivity symptoms that is outside the limits of normal variation expected for age and level of intellectual development. Symptoms vary according to chronological age and disorder severity.</li></ul><h3 id="inattention">Inattention</h3><ul><li>Several symptoms of inattention that are persistent, and sufficiently severe that they have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. Symptoms are typically from the following clusters:</li><li>Difficulty sustaining attention to tasks that do not provide a high level of stimulation or reward or require sustained mental effort; lacking attention to detail; making careless mistakes in school or work assignments; not completing tasks.</li><li>Easily distracted by extraneous stimuli or thoughts not related to the task at hand; often does not seem to listen when spoken to directly; frequently appears to be daydreaming or to have mind elsewhere.</li><li>Loses things; is forgetful in daily activities; has difficulty remembering to complete upcoming daily tasks or activities; difficulty planning, managing and organizing schoolwork, tasks and other activities.</li></ul><blockquote><p>Note: Inattention may not be evident when the individual is engaged in activities that provide intense stimulation and frequent rewards.</p></blockquote><h3 id="hyperactivity-impulsivity">Hyperactivity Impulsivity</h3><ul><li>Several symptoms of hyperactivity/impulsivity that are persistent, and sufficiently severe that they have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning. These tend to be most evident in structured situations that require behavioural self-control. Symptoms are typically from the following clusters:</li><li>Excessive motor activity; leaves seat when expected to sit still; often runs about; has difficulty sitting still without fidgeting (younger children); feelings of physical restlessness, a sense of discomfort with being quiet or sitting still (adolescents and adults).</li><li>Difficulty engaging in activities quietly; talks too much.</li><li>Blurts out answers in school, comments at work; difficulty waiting turn in conversation, games, or activities; interrupts or intrudes on others conversations or games.</li><li>A tendency to act in response to immediate stimuli without deliberation or consideration of risks and consequences (e.g., engaging in behaviours with potential for physical injury; impulsive decisions; reckless driving)</li><li>Evidence of significant inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity symptoms prior to age 12, though some individuals may first come to clinical attention later in adolescence or as adults, often when demands exceed the individual’s capacity to compensate for limitations.</li><li>Manifestations of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity must be evident across multiple situations or settings (e.g., home, school, work, with friends or relatives), but are likely to vary according to the structure and demands of the setting.</li><li>Symptoms are not better accounted for by another mental disorder (e.g., an Anxiety or Fear-Related Disorder, a Neurocognitive Disorder such as Delirium).</li><li>Symptoms are not due to the effects of a substance (e.g., cocaine) or medication (e.g., bronchodilators, thyroid replacement medication) on the central nervous system, including and withdrawal effects, and are not due to a Disease of the Nervous System.</li></ul><h3 id="specifiers-to-describe-predominant-characteristics-of-clinical-presentation">Specifiers to describe predominant characteristics of clinical presentation:</h3><p>The characteristics of the current clinical presentation should be described using one of the following specifiers, which are meant to assist in recording the main reason for the current referral or services. Predominance of symptoms refers to the presence of several symptoms of either an inattentive or hyperactive/impulsive nature with few or no symptoms of the other type.</p><h4 id="6a050-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-predominantly-inattentive-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.0</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, predominantly inattentive presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and inattentive symptoms predominate.</li></ul><h4 id="6a051-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-predominantly-hyperactive-impulsive-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.1</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, predominantly hyperactive-impulsive presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and symptoms of hyperactivity-impulsivity predominate.</li></ul><h4 id="6a052-attention-deficit-hyperactivity-disorder-combined-presentation"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6A05.2</code> Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, combined presentation</h4><ul><li>All diagnostic requirements for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder are met and both hyperactive-impulsive and inattentive symptoms are clinically significant aspects of the current clinical presentation, with neither clearly predominating.</li></ul><h3 id="additional-clinical-features">Additional Clinical Features:</h3><ul><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder usually manifests in early or middle childhood. In many cases, hyperactivity symptoms predominate in preschool and decrease with age such that they are no longer prominent beyond adolescence or may instead be reported as feelings of physical restlessness. Attentional problems may be more commonly observed beginning in later childhood, especially in school and in adults in occupational settings.</li><li>The manifestations and severity of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often vary according to the characteristics and demands of the environment. Symptoms and behaviours should be evaluated across multiple types of environments as a part of clinical assessment.</li><li>Where available, teacher and parent reports should be obtained to establish the diagnosis in children and adolescents. In adults, the report of a significant other, family member, or co-worker can provide important additional information.</li><li>Some individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder may first present for services in adulthood. When making the diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in adults, a history of inattention, hyperactivity, or impulsivity before age 12 is an important corroborating feature that can be best established from school or local records, or from informants who knew the individual during childhood. In the absence of such corroborating information, a diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in older adolescents and adults should be made with caution.</li><li>In a subset of individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, especially in children, an exclusively inattentive presentation may occur. There is no hyperactivity and the presentation is characterized by daydreaming, mind-wandering, and a lack of focus. These children are sometimes referred to as exhibiting a restrictive inattentive pattern of symptoms or sluggish cognitive tempo.</li><li>In a subset of individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder, combined presentation, severe inattentiveness and hyperactivity-impulsivity are both consistently present in most of the situations that an individual encounters, and are also evidenced by the clinician’s own observations. This pattern is often referred to as hyperkinetic disorder and is considered a more severe form of the disorder.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms often significantly limit academic achievement. Adults with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often find it difficult to hold down a demanding job and may be disproportionately underemployed or unemployed. Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder can also strain interpersonal relationships across the life span including those with family members, peers, and romantic partners. Individuals with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often have greater difficulty regulating their behaviour in the context of groups than in one-on-one situations.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder often co-occurs with other Neurodevelopmental Disorders, including Developmental Speech or Language Disorders, and Primary Tics or Tic Disorders, which are classified in the Chapter on Diseases of the Nervous System but cross-listed under Neurodevelopment Disorders. Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is associated with an increased risk of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder and with elevated rates of epilepsy. Emotional dysregulation, low frustration tolerance, and subtle clumsiness and other minor (‘soft’) neurological abnormalities in sensory and motor performance in the absence of any identifiable brain pathology are also common in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is associated with an increased risk for physical health problems including accidents.</li><li>Acute onset of hyperactive behaviour in a school-age child or adolescent should raise the possibility that symptoms are better accounted for by another mental disorder or by a medical condition. For example, abrupt onset of hyperactivity in adolescence or adulthood may indicate an emergent Primary Psychotic or Bipolar Disorder.</li><li>Although Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder tends to run in families with evidence of high heritability, the predominant symptom pattern in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in a given individual often changes over time and cannot be predicted based on the predominant symptoms of other family members.</li></ul><h3 id="boundary-with-normality-threshold">Boundary with Normality (Threshold):</h3><ul><li>Inattention, hyperactivity and impulsivity symptoms are present in many children, adolescents and adults, especially during certain developmental periods (e.g., early childhood). The diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder requires that these symptoms be persistent across time, pervasive across situations, significantly out of keeping with developmental level, and have a direct negative impact on academic, occupational, or social functioning.</li></ul><h3 id="course-features">Course Features:</h3><ul><li>Nearly half of all children diagnosed with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder will continue to exhibit symptoms into adolescence. Predictors of persistence into adolescence and adulthood include: co-occurring childhood onset Mental, Behavioural or Neurodevelopmental Disorders, lower intellectual functioning, poorer social functioning, and behavioural problems.</li><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms tend to remain stable throughout adolescence with approximately one third of individuals diagnosed in childhood continuing to experience impairment in adulthood.</li><li>Although symptoms of hyperactivity become less overt during adolescence and adulthood, individuals may still experience difficulties with inattention, impulsivity, and restlessness.</li></ul><h3 id="developmental-presentations">Developmental Presentations:</h3><ul><li>Adolescents and adults may only seek clinical services after age 12 once symptoms become more limiting with increasing social, emotional, and academic demands or in the context of an evolving co-occurring Mental, Behavioural, or Neurodevelopmental Disorders that results in an exacerbation of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder symptoms.</li></ul><h3 id="culture-related-features">Culture-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>The symptoms of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder consistently fall into two separate dimensions across cultures: inattention and hyperactivity/impulsivity. However, culture can influence acceptability of symptoms as well as how caregivers respond to them.</li><li>The assessment of hyperactivity should take into account cultural norms of age and gender-appropriate behaviour. For example, in some countries hyperactive behaviour may be seen as a sign of strength in a boy (e.g., ‘boiling blood’) while being perceived very negatively in a girl.</li><li>Symptoms of inattention or hyperactivity/impulsivity may occur in response to exposure to traumatic events and grief reactions during childhood particularly in highly vulnerable and disadvantaged populations, including in post-conflict areas. In these settings, clinicians should consider whether the diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is warranted.</li></ul><h3 id="sex--andor-gender-related-features">Sex- and/or Gender-Related Features:</h3><ul><li>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder is more common in males.</li><li>Females are more likely to exhibit inattentive symptoms whereas males are more likely to exhibit symptoms of hyperactivity and impulsivity particularly at younger ages.</li></ul>]]></content><author><name>World Health Organisation (WHO)</name></author><category term="ADHD," /><category term="Diagnostic," /><category term="Reference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ICD-11 entry for Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/2018/icd11_6a05_adhd.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/2018/icd11_6a05_adhd.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Mourn for Us</title><link href="/insights/jim_sinclair_dont_mourn_for_us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Mourn for Us" /><published>1993-03-01T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-10-12T16:46:00+11:00</updated><id>/insights/dont-mourn-for-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="/insights/jim_sinclair_dont_mourn_for_us.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="dont-mourn-for-us">Don’t Mourn for Us</h1><p><strong>by Jim Sinclair</strong><br /><em>Extracted from <a href="https://www.autreat.com/dont_mourn.html">https://www.autreat.com/dont_mourn.html</a></em>.</p><blockquote><p><em>[This article was published in the Autism Network International newsletter, Our Voice, Volume 1, Number 3, 1993. It is an outline of the presentation Jim gave at the 1993 International Conference on Autism in Toronto, and is addressed primarily to parents.]</em></p></blockquote><p>Parents often report that learning their child is autistic was the most traumatic thing that ever happened to them. Non-autistic people see autism as a great tragedy, and parents experience continuing disappointment and grief at all stages of the child’s and family’s life cycle.
But this grief does not stem from the child’s autism in itself. It is grief over the loss of the normal child the parents had hoped and expected to have. Parents’ attitudes and expectations, and the discrepancies between what parents expect of children at a particular age and their own child’s actual development, cause more stress and anguish than the practical complexities of life with an autistic person.</p><p>Some amount of grief is natural as parents adjust to the fact that an event and a relationship they’ve been looking forward to isn’t going to materialize. But this grief over a fantasized normal child needs to be separated from the parents’ perceptions of the child they do have: the autistic child who needs the support of adult caretakers and who can form very meaningful relationships with those caretakers if given the opportunity. Continuing focus on the child’s autism as a source of grief is damaging for both the parents and the child, and precludes the development of an accepting and authentic relationship between them. For their own sake and for the sake of their children, I urge parents to make radical changes in their perceptions of what autism means.</p><p>I invite you to look at our autism, and look at your grief, from our perspective:</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-an-appendage">Autism is not an appendage</h5><p>Autism isn’t something a person has, or a “shell” that a person is trapped inside. There’s no normal child hidden behind the autism. Autism is a way of being. It is pervasive; it colors every experience, every sensation, perception, thought, emotion, and encounter, every aspect of existence. It is not possible to separate the autism from the person–and if it were possible, the person you’d have left would not be the same person you started with.</p><p>This is important, so take a moment to consider it: Autism is a way of being. It is not possible to separate the person from the autism.</p><p>Therefore, when parents say,</p><blockquote><p>I wish my child did not have autism,</p></blockquote><p>what they’re really saying is,</p><blockquote><p>I wish the autistic child I have did not exist, and I had a different (non-autistic) child instead.</p></blockquote><p>Read that again. This is what we hear when you mourn over our existence. This is what we hear when you pray for a cure. This is what we know, when you tell us of your fondest hopes and dreams for us: that your greatest wish is that one day we will cease to be, and strangers you can love will move in behind our faces.</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-an-impenetrable-wall">Autism is not an impenetrable wall</h5><p>You try to relate to your autistic child, and the child doesn’t respond. He doesn’t see you; you can’t reach her; there’s no getting through. That’s the hardest thing to deal with, isn’t it? The only thing is, it isn’t true.</p><p>Look at it again: You try to relate as parent to child, using your own understanding of normal children, your own feelings about parenthood, your own experiences and intuitions about relationships. And the child doesn’t respond in any way you can recognize as being part of that system.</p><p>That does not mean the child is incapable of relating at all. It only means you’re assuming a shared system, a shared understanding of signals and meanings, that the child in fact does not share. It’s as if you tried to have an intimate conversation with someone who has no comprehension of your language. Of course the person won’t understand what you’re talking about, won’t respond in the way you expect, and may well find the whole interaction confusing and unpleasant.</p><p>It takes more work to communicate with someone whose native language isn’t the same as yours. And autism goes deeper than language and culture; autistic people are “foreigners” in any society. You’re going to have to give up your assumptions about shared meanings. You’re going to have to learn to back up to levels more basic than you’ve probably thought about before, to translate, and to check to make sure your translations are understood. You’re going to have to give up the certainty that comes of being on your own familiar territory, of knowing you’re in charge, and let your child teach you a little of her language, guide you a little way into his world.</p><p>And the outcome, if you succeed, still will not be a normal parent-child relationship. Your autistic child may learn to talk, may attend regular classes in school, may go to college, drive a car, live independently, have a career–but will never relate to you as other children relate to their parents. Or your autistic child may never speak, may graduate from a self-contained special education classroom to a sheltered activity program or a residential facility, may need lifelong full-time care and supervision–but is not completely beyond your reach. The ways we relate are different. Push for the things your expectations tell you are normal, and you’ll find frustration, disappointment, resentment, maybe even rage and hatred. Approach respectfully, without preconceptions, and with openness to learning new things, and you’ll find a world you could never have imagined.</p><p>Yes, that takes more work than relating to a non-autistic person. But it can be done–unless non-autistic people are far more limited than we are in their capacity to relate. We spend our entire lives doing it. Each of us who does learn to talk to you, each of us who manages to function at all in your society, each of us who manages to reach out and make a connection with you, is operating in alien territory, making contact with alien beings. We spend our entire lives doing this. And then you tell us that we can’t relate.</p><h5 id="autism-is-not-death">Autism is not death</h5><p>Granted, autism isn’t what most parents expect or look forward to when they anticipate the arrival of a child. What they expect is a child who will be like them, who will share their world and relate to them without requiring intensive on-the-job training in alien contact. Even if their child has some disability other than autism, parents expect to be able to relate to that child on the terms that seem normal to them; and in most cases, even allowing for the limitations of various disabilities, it is possible to form the kind of bond the parents had been looking forward to.</p><p>But not when the child is autistic. Much of the grieving parents do is over the non-occurrence of the expected relationship with an expected normal child. This grief is very real, and it needs to be expected and worked through so people can get on with their lives–</p><p>but it has nothing to do with autism.</p><p>What it comes down to is that you expected something that was tremendously important to you, and you looked forward to it with great joy and excitement, and maybe for a while you thought you actually had it–and then, perhaps gradually, perhaps abruptly, you had to recognize that the thing you looked forward to hasn’t happened. It isn’t going to happen. No matter how many other, normal children you have, nothing will change the fact that this time, the child you waited and hoped and planned and dreamed for didn’t arrive.</p><p>This is the same thing that parents experience when a child is stillborn, or when they have their baby to hold for a short time, only to have it die in infancy. It isn’t about autism, it’s about shattered expectations. I suggest that the best place to address these issues is not in organizations devoted to autism, but in parental bereavement counseling and support groups. In those settings parents learn to come to terms with their loss–not to forget about it, but to let it be in the past, where the grief doesn’t hit them in the face every waking moment of their lives. They learn to accept that their child is gone, forever, and won’t be coming back. Most importantly, they learn not to take out their grief for the lost child on their surviving children. This is of critical importance when one of those surviving children arrived at t time the child being mourned for died.</p><p>You didn’t lose a child to autism. You lost a child because the child you waited for never came into existence. That isn’t the fault of the autistic child who does exist, and it shouldn’t be our burden. We need and deserve families who can see us and value us for ourselves, not families whose vision of us is obscured by the ghosts of children who never lived. Grieve if you must, for your own lost dreams. But don’t mourn for us. We are alive. We are real. And we’re here waiting for you.</p><p>This is what I think autism societies should be about: not mourning for what never was, but exploration of what is. We need you. We need your help and your understanding. Your world is not very open to us, and we won’t make it without your strong support. Yes, there is tragedy that comes with autism: not because of what we are, but because of the things that happen to us. Be sad about that, if you want to be sad about something. Better than being sad about it, though, get mad about it–and then do something about it. The tragedy is not that we’re here, but that your world has no place for us to be. How can it be otherwise, as long as our own parents are still grieving over having brought us into the world?</p><p>Take a look at your autistic child sometime, and take a moment to tell yourself who that child is not. Think to yourself: “This is not my child that I expected and planned for. This is not the child I waited for through all those months of pregnancy and all those hours of labor. This is not the child I made all those plans to share all those experiences with. That child never came. This is not that child.” Then go do whatever grieving you have to do–away from the autistic child–and start learning to let go.</p><p>After you’ve started that letting go, come back and look at your autistic child again, and say to yourself: “This is not my child that I expected and planned for. This is an alien child who landed in my life by accident. I don’t know who this child is or what it will become. But I know it’s a child, stranded in an alien world, without parents of its own kind to care for it. It needs someone to care for it, to teach it, to interpret and to advocate for it. And because this alien child happened to drop into my life, that job is mine if I want it.”</p><p>If that prospect excites you, then come join us, in strength and determination, in hope and in joy. The adventure of a lifetime is ahead of you.</p><p><em>– Jim Sinclair.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Jim Sinclair</name></author><category term="Autism," /><category term="ASD" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are frequently asked why we decided to support neurodiversity. This speech is one of the answers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/insights/1993/jim_sinclair.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/insights/1993/jim_sinclair.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>